<?xml-model href="rnc_ill-kids.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI>
    <teiHeader/>
    <text xml:id="GuthredsTale">
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Agnes Strickland</docAuthor>
            <docTitle>Historical Tales of Illustrious Children: Guthred's Tale</docTitle>
            <profileDesc>
                    <!-- List of People -->
                    <!--author-->
                <person xml:id="Guthred" sex="male">
                     <persName>Guthred</persName>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Winifred" sex="female">
                    <persName>Winifred</persName>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Ricsig" sex="male">
                    <persName>Ricsig</persName>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Eadred" sex="male">
                    <persName>Eadred</persName>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Selwood" sex="male">
                    <persName>Selwood</persName>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Swindreda" sex="female">
                    <persName>Swindreda</persName>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="AlfredTheGreat" sex="male">
                    <persName>Alfred the Great</persName>
                </person>
            </profileDesc>
        </front>
        <body xml:id="GuthredsTaleStory">
            <title>Guthred's Tale</title>
            <p>
                <s><w type="verb" subtype="action">Will</w> it <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >be</w>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="action">credited</w> by the <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">youthful</w> reader, that in this <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adverb">now</w>
                    <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">free</w> and <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">happy</w> land, slaves <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >were</w>
                    <w type="descLang" subtype="adverb">once</w>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="action">bought</w> and <w type="verb" subtype="action"
                        >sold</w> with as <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">little</w> remorse
                    as cattle <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">are</w> in the present day <w
                        type="verb" subtype="action">transferred</w> from one master to another?</s>
                <s><w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">Strange</w> and <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">revolting</w> as it must <w type="verb" subtype="action"
                        >appear</w> to <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">every</w> lover of his
                    country, such <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w>
                    <w type="descLang" subtype="adverb">once</w> the <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">existing</w> practice, not only in the <w
                        type="descLang" subtype="adjective">remote</w> ages, when the darkness of <w
                        type="descLang" subtype="adjective">heathen</w> barbarism <w type="verb"
                        subtype="action">overshadowed</w> the British islands, but even in the reign
                    of the <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">benevolent</w> and <w
                        type="descLang" subtype="adjective">enlightened</w> Alfred, under whose
                    auspices law and justice <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> established in
                    form so <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">pure</w> and <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">equitable</w>, that <w type="descLang" subtype="adverb"
                        >many</w> of his institutions <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">have been</w>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="action">handed</w> down to us from our ancestors as the
                        <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">noblest</w> legacy in their power to
                        <w type="verb" subtype="action">bestow</w>.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>Civilization, it <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> true, <w type="verb"
                        subtype="action">made</w> a <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">great</w>
                    progress during the era of this <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective"
                        >accomplished</w> monarch, but he <w type="verb" subtype="action">had</w> so
                        <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">many</w> difficulties to <w
                        type="verb" subtype="action">contend</w> with, and so <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">many</w> prejudices to <w type="verb" subtype="action"
                        >overcome</w>, that it <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> not to <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="action">wondered</w> if <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">some</w> abuses <w type="verb" subtype="action"
                        >remain</w>
                    <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">unreformed</w>, and, among others, this
                        <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">inhuman</w> traffic.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>There <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w>
                    <w type="descLang" subtype="adverb">few</w> occupiers of land in those days who
                        <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> not <w type="verb" subtype="action"
                        >possessed</w> of thralls, or <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective"
                        >domestic</w> slaves, who <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="action">distinguished</w> from the <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">hired</w> servants, by the <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">degrading</w> badge of an <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">iron</w> collar, on which <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">was</w>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="action">inscribed</w> the name of the <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">hapless</w> bondman, with the notification that he <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> the purchased or the born thrall,
                    whichever it might happen to <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w>, of such a
                    person, of such a place.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The tale I <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">am</w> about to <w type="verb"
                        subtype="action">relate</w>, which <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="action">founded</w> on an <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">authentic</w>
                    <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">historical</w> fact of this nature, <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> an <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">illustrative</w> sketch of the manners and customs of
                    the Anglo Saxons and Danes, during that <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective"
                        >glorious</w> period of our annals, the age of <name who="AlfredTheGreat"
                        >Alfred the Great</name>, in whose <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective"
                        >reign</w> its events took place.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>One <w type="descLang" subtype="adverb">bright</w>
                    <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">autumnal</w> morning, about eleven
                    o'clock, the hour at which our Saxon ancestors <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adverb">usually</w>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="action">took</w> their <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">principal</w> meal, just as the family and serving-folk
                    of the Saxon franklin,<gloss>A Saxon Freeholder, or gentleman, who possessed of
                        one or more hydes of land. A hyde contains 100 acres.</gloss>
                    <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name>, <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="action">seating</w> themselves at the <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adverb">well</w>
                    <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">covered</w> board, a <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">loud</w> barking from the watch dogs that <w type="verb"
                        subtype="action">guarded</w> the homestead, <w type="verb" subtype="action"
                        >answered</w> by the <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">low</w>, but <w
                        type="descLang" subtype="adverb">more</w>
                    <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">angry</w>, growling of the household curs
                        <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">under</w> the table, <w type="verb"
                        subtype="action">announced</w> the approach of strangers.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Selwood">Selwood</name>, who <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w>
                    beginning to <w type="verb" subtype="action">carve</w> for his household, <w
                        type="verb" subtype="action">paused</w> to <w type="verb" subtype="action"
                        >listen</w>, and <w type="verb" subtype="action">grasped</w> his <w
                        type="descLang" subtype="adjective">huge</w> knife with a <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">firmer</w> hold, as though he <w type="verb"
                        subtype="action">meditated</w>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="action">using</w> it as a weapon of defence in case of
                        <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">approaching</w> danger.</s>
                <s>His serving-folk, who, according to the custom of those days, <w type="verb"
                        subtype="action">sat</w> at the same table with their master, but <w
                        type="descLang" subtype="adjective">below</w> the salt, <w type="verb"
                        subtype="action">started</w> from their seats on the <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adjective">rough</w>
                    <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">oaken</w> benches that <w type="verb"
                        subtype="action">surrounded</w> the <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective"
                        >lower</w> end of the board, and <w type="verb" subtype="action">laid</w>
                    hand on scythes, flails, or <w type="descLang" subtype="adjective">reaping</w>
                    hooks, <w type="verb" subtype="action">exclaiming</w> in alarm, <q who="text"
                        >The Danes be upon us!</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>So contiguous indeed <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> the town of
                    Whitingham, near which the farm and homestead of <name who="Selwood"
                        >Selwood</name>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> situated, to the Danelagh, or Danish
                    colony that had established itself in great power in Northumberland, that
                    perpetual fear existed in the minds of the franklin and his household, lest
                    their dangerous neighbours should at any time think proper to break the hollow
                    truce then subsisting between the Saxons and Danes, and pay him one of their
                    predatory visits.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The Danish settlements were, in fact, neither more nor less than so <w
                        type="descLang" subtype="adverb">many</w> formidable hordes of rapacious
                    banditti, always ready to give and take offence, and on the look-out for
                    plunder.</s>
                <s>They <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> a cruel, faithless race, in whose
                    promises no reliance could <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> placed, and
                    whose only occupation consisted in rapine and deeds of blood.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The industrious habits and peaceful employments of the Saxons, who having become
                    naturalized to the soil, had abandoned the warlike manners of their fierce
                    ancestors for the useful pursuits of the shepherd and the husbandman, were
                    sorely interrupted by the incursions and ravages of the <emph>black
                        strangers,</emph> as the invading Danes <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >were</w> emphatically styled, from the sable hue of the vessels which
                    brought this unwelcome swarm of northern robbers to the shores of England, where
                    they first arrived in the reign of Egbert, and from that time contrived to
                    obtain a footing in the country, and <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">being</w>
                    yearly reinforced with fresh bands of adventurers from the coasts of Denmark and
                    Norway, they continued to gain strength, and at length establishing themselves,
                    side by side as it were, by the Saxons, rendered themselves the terror of the
                    peacefully disposed, and the scourge of the whole country.</s>
                <s><q who="text">They <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">are</w> always before us,</q>
                    says the Saxon Chronicler; <q who="text">we always see the horizon reddened with
                        flame, we always hear the tramp of war.</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>At the period of Alfred's accession to the throne, nine pitched battles were
                    fought in one year, between the English and the Danes, besides skirmishes and
                    private conflicts innumerable.</s>
                <s>Sometimes the Danes <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> defeated, but after
                    each reverse they appeared to redouble their activity, and actually increased in
                    power.</s>
                <s><q who="text">If thirty thousand <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">are</w> slain in
                        one day,</q> said the despairing Saxons, <q who="text">there will <w
                            type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> double that number in the field
                        to-morrow.</q></s>
                <s>Sometimes, when the Saxons found themselves unable to cope with their formidable
                    opponents, they <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> unwise enough to
                    endeavour to purchase a shameful peace with gold; but the bribe <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">was</w> no sooner in the possession of the greedy
                    barbarians, than they violated the dear-bought treaty, and committed all sorts
                    of violence, for the sake of extorting fresh sums of money.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The appearance of a Danish holda, or chief, approaching the homestead of <name
                        who="Selwood">Selwood</name>, though only attended by a boy of tender years,
                    who <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> leading a brace of wolf-hounds in a
                    leash, <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> sufficient to spread dismay
                    through the dwelling.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>There <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> an immediate consultation between
                        <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name> and his wife, <name who="Winifred"
                        >Winifred</name>, as to whether they should treat the unwelcome visitor as
                    an enemy, by refusing him admittance into the homestead, which doubtless he
                    approached in the quality of a spy, or, as he came in a peaceful guise, choose
                    the alternative of conciliating his friendship, by receiving him as a guest.</s>
                <s><q who="text">He <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> a stranger, and as it <w
                            type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> meal time it would <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">be</w> churlish to deny him entrance,</q> said <name
                        who="Selwood">Selwood</name>, <q who="text">albeit, I would with greater
                        pleasure invite a wolf to <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> my
                        dinner-guest.</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">The wolf would <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> the less
                        dangerous visitor of the two, I trow,</q> said the careful <name
                        who="Winifred">Winifred</name>, pocketing, as she spoke, the silver ladle,
                    with which she <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> preparing to help herself
                    from the bowl of plum porridge which stood before her.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Swindreda">Swindedra</name>, her niece, <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">was</w> in the very act of whisking away the porridge, also
                    muttering as she did so, <q who="text">that she had never taken the trouble of
                        compounding such a dainty dish to tickle the palate of a Danish raven, for
                        whom swine's flesh and barley broth <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w>
                        more than good enough,</q> when the holda, whose quick eye had caught the
                    manoeuvre as he entered, called out, <q who="text">Holla there, maiden! <w
                            type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> it your Saxon fashion to remove the
                        best part of the cheer when a stranger surprises you at your meals? Now,
                        that is the very dish whereof I mean to eat.</q></s>
                <s>So saying, he snatched it from her hand, and placing himself in the seat of
                    honour at the table, he took a horn spoon from one of the serving men, and
                    devoured the contents in a trice, with the exception of a small portion, which
                    he left at the bottom of the vessel, and handed over his shoulder with a
                    patronizing air to his youthful atttendant, who stood behind his stool, still
                    holding the hounds in leash.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, for so the Danish chief called the boy,
                    received this mark of favour with a sullen and reluctant air, and maintained a
                    proud, cold demeanour, to the astonishment of the Saxon servants, who knew, from
                    the iron collar, and other unequivocal badges of slavery about his person, that
                    the boy <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> in a more degraded condition
                    than themselves, <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">being</w> the purchased thrall
                    or slave of <name who="Ricsig">Ricsig</name> the Dane.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Ricsig">Riscig</name> appeared by no means an unkind master, for he
                    took some pains to supply both the cravings of his hounds, and the probable
                    wants of his young slave, with the choisest provisions on the franklin's table,
                    without paying the slightest attention to the feelings of the indignant host and
                    mortified household; but it <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> thus that
                    the insolent northmen conducted themselves when they entered the dwellings of
                    the peaceful Saxons, who very seldom ventured to remonstrate with their
                    unwelcome guests, lest they should draw upon themselves a still more formidable
                    visitation in the shape of fire and sword, taking it for granted, that where one
                    Dane made himself visible, ten more at least <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >were</w> lurking within call, in readiness to espouse any quarrel in which
                    he might involve himself.</s>
                <s>It <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> this apprehension that withheld <name
                        who="Selwood">Selwood</name> and his men from expelling the insolent
                    intruder, who, after astonishing all parties with his voracity, laid hands on a
                    curiously carved drinking horn, which <name who="Swindreda">Swindreda</name>, in
                    her anxiety to secure the plum porridge, had forgotten to remove, and calling
                    for metheglin, emptied and replenished it so often with this heady beverage,
                    that he soon got into high humour, and after bestowing great commendations on
                    the beauty of the horn, he, instead of taking possession of it by sticking it
                    into his girdle, beside his battle axe, as too <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adverb">many</w> of his countrymen in such case would have done,
                    actually offered to purchase it of <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name>.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">It <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> the horn of my
                        fathers,</q> said the Saxon, <q who="text">and if I sell it to thee, it
                        shall <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> for naught less than gold.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Gold,</q> echoed the Dane scornfully, <q who="text">dost think I am
                        a Saxon monk, to carry coined pieces in my girdle? My wealth,</q> added he,
                    significantly grasping the handle of his battle axe, <q who="text">is in the
                        purses of my enemies.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">That <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> to say,</q> rejoined
                        <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name>, <q who="text">that you mean to carry off
                        my cunningly-wrought drinking horn, as a reward for my hospitality to thee
                        and thy thrall.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Said I not that I would purchase it of thee?</q> demanded <name
                        who="Ricsig">Ricsig</name>.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Ay, but what art thou willing to give me in exchange?</q> said the
                    franklin.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Thou shalt choose, whether thou wilt have my hound, Snath; his
                        fleet-footed companion, Wilbrach; or my thrall, <name who="Guthred"
                            >Guthred</name>,</q> replied the holda; <q who="text">all three of these
                        have displeased me this morning: the two first led me hither on a false
                        track of deer, and the latter perversely refused to eat of the food which I
                        flung to him even now from my own trencher; so choose between them, for the
                        horn <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> now more precious in my sight
                        than either.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Selwood">Selwood</name>'s judgment <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >was</w> assisted in making his election by a hint from the most prudent of
                    housewives, the thrifty <name who="Winifred">Winifred</name>, who whispered in
                    his ear, <q who="text">Curs have we more than plenty, master mind, for they only
                        encourage the serving folk in idle pastimes, and serve as a cloak to conceal
                        their wastery when the oaten cakes wax mouldy, or the meat <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">is</w> too fat for their liking: but we <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">are</w> in need of a boy to tend the swine and sheep,
                        and to do <w type="descLang" subtype="adverb">many</w> other things, so
                        choose the young thrall, who <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> a stout
                        healthy lad, and if discreetly trained, will do us worthy service both in
                        and out of doors.</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>No sooner had <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name> signified his choice to <name
                        who="Ricsig">Ricsig</name>, than the barter was completed by the Dane taking
                    the boy by the collar, and transferring him to his new master in these
                    words:</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">I, <name who="Ricsig">Ricsig</name>, give to thee, <name
                            who="Selwood">Selwood</name>, <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> my
                        slave, to <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> thy thrall for
                    ever.</q></s>
                <s> Then tucking the drinking horn into his belt, he strode out of the Saxon
                    homestead, whistling to his dogs to follow.</s>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> flung himself on the ground and wept.</s>
                <s><q who="text">Nay, cheer up, my dainty bird,</q> said <name who="Winifred"
                        >Winifred</name> compassionately, <q who="text">thou wilt have no cause to
                        lament thy change of masters, I promise, if thou wilt <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">be</w> a dutiful and painstaking slave.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> redoubled his tears, and at length sobbed
                    audibly.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Thou didst not seem so loving to thy Danish master that thou
                        shouldst bewail a separation from him thus passionately,</q> observed <name
                        who="Swindreda">Swindreda</name>.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Loving to him !</q> echoed the boy indignantly, his large dark eyes
                    flashing through his streaming tears as he spoke, <q who="text">loving unto a
                        Dane,to my born foe?</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Why then, thou shouldst rejoice in thy change of thraldom,</q> said
                        <name who="Winifred">Winifred</name>.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">It <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> for my thraldom that I
                        weep,</q> replied <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, <q who="text">for I <w
                            type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> free born, and <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">am</w> no more disposed to serve a Saxon churl than to
                            <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> the slave of a Danish robber.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">High words do oft proceed from an empty stomach,</q> observed his
                    new master, sternly; <q who="text">but I counsel thee, boy, to stint thy
                        perverse prating, which can answer no other purpose than to bring the thong
                        across thy shoulders.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Thy women folk pestered me with questions, or I had only wept in
                        silence,</q> replied <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> scornfully.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Women folk, indeed!</q> cried <name who="Swindreda"
                        >Swindreda</name>, giving him a smart box on the years. <q who="text">I'll
                        teach thee to use more respectful language of thy betters, and let thee
                        know, withal, that it <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> not the
                        business of a thrall to weep, but to work.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">It <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> well for thee that thou
                        art a women, though an ill-favoured one, or I had returned thy hard blow
                        with usury,</q> retorted <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, clenching his
                    hand.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Swindreda">Swindreda</name>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> preparing to inflict summary vengeance
                    on the imprudent railer, but <name who="Winifred">Winifred</name> humanely
                    interposed to prevent the visitation of her wrathful displeasure, by sending her
                    to feed the poultry, while she herself proceeded to instruct the newly-purchased
                    slave in some of the household duties which he would <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">be</w> required to perform.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>On the following day, <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name> ordered his shepherd,
                    his neatherd, swineherd, and wood cutter, to put him in the way of becoming a
                    useful assistant in their several vocations, but <name who="Guthred"
                        >Guthred</name>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> sullen and refractory with the men, and
                    rebellious to the women; the authority of both was, of course, enforced by harsh
                    measures, and the young thrall <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> compelled
                    to yield reluctant obedience after repeated chastisements; thus entailing upon
                    himself severe personal sufferings in addition to the hardships of
                    servitude.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>His foreign accent and complexion, so different from that of his Saxon masters,
                    had obtained for <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> the name of the Son of the
                    stranger, a designation by no means likely to improve his condition among the
                    Saxon serfs and ceorls, who had suffered too deeply from the aggressions of the
                    Danes to <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> disposed to regard any foreigner
                    with favourable eyes.</s>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> exposed to <w type="descLang"
                        subtype="adverb">many</w> taunts from the serving folk, on account of his
                    persisting in wearing his dark hair, flowing on his shoulders, in its natural
                    length, and rich luxuriance of spiral ringlets.</s>
                <s>Long hair <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> only worn by persons of noble
                    or royal birth; and though <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> had refused to
                    declare his birth and lineage, he assumed this envied distinction, to the
                    infinite displeasure of his associates in labour, who had more than once seized
                    upon him, and, forcibly shorn these aristocratical honours from the proud head
                    of the youthful slave; and when their mistress interposed her authority to
                    prevent a repetition of the outrage, they vented their spleen in addressing him
                    by the title of <q who="text">high and mighty thane,</q> whenever they required
                    him to perform the most servile offices.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> once smiled in scorn at the insult, and told
                    his tormentors, <q who="text">that, like ignorant churls as they were, they
                        addressed him by a title far below that which <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">was</w> his due.</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>But this intimation drew upon him a torrent of such bitter mockery, that from
                    that time forward he preserved a contemptuous silence when assailed by the
                    taunts of the serfs.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The long weary winter, the hardest time of bondage that <name who="Guthred"
                        >Guthred</name> had yet sustained, passed away, and the sweet season of
                    spring once more clothed the Northumbrian fields with verdure, and enamelled the
                    pastures with flowers.</s>
                <s>It <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> some relief to the persecuted thrall
                    of <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name>, when he <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >was</w> separated from the rude churls, and employed in the solitary office
                    of keeping the sheep on the extensive downs, heath-clad hills, or pleasant
                    meads; but lovely as the scenes were, the sick heart of the young exile fondly
                    yearned after the wild and rugged scenery of the far distant land of his
                    fathers, Those eternal forests of sombre pines and chains of barren mountains,
                    he preferred to the oaken glades, and the verdant hills and dales of the fertile
                    island of the west, of which he had become an unwilling denizen.</s>
                <s>The land <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> indeed fair; but to him who has
                    neither sympathies nor companionship, the most smiling landscape becomes a
                    dreary desert.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>Had <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> ever felt the divine influence of
                    religion, he might have supported his early sorrows with resignation; for,
                    though companionless, he would have known that he <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">was</w> not alone, that he <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >was</w> upheld by the everlasting arm of his Father and his God, and would
                    have learned in every dispensation, however afflicting, to recognise his hand;
                    but he had <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">been</w> born in a heathen land, and
                    the light of Christianity had never dawned on his benighted mind.</s>
                <s><name who="Selwood">Selwood</name> and his household, indeed, were, nominally
                    speaking, Christians; but their creed and practice <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">were</w> so corrupted, and interwoven with pagan
                    superstitions and idolatries, that they <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w>
                    scarcely in less darkness than the young heathen, whose aversion to their mode
                    of worship excited their anger and contempt.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> only disliked their mode of worship because it
                        <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> theirs, for he had never deigned to
                    examine into the nature of their belief; from his own he drew no consolation; it
                        <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> made up of shadowy recollections of
                    gigantic idols, before whose images he had <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >been</w> taught by his father to bow the knee in the depth of gloomy
                    groves.</s>
                <s>His remembrance recalled their terrific forms, but of their attributes he
                    retained no idea, though he <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> occasionally
                    wont to revoke them as the avengers of his wrongs, when injured by his Danish or
                    Saxon task-masters.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>One day, when a war of words between him and <name who="Swindreda"
                        >Swindreda</name> had ended in his stubborn refusal to draw water at her
                    behest, and a severe corporeal punishment from the franklin had compelled him to
                    submission, he proceeded to the sheepfold with a swelling heart, and throwing
                    himself upon the ground, called aloud upon Thor and Woden to bring destruction
                    upon <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name> and his whole household.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>He paused, partly exhausted by the violence of his transport of fury, and partly,
                    perhaps, from a sort of undefined expectation of receiving an answer to his
                    vengeful invocation.</s>
                <s>It came; but neither in the uproar of the elements, nor the rush of the chariot
                    wheels of the destroyer careering through the air; but in the soft low voice of
                    compassionate expostulation.</s>
                <s>He raised his face from the earth, and perceived a stranger beside him, whose
                    majestic form and mild countenance impressed him with the idea that he <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> a <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >being</w> of a different order from the rude and savage men with whom he
                    had been accustomed to associate.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Unhappy boy!</q> said the stranger, <q who="text">upon whom hast
                        thou called?</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">On the gods of my fathers,</q> replied <name who="Guthred"
                        >Guthred</name>.</s>
                <s><q who="text">Those whom mine own people worshipped within the strong circles of
                        their power, and on whose rough-hewn altars my father <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">was</w> wont to pour forth the blood of his slaughtered
                        foes.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The stranger shuddered.</s>
                <s><q who="text">Alas, poor child!</q> said he,<q who="text"> and canst thou believe
                        that such inhuman sacrifices could <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w>
                        acceptable to the beneficent Creator of this beautiful world, which he has
                        formed for the happiness and delight of his creatures, whom he has commanded
                        to love one another, and to worship him in the beauty of holiness, not with
                        polluted hands and bloody rites?</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> looked perplexed, for the language of the
                    stranger <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> incomprehensible to him.</s>
                <s>At length he said, <q who="text">It <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> to
                        Thor and Woden these sacrifices were offered by my father. To them the
                        savour of the blood <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> sweet; for they
                        are called the Destroyer and the Avenger. Oh that they would bring fire and
                        sword upon the homestead of <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name>, the
                        Saxon!</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Thy guilty prayer <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> such as
                        might indeed <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> expected from the lips
                        of a benighted worshipper of the powers of evil,</q> replied the stranger:
                        <q who="text">but know, my son, that in offering homage to Thor and Woden
                        you <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">are</w> acting in direct rebellion to
                        the Lord and Giver of Life, and the Supreme Ruler of the Universe, and <w
                            type="verb" subtype="beVerb">are</w> provoking his wrath to visit you
                        with those maledictions which you impiously call down upon your enemies.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">I cannot <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> more wretched than
                        I am,</q> replied <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, <q who="text">or
                        suffer greater reverses, for I, who <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w>
                        born a prince, <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">am</w> now the slave of
                        slaves.</q></s>
                <s>He bowed his face once more upon the earth, and lifting up his voice, wept
                    aloud.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The stranger allowed his passionate grief to vent itself, without interruption,
                    for some moments, and then drawing <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> to him, he
                    addressed him in words of sympathy and encouragement.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The soothing tones, and language of compassion and tenderness, <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">were</w> new to the ears of the youthful slave; but they
                    made their way to his heart, and melted the obdurate pride which had always
                    prompted him to oppose violence to violence, and to return wrong for wrong, and
                    with the confiding frankness of childhood, he flung himself into the arms of his
                    unknown comforter, and wetted his bosom with his tears.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">You say you <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> born a
                        prince,</q> observed the stranger, after a pause. <q who="text">Whence come
                        you?</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">From the land of the dark forest and the snowclad mountain,</q>
                    replied <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, with a flushing cheek and kindling
                    eye, <q who="text">from Lethra,<gloss>Lethra, a province of ancient
                            Sweden.Palgrave.</gloss> where my father, Hardacanute, <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">was</w> a king and a warrior: and I, his heir, was
                        brought up on the knees of the valiant, served by the hands of the noble,
                        and lulled to sleep by the songs of the bards, who told of the deeds of my
                        great forefather, the mighty Odin, whose coal-black eye, and raven hair,
                        they said resembled mine. But Halfdane and Hubba, the fierce sons of Regner
                        Lodbrok, came, like a wintry torrent, spreading woe and desolation through
                        my native Lethra, and having slain my sire, and burned his cities, they bore
                        me, a helpless sorrowing child, from the place of my birth, and the kingdom
                        I should have inherited, to their own detested land of Denmark, where
                        Halfdane, the eldest of the fierce brethren, the same who now awes the
                        trembling Northumbrian Saxons, with the terror of his name, this Halfdane, I
                        say, exchanged me with his hunting companion, <name who="Ricsig"
                            >Ricsig</name>, for a wolf-hound, and <name who="Ricsig">Ricsig</name>,
                        in his turn, trucked me away to <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name>, the
                        Saxon, for a paltry drinking horn, as though I had <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">been</w> a thing of nought, a senseless utensil, or a
                        beast of the field.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">And how have you <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">been</w> treated
                        in the household of the Saxon franklin?</q> demanded the stranger.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">With hard words and harder blows,</q> returned <name who="Guthred"
                        >Guthred</name>, indignantly, <q who="text">have I <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">been</w> driven forth to the performance of vile
                        offices. A hewer of wood and a drawer of water have I <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">been</w> to sordid household queens, and a drudge in
                        field and fold to the base churls who served my Saxon master, and with their
                        injurious usage increased the bitterness of a prince's bondage. Pity have I
                        had from no one save from thyself,</q> added he, in a softened tone, on
                    perceiving the kindly drops which the tale of his sorrows had drawn from the
                    benign eyes of the stranger.</s>
                <s><q who="text">And who art thou that weepest for the woes of an alien and a slave?
                        Surely thou belongest not to the race of the unfeeling Saxon, or the savage
                        Dane!</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">My name <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w>
                        <name who="Eadred">Eadred</name>,</q> replied the stranger, <q who="text"
                        >and, though of Saxon lineage, I <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">am</w> not,
                        I trust, unfeeling, but the servant of One who <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">is</w> the friend of the friendless; who hath, in his
                        Divine wisdom, for some good purpose, doubtless, brought thee hither, and
                        hath sent me to thee with tidings of comfort.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>In reply to <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>'s eager inquiries, <name
                        who="Eadred">Eadred</name> proceeded to reveal to him that God, of whose
                    name and attributes he had hitherto remained in profound ignorance.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> listened patiently, for the manners of the
                    eloquent speaker had that mild persuasive charm which appeals resistlessly to
                    every heart.</s>
                <s>He listened attentively, for the subject <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w>
                    one of powerful interest, conveyed as it was, in the impressive, but sublime
                    simplicity of truth.</s>
                <s>He listened with delight, for the pure doctrines of Christianity <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">were</w> glad tidings to the desolate, heartbroken captive,
                    to whom they offered better hopes of happiness in a future state of existence
                    than the savage pleasure of quaffing mead and beer from the skulls of
                    slaughtered foes, in the joyless valhalla, or heaven, of Scandinavian mythology
                    ; and <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, the lineal descendant of the renowned
                    Odin, who <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> honoured as one of the
                    mightiest of the northern divinities, became a convert to the Christian
                    faith.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Eadred">Eadred</name> frequently sought his young friend in the lonely
                    pastures where he kept the franklin's sheep, for the purpose of imparting to his
                    powerful, but uncultivated mind, the advantages of that learning which he <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> ably qualified to communicate; for
                        <name who="Eadred">Eadred</name>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> a Saxon monk of distinguished talents
                    and eminent acquirements, who resided in a neighbouring convent, and employed
                    himself in works of mercy and charity, and experienced a pure delight in
                    diffusing the light of knowledge and religion, in succouring the distrest, and
                    comforting the sorrowful.</s>
                <s>As his pupil, the hitherto fierce and intractable <name who="Guthred"
                        >Guthred</name>, became mild, reflective, and intelligent, the hours that he
                    had <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">been</w> accustomed to waste in vain
                    repining, listless inanity, or stormy bursts of passion, <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">were</w> now employed in study or heavenward meditation,
                    which enabled him to correct the defects of his character, and to endure with
                    resignation and fortitude the toil and persecution he occasionally had to
                    bear.</s>
                <s>He no longer regretted the loss of power and dominions, for his mind <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> to him a kingdom, and the intercourse
                    he enjoyed with the pious and accomplished <name who="Eadred">Eadred</name>, he
                    would not have resigned for all the riches the world could bestow.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>Books <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> then rare possessions, confined to
                    the libraries of convents, and but seldom to <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >be</w> met with in the cabinets of monarchs, yet <name who="Guthred"
                        >Guthred</name>, through the favour of his learned friend, <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">was</w> seldom without a roll of illuminated MS. in his
                    bosom wherewith to beguile his solitary hours, and sweeten the labours of the
                    day.</s>
                <s>Nor <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> his studies confined to
                    book-learning alone; he became an observer of the face of nature, and the
                    characters of his fellow men.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Knowledge <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> power,</q> Lord
                    Bacon, in later times, has said, and the enslaved <name who="Guthred"
                        >Guthred</name>, the servant of servants, as he, in the bitterness of his
                    soul had aptly styled himself, acquired with his growing wisdom such influence
                    over the minds of those around him, that he became as it <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">were</w> the oracle of the household and neighbourhood.</s>
                <s>His sayings <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> quoted, his advice
                    solicited, and his judgment appealed to, in all cases where parties <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> at issue or difficulties occurred.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>Like the captive Hebrew in the house of the Egyptian lord, every thing appeared
                    to prosper with him.</s>
                <s>The flocks and herds of <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name> increased, and his
                    crops <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> more abundant; plenty <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> without, and peace <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">was</w> within the dwelling, where the master mind of the
                    young slave, as he approached to manhood, manifested its superiority over the
                    ignorant serfs and ceorls, by the improvements he suggested, and the good order
                    he contributed to establish and maintain.</s>
                <s>But these days of tranquillity <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> not to
                    last.</s>
                <s>The growing wealth of <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name> excited the cupidity of
                    the Danish hordes in the neighbourhood, who, taking advantage of a dispute among
                    themselves, in which they pretended that the inhabitants of Whitingham had
                    interfered, poured down upon the devoted Saxons, plundered their dwellings,
                    drove away their flocks and herds, and put every man to the sword who dared to
                    offer resistance to their lawless rapacity.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>When <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, who had <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >been</w> sent by his master on a message of trust, to receive a sum of
                    money from the monks of Lindisfairne, for a drove of fat bullocks, returned to
                    Whitingham, he found the lands harried, the flocks and herds gone, and his
                    mistress sitting on her ruined hearth-stone, weeping over the mangled corse of
                    the murdered franklin, her husband; deserted by serfs and thralls, they having
                    taken advantage of her calamity to provide for their own interests; and even
                    abandoned by her niece and sole relative, <name who="Swindreda"
                    >Swindreda</name>, that damsel having taken a fancy to one of the Danish
                    plunderers, with whom she departed to the Danelagh.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>It <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> then that <name who="Guthred"
                        >Guthred</name> found occasion for the exercise of those principles of
                    Christian benevolence, which had <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">been</w>
                    inculcated by the pious <name who="Eadred">Eadred</name>.</s>
                <s>That beloved friend <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> indeed lost to him,
                    for the convent had <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">been</w> plundered and
                    burned by the ferocious Danes, and no trace of the monks or their peaceful and
                    useful occupations remained; but the precepts of <name who="Eadred"
                        >Eadred</name> remained indelibly impressed on tablets of <name
                        who="Guthred">Guthred</name>'s heart, whose first impulse <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">was</w> to bestow such consolation and assistance as it <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> in his power to offer to the
                    broken-hearted widow.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>Poor <name who="Winifred">Winifred</name>, who had not expected to receive that
                    sympathy and succour from the foreign thrall which had <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">been</w> denied by those from whom she had most reason to
                    expect it, lifted up her voice, and blessed him with the blessing of the widow
                    and the destitute.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>When <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> had consigned the bleeding remains of his
                    murdered master to a grave, which he dug for him beneath the umbrage of one of
                    the noble elms that had formerly overshadowed the low roofed but pleasant
                    dwelling, he conducted his sorrowing mistress to a miserable shieling, or
                    cottage, that had escaped the general conflagration that had consumed house,
                    barns, and cattle sheds; but, notwithstanding all his care and consideration,
                        <name who="Winifred">Winifred</name> must have perished of want, had it not
                        <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">been</w> for the sum which <name
                        who="Guthred">Guthred</name> had received from the monks of Lindisfairne for
                    his deceased master, and which he now, with scrupulous fidelity, delivered to
                    the astonished widow.</s>
                <s><q who="text">Keep it, my son,</q> said she, <q who="text">and use it for our
                        mutual benefit; surely it will <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> safer
                        in thy hands than in mine, and will prosper under thy management.</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> applied this little store with such prudence
                    and success, and used such unremitting personal exertions, in improving the
                    widow's mite, that, by degrees, her desolate dwelling began to wear an air of
                    comfort, and at length she found herself the mistress of a productive little
                    farm, with kine, sheep, swine, and poultry, sufficient for her use.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, who found a sweet satisfaction in
                    administering to her comforts, was repaid a thousand fold by the tender
                    affection with which he <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> regarded by the
                    grateful widow, who <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> to him as a
                    mother.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>Northumbria continued the theatre of petty intestine wars, not only between its
                    rival population of Saxons and Danes, but of fierce dissensions among the Danes
                    themselves, who, since the death of Halfdane, their leader, and the overthrow
                    and slaughter of his brother Hubba (the sons of Begner Lodbrok, and chief
                    governors of the Danelagh), had not <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">been</w>
                    able to agree among themselves respecting the choice of a successor to the
                    sovereign authority, not one of the royal line of Odin remaining among their
                    hordes.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>But the wars and rumours of wars, which spread desolation, bloodshed, and terror,
                    through country and town of this unfortunate district, disquieted not the humble
                    cottage where the widowed <name who="Winifred">Winifred</name> and her thrall,
                        <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, found shelter and contentment.</s>
                <s>There <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> moments, perhaps, when <name
                        who="Guthred">Guthred</name> felt disposed to regret that his talents and
                    acquirements had no nobler sphere for their exercise than the occupations of a
                    shepherd or husbandman; but then the reflection that he was engaged in the
                    virtuous performance of the duties of that state to which it had pleased his
                    heavenly Father to call him, checked the rebellious suggestions of ambition and
                    discontent, and he returned to his toils with the pious conviction, that if it
                        <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> the will of God that the hand that
                    ought to have wielded a sceptre should <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w>
                    doomed to guide a plough in an obscure corner of a foreign land, it <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> right that it should <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">be</w> so.</s>
                <s>But other things <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> in store for the royal
                    orphan, who had <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">been</w> prepared and fitted in
                    the school of adversity for a better inheritance than that which was his
                    birthright.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>One morning, on returning from the field to breakfast, he found <name
                        who="Winifred">Winifred</name> attired in her best black kirtle, surcoat,
                    and hood, and busily engaged in smoothing, with an iron, the plaits and coarse
                    embroidery on the back and shoulder of his sabbath supertunic, which garment <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> made of coarse home-spun white linen,
                    precisely similar in all respects to the long open frocks worn in the present
                    day by waggoners. <q who="text">How now, my good mother,</q> said <name
                        who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, with a smile, for by that endearing title he
                    had long <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">been</w> accustomed to address her, <q
                        who="text">what makes you so full of business with my best parelling to-day?
                        To-morrow <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> neither Sunday nor a
                        saint's day, you know.</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">No matter, my son,</q> replied <name who="Winifred"
                    >Winifred</name>, <q who="text">there <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> to
                            <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> a goodly show and a great
                        festival at Oswindune, for the Danes and Saxons <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">are</w> tired of their quarrels and evil doing, and
                        have resolved to choose a king of Northumberland by mutual agreement, this
                        blessed day, to put an end to bloodshed and deadly debate; and Ulph, the
                        miller, of Whitingham, who hath just told me the glad tidings, hath promised
                        to lend us one of his grist carts, and the old pied mare, that we may go
                        thither like our neighbours to view the joyful sight.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">My dear mother,</q> said <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, <q
                        who="text">those will be wisest who keep at home on such a day, especially
                        women folk and Saxons, believe me; for such a meeting <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">is</w> far more likely to create deadly debate than to
                        end them, and then the sword and the battleaxe will <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">be</w> the umpires that will decide any quarrel that
                        may arise; for as to the Danes and Saxons agreeing in any thing, much less
                        on a matter of such importance as the choice of a king, it <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">is</w> not to <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w>
                        expected ; therefore, their assembly will only <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">be</w> the cause of bloodshed, so, dear mother, <w
                            type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> persuaded by me, and go not thither
                        to-day.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Nay! nay ! my son, thou art, for once, mistaken in thy
                        judgment,</q> said <name who="Winifred">Winifred</name>, <q who="text">for
                        our people and the Danes have already agreed in the wise determination of
                        leaving the nomination of their mutual governor to our good king Alfred and
                        the pious bishop of Lindisfairne, who will both <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">be</w> present, they say; and if we go not to Oswindune
                        to-day, we may never again enjoy the felicity of looking upon such a king
                        and such a prelate.</q></s>
                <s><q who="text">Besides,</q> added she, on observing that <name who="Guthred"
                        >Guthred</name>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> about to offer some fresh objection, <q
                        who="text">I <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">am</w> resolved on going,
                        whether you approve of it or not; for I have lived under the shadow of this
                        poor shieling in the depth of a wood, lo! this seven years, and seen neither
                        feast nor festival since the day of my sad widowhood, and 'tis time now, I
                        wot, that I should enjoy some pastime; so, if thou likest not to drive the
                        pied mare, I will e'n ask Ulph the miller to give me a seat in his great
                        meal waggon, with the rest of the gossips and neighbours, who <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">are</w> going to see this blessed sight.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>Well, mother,<q who="text"/> replied <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, <q
                        who="text">if you <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">are</w> thus bent on
                        going, I <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">am</w> your thrall, you know, and
                        bound to do your bidding; and even <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w>
                        that not the case, I would attend you for love's sake, especially as there
                        may <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> danger.</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Winifred">Winifred</name>, in high good humour at having carried her
                    point, packed up a store of oaten cakes, cheese, and dried mutton, to which she
                    added a bottle of her best metheglin, as a store for the journey, while <name
                        who="Guthred">Guthred</name> combed his long dark ringlets, washed his face
                    and hands, and donned his snowy super-tunic and fox-fur cap, in readiness to
                    attend his mistress.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The roads <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> like all roads in those days,
                    of a very rough description, full of deep ruts and holes, here and there mended
                    with rough blocks of stone, or the trunks of trees laid side by side.</s>
                <s>The grist cart <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> an uncouth, and what <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> worse, a jolting conveyance, and the
                    miller's old pied mare a sorry jade; nevertheless, the day <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">was</w> so fine, and they met with such abundance of good
                    company on the road, that both mistress and slave <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">were</w> in the best possible spirits, and <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">were</w> willing to overlook all inconveniences, and only
                    to dwell on the agreeable part of the journey.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>When they drew near the scene of action, <name who="Winifred">Winifred</name>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> greatly amused by examining the various
                    cavalcades of Danish holdas in their burnished armour, over which flowed silken
                    mantles, and their long red tresses braided with gems and threads of gold, for
                    the Danes, notwithstanding their ferocious and barbarous manners, affected great
                    nicety in dress, and <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> the fops of the
                    ninth century; the gallantly armed and mounted Saxon thanes, with their courtly
                    yet warlike bearing, and festal array, each attended by a train of martial
                    followers; the bands of wealthy franklins, and sturdy ceorls, with their wives
                    and families; even the poor serfs and craftsmen of low degree <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">were</w> flocking from all directions to the spot.</s>
                <s>Besides these <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> glee men and harps;
                    travelling jugglers with apes and bears; morrice dancers; and itinerants of
                    various descriptions, with their tempting wares, mingling in the motley
                    groups.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The simple <name who="Winifred">Winifred</name>, who had never seen half so <w
                        type="descLang" subtype="adverb">many</w> grand people in the whole course
                    of her life, was, in her ecstasies, ready to leap out of the grist cart with
                    delight one moment, and the next inclined to rate the prudent <name
                        who="Guthred">Guthred</name> soundly, for having endeavoured to prevent her
                    from enjoying the pleasure of so brave a spectacle.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">All <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> well that ends well,</q>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> his only reply to her reproaches.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">All must end well that hath so joyous a beginning,</q> cried <name
                        who="Winifred">Winifred</name>, <q who="text">for lo! how lovingly <w
                            type="verb" subtype="beVerb">are</w> the Danish holdas riding with our
                        noble thanes, and their grim spearsmen behave like brethren to the ceorls
                        and milk maidens. Oh, it <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> never so
                        seen in my time! or my poor dear <name who="Selwood">Selwood</name> had not
                            <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">been</w> barbarously slain, only for
                        withstanding the foul robbers from plundering his homestead! but the Lord
                        hath turned their wolfish hearts since then, I trow!</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Or rather, the victorous arm of our noble Alfred hath taught them
                        the necessity of adopting better manners,</q> rejoined <name who="Guthred"
                        >Guthred</name> smiling. <q who="text">The Saxon hath the best of it now,
                        good mother, or the Danes had never consented to adopt a king of his
                        choosing; but the truth of it is, Alfred's valour and Alfred's wisdom have
                        so completely broken the power of the Danelagh, that their leaders <w
                            type="verb" subtype="beVerb">are</w> happy to accede to any terms he may
                        choose to impose, as a condition of <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                            >being</w> allowed to remain in possession of the lands they have
                        acquired in Northumbria.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>When they arrived at Oswindune, <name who="Winifred">Winifred</name> expressed an
                    earnest desire to obtain a sight of the holy bishop of Lindisfairne; but, as he
                        <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> surrounded by Saxon thanes and
                    Danish chiefs, with whom he <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> discussing
                    the important business on which this assembly had <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">been</w> convened, there would have <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">been</w> little chance of her wish <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">being</w> gratified, had it not <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">been</w> for the impertinence of the jester of a Danish
                    holda, who, perceiving that his master <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w>
                    exceedingly amused at poor <name who="Winifred">Winifred</name>'s equipage,
                    maliciously rattled his bauble about the ears of the pied mare, which so
                    terrified the animal, that, becoming perfectly unmanageable, she started off at
                    headlong speed, and in spite of all <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>'s efforts
                    to restrain her, carried the grist cart, with himself and <name who="Winifred"
                        >Winifred</name>, into the very centre of the privileged circle that
                    surrounded the bishop of Lindisfairne.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The arrival of this unexpected addition to the national council appeared so
                    thoroughly ludicrous to all parties, that Saxons and Danes alike indulged in the
                    most immoderate bursts of laughter, while some of the younger of both nations <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> found sufficiently illmannered and
                    undignified as to make sport for their companions, by scornfully calling their
                    attention to the long tresses, indicative of high rank, which <name
                        who="Guthred">Guthred</name> wore flowing over the coarse array of a
                    peasant, and which ill assorted with the badge of thraldom on his neck.</s>
                <s>Others still more annoying, drew near, and goaded the startled mare on every
                    side.</s>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> on this, perceiving that his mistress's
                    personal safety <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> greatly imperilled, by
                    the kicking and plunging of the terrified animal, sprang from the cart, and
                    seizing the head rein, attempted to lead the mare out of the press.</s>
                <s>The rude chiefs closed round about the cart, to prevent the escape of the objects
                    of their amusement.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> on this, mildly, but boldly, addressed himself
                    to both Saxons and Danes, requesting them to desist from tormenting the mare; <q
                        who="text">for,</q> said he, <q who="text">the poor animal will receive some
                        injury, and although she be a sorry beast, it behoves us to <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">be</w> careful of her, for, my masters, she <w
                            type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> a borrowed one.</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>This explanation <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> received with noisy
                    shouts of mirth, the annoyances were redoubled on every side, while both Saxons
                    and Danes bade <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> stand back, and not presume to
                    interrupt their pastime.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> boldly maintained his ground, and brandishing
                    his oaken quarter-staff, avowed his intention of defending his mistress and the
                    miller's mare from all aggressions.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The imperious nobles of both nations <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w>
                    astonished and enraged at the hardihood displayed by a peasant's thrall, in
                    daring singly to resist the will of powerful chiefs and magnates; and a gigantic
                    holda, whose mature years and high rank ought to have restrained him from
                    engaging in such proceedings, <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> preparing
                    to deal the dauntless <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> a blow with the heavy
                    handle of his battleaxe, which must have prostrated him, had not <name
                        who="Winifred">Winifred</name>, who perceived his intention, and recognised
                    his person at the same moment, called out, <q who="text">It doth ill become thee
                        to pay in such base coin, methinks, for the plum porridge and metheglin with
                        which thou wert feasted at the board of my husband, <name who="Selwood"
                            >Selwood</name>.</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><q who="text">Just ten years agone, good wife, I think,</q> returned <name
                        who="Ricsig">Ricsig</name> (for it <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w>
                    no other).</s>
                <s><q who="text">I remember thee now by the token of that shrill voice of thine, and
                        for the sake of the excellent plum porridge and metheglin whereof thou speak
                        est, the like of which I have not tasted since, I will now stand thy friend,
                        and help thee and thy son to a place whence thou mayest see the bishop, and
                        hear him speak.</q>
                </s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Winifred">Winifred</name>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> profuse in her acknowledgments to the
                    holda; but, with the pride that formed a prominent part of her character, she
                    thought proper to inform him that the young man <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >was</w> not her son, but her thrall; <q who="text">The very lad,</q>
                    pursued she, <q who="text">whom you gave to my poor dear husband, <name
                            who="Selwood">Selwood</name>, for his carved ivory drinking
                    horn.</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>Notwithstanding all <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>'s magnanimity and acquired
                    philosophy, he felt mortified at the feeling of littleness in his mistress,
                    which prompted her to make this communication to the holda; and he thought from
                    the eager manner in which his former master turned about and scrutinized him
                    from head to foot, that it <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> more than
                    probable he might think proper to reclaim him.</s>
                <s>But <name who="Ricsig">Ricsig</name>, clapping his hands together, shouted in a
                    loud voice, <q who="text">He <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> found,
                        Bishop! the lost son of Hardacanute, the last of the god-like race of Odin,
                        the king whom you have named and we have chosen, <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">is</w> here! Behold, ye valiant Danes, the dark eyes
                        and raven hair of the royal line of the 'king of men,' whose descendants
                        alone <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">are</w> meet to sway a Danish sceptre.
                        Lo! <name who="Ricsig">Ricsig</name>, the son of Kingvar, <w type="verb"
                            subtype="beVerb">is</w> the first to bow the knee before him in
                        homage.</q></s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The bishop of Lindisfairne, at these words, descended from the rude episcopal
                    throne, which had <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">been</w> raised for him on the
                    green turf, and, revealing to the astonished eyes of <name who="Guthred"
                        >Guthred</name> the dearly loved and unforgotten features of his friend and
                    instructor, <name who="Eadred">Eadred</name>, folded him to his bosom for a
                    moment; then, amidst the mingling acclamations of Saxons and Danes, conducted
                    him to the summit of the hill of Oswindune, where the royal inaugurations of the
                    Northumbrian monarchs always took place, and pouring the consecrated oil on his
                    head, exchanged the iron badge of thraldom for the golden bracelets and circlet
                    of royalty, and presented him to the mixed multitude of Northumbrian Danes and
                    Saxons as their king.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>To the enfranchised slave, so lately the sport of adverse fortune, this sudden
                    elevation appeared like a strange dream; but when he <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">was</w> admitted into the presence of the royal Alfred, to
                    swear the oath of fealty to him as his liege lord, he learned from his lips that
                    he had <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">been</w> long marked by him to fill the
                    vassal throne of Northumbria on the recommendation of his friend and counsellor,
                    the bishop of Lindisfairne, who had educated and (unknown to himself) fitted him
                    for the discharge of royal duties, while he wore the iron badge of
                    servitude.</s>
                <s>Nor did <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, when intrusted with the awful
                    responsibility of despotic power, prove unworthy of the confidence reposed in
                    him.</s>
                <s>The illustrious Alfred found in him a faithful friend, and an able coadjutor in
                    establishing equitable laws, reforming abuses, and diffusing the pure light of
                    Christianity through a semi-barbarous land, and introducing the refinements and
                    virtues of civilization among the rugged race over, which he reigned, in peace
                    and prosperity, during <w type="descLang" subtype="adverb">many</w> years.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>'s first exercise of regal authority <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> to raise his friend and instructor,
                        <name who="Eadred">Eadred</name>, to the bishopric of Durham, which he
                    richly endowed ; nor <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> he forgetful of his
                    old mistress, <name who="Winifred">Winifred</name>, whom he cherished with the
                    greatest tenderness, and watched over her declining years with the dutiful
                    affection of a son.</s>
            </p>
        </body>
        <back xml:id="GuthredsTaleHist">
            <title>Historical Summary</title>
            <p>
                <s>Those who have not examined the map of that part of Great Britain which formed
                    the Anglo Saxon empire, will <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> astonished
                    to find, how large and important a portion of our island <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">was</w> once designated by the name of Northumberland.</s>
                <s>Children cast their eyes on the map, and see our northernmost county, or the land
                    lying between the Tyne and the Tweed, at present so called, and must necessarily
                    form a very inadequate idea of the power of the Saxon Northumbrian king;
                    especially when they find from history that this sovereignty had two divisions,
                    the north <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> called the Kingdom of
                    Bernicia, and the south that of Deira.</s>
                <s>It <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> requisite to explain, that the ancient
                    North Humber Land literally meant all the land lying north of the river Humber ;
                    and the possessions of the monarchs of this district comprised the whole of the
                    great county of York, Durham, and not only the spot now corruptly called
                    Northumberland, but Roxburghshire, Lothianshire, and the north-eastern counties
                    of Scotland as far as the Frith of Forth, and as much further as the strong hand
                    of violence could grasp and retain.</s>
                <s>Edinburgh, or Edwinsborough, <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> then a city
                    and a fortress belonging to the Saxons, founded by one of their chiefs.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>A further examination of the map of Europe will shew the youthful student how
                    conveniently Northumbria, with her noble ports and rivers, and her long line of
                    coast washed by the German Ocean, <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> to the
                    piratical rovers that swarmed into England from Norway, Denmark, Sweden, and the
                    north of Germany.</s>
                <s>These <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> collectively first called Saxons,
                    then Danes, and afterwards Normans, who successively supplanted each other and
                        <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> originally the inhabitants of the
                    shores of the Baltic and North Sea.</s>
                <s>At the era of the tale of <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, or the Widow's
                    Slave, the kingdom of Northumberland <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> the
                    strong hold of the Danelagh, or Danish invaders, from whence they harassed the
                    rest of the island.</s>
                <s>Another glance on the map of our country will shew our juvenile reader how
                    strongly fortified by nature Northumbria <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w>
                    bounded on the north by the Frith or Forth; on the west by the chain of
                    mountainous hills that divide the six northern counties; and on the south by the
                    great estuary of the Humber, which is the receptacle of the Trent, with her
                    thirty arms to the south ; and <w type="descLang" subtype="adverb">many</w> fine
                    rivers on the north, that traverse Yorkshire, the Alde, the Swale, the Wharfe,
                    the two Dons, and their dependencies.</s>
                <s>We may aptly compare the figure of the Humber on the map to the thick trunk of an
                    oak tree, with its numerous branches; and the mischievous influence of the Danes
                    may <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> imagined, when we remember that they
                        <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> able to navigate these rivers in
                    their flatbottomed boats, and by these means pierce into the heart of South
                    Britain.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">is</w> an historical character, and the Saxon
                    annals thus relate his adventures.</s>
                <s>After the death of Halfdane, the <emph>Host</emph> of Danes, who had conquered
                    Northumbria, remained without a leader.</s>
                <s>The Northmen <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">were</w> much at variance among
                    themselves.</s>
                <s>Several years before, the sons of Regner Lodbrok had seized upon <name
                        who="Guthred">Guthred</name>, the son of Hardacanute, the king of Lethra, in
                    Sweden; they sold him as a slave or thrall, and in 803 he <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">was</w> the property of an old widow in Northumberland.</s>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>'s lineage <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >was</w> known, he <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> marked as one of
                    the royal race, and he was raised to the supreme authority in a very singular
                    manner.</s>
                <s><name who="Eadred">Eadred</name>, Bishop of Lindisfairne, acting, as it <w
                        type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> said, under the direction of St.</s>
                <s>Cuthbert, who had appeared to him in a dream, proceeded to the host of the Danes,
                    and persuaded them, as well as the Saxons, to accept <name who="Guthred"
                        >Guthred</name> as their sovereign.</s>
                <s>He <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> conducted to Oswin's Dune, or the hill
                    of Oswin, and invested with the golden bracelets, the ensigns of royal dignity,
                    and solemnly inaugurated as king of the Northumbrians, though in vassalage to
                    Alfred the Great as his superior.</s>
                <s><name who="Guthred">Guthred</name>
                    <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> deeply indebted to Bishop <name
                        who="Eadred">Eadred</name>, and he paid his debt of gratitude by granting
                    and confirming, not only the lands between the Tyne and Wear, but the royal
                    dominion over all between the Tyne and Tees, now of the county of Durham.</s>
                <s>Alfred assented to this donation; for he saw the great advantage that would
                    result to his country, from the wild forests of that district <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">being</w> reclaimed by the peaceful monks.</s>
                <s>From this grant the palatinate rights of the wealthy bishops of Durham arise, and
                    which <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">are</w> still retained, in a great
                    measure, in the present day.</s>
                <s>The bishop <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> a prince between the Tyne and
                    Tees.</s>
                <s>He could pardon and condemn, and even exercise the power of life and death; and
                    for this reason, a bishop of Durham may, if he please, sit on the bench in
                    scarlet robes when the judges try a criminal within his diocese.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>We must not omit to mention that <name who="Guthred">Guthred</name> ever remained
                    faithful to Alfred.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>The ready election of this prince by his former enemies, the Danes, as well as
                    the Saxons, may <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">be</w> accounted for, by the
                    reverence in which the royal line of Sweden <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb"
                        >was</w> held throughout the north as the genuine descendants of Odin, who
                    was the reformer, conqueror, and lawgiver, of the north, and for several ages
                    worshipped as a god.</s>
                <s>He <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> said to <w type="verb"
                        subtype="beVerb">be</w> of Asiatic origin, and the dark hair and eyes that
                    tradition decribes his descendants to have possessed, makes that idea
                    probable.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s>In such respect <w type="verb" subtype="beVerb">was</w> a king of Sweden held in
                    ancient times, on account of his lineal descent from this mighty ruler of the
                    north, that the rival monarchs of Denmark and Norway condescended to hold his
                    bridle and stirrup when he mounted or dismounted, on solemn occasions, when
                    these princes met.</s>
            </p>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
