<illustrious_children>
<meta><title>HISTORICAL TALES OF ILLUSTRIOUS BRITISH CHILDREN</title>
<author>AGNES STRICKLAND</author></meta>
<body><tale><tale_title>GUTHRED THE WIDOW'S SLAVE.</tale_title>
<p>Will it be credited by the youthful reader, that in this now free and happy land, slaves were once bought and sold with as little remorse as cattle are in the present day transferred from one master to another? Strange and revolting as it must appear to every lover of his country, such was once the existing practice, not only in the remote ages, when the darkness of heathen barbarism overshadowed the British islands, but even in the reign of the benevolent and enlightened Alfred, under whose auspices law and justice were established in form so pure and equitable, that many of his institutions have been handed down to us from our ancestors as the noblest legacy in their power to bestow.</p>
<p>Civilization, it is true, made a great progress during the era of this accomplished monarch, but he had so many difficulties to contend with, and so many prejudices to overcome, that it is not to be wondered if some abuses remain unreformed, and, among others, this inhuman traffic.</p>
<p>There were few occupiers of land in those days who were not possessed of thralls, or domestic slaves, who were distinguished from the hired servants, by the degrading badge of an iron collar, on which was inscribed the name of the hapless bondman, with the notification that he was the purchased or the born thrall, whichever it might happen to be, of such a person, of such a place.</p>
<p>The tale I am about to relate, which is founded on an authentic historical fact of this nature, is an illustrative sketch of the manners and customs of the Anglo Saxons and Danes, during that glorious period of our annals, the age of Alfred the Great, in whose reign its events took place.</p>
<p>One bright autumnal morning, about eleven o'clock, the hour at which our Saxon ancestors usually took their principal meal, just as the family and serving-folk of the Saxon franklin*, Selwood, were seating themselves at the well covered board, a loud barking from the watch dogs that guarded the homestead, answered by the low, but more angry, growling of the household curs under the table, announced the approach of strangers.</p>
<p>* A Saxon Freeholder, or gentleman, who was possessed of one or more hydes of land. A hyde contains 100 acres.</p>
<p>Selwood, who was beginning to carve for his household, paused to listen, and grasped his huge knife with a firmer hold, as though he meditated using it as a weapon of defence in case of approaching danger. His serving-folk, who, according to the custom of those days, sat at the same table with their master, but below the salt, started from their seats on the rough oaken benches that surrounded the lower end of the board, and laid hand on scythes, flails, or reaping hooks, exclaiming in alarm, <quote>"The Danes be upon us!"</quote></p>
<p>So contiguous indeed was the town of Whitingham, near which the farm and homestead of Selwood were situated, to the Danelagh, or Danish colony that had established itself in great power in Northumberland, that perpetual fear existed in the minds of the franklin and his household, lest their dangerous neighbours should at any time think proper to break the hollow truce then subsisting between the Saxons and Danes, and pay him one of their predatory visits.</p>
<p>The Danish settlements were, in fact, neither more nor less than so many formidable hordes of rapacious banditti, always ready to give and take offence, and on the look-out for plunder. They were a cruel, faithless race, in whose promises no reliance could be placed, and whose only occupation consisted in rapine and deeds of blood.</p>
<p>The industrious habits and peaceful employments of the Saxons, who having become naturalized to the soil, had abandoned the warlike manners of their fierce ancestors for the useful pursuits of the shepherd and the husbandman, were sorely interrupted by the incursions and ravages of the <quote>"black strangers," as the invading Danes were emphatically styled, from the sable hue of the vessels which brought this unwelcome swarm of northern robbers to the shores of England, where they first arrived in the reign of Egbert, and from that time contrived to obtain a footing in the country, and being yearly reinforced with fresh bands of adventurers from the coasts of Denmark and Norway, they continued to gain strength, and at length establishing themselves, side by side as it were, by the Saxons, rendered themselves the terror of the peacefully disposed, and the scourge of the whole country. "They are always before us," says the Saxon Chronicler; "we always see the horizon reddened with flame, we always hear the tramp of war."</quote></p>
<p>At the period of Alfred's accession to the throne, nine pitched battles were fought in one year, between the English and the Danes, besides skirmishes and private conflicts innumerable. Sometimes the Danes were defeated, but after each reverse they appeared to redouble their activity, and actually increased in power. <quote>"If thirty thousand are slain in one day," said the despairing Saxons, "there will be double that number in the field to-morrow."</quote> Sometimes, when the Saxons found themselves unable to cope with their formidable opponents, they were unwise enough to endeavour to purchase a shameful peace with gold; but the bribe was no sooner in the possession of the greedy barbarians, than they violated the dear-bought treaty, and committed all sorts of violence, for the sake of extorting fresh sums of money.</p>
<p>The appearance of a Danish holda, or chief, approaching the homestead of Selwood, though only attended by a boy of tender years, who was leading a brace of wolf-hounds in a leash, was sufficient to spread dismay through the dwelling.</p>
<p>There was an immediate consultation between Selwood and his wife, Winifred, as to whether they should treat the unwelcome visitor as an enemy, by refusing him admittance into the homestead, which doubtless he approached in the quality of a spy, or, as he came in a peaceful guise, choose the alternative of conciliating his friendship, by receiving him as a guest. <quote>"He is a stranger, and as it is meal time it would be churlish to deny him entrance," said Selwood, "albeit, I would with greater pleasure invite a wolf to be my dinner-guest."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"The wolf would be the less dangerous visitor of the two, I trow,"</quote> said the careful Winifred, pocketing, as she spoke, the silver ladle, with which she was preparing to help herself from the bowl of plum porridge which stood before her.</p>
<p>Swindedra, her niece, was in the very act of whisking away the porridge, also muttering as she did so, <quote>"that she had never taken the trouble of compounding such a dainty dish to tickle the palate of a Danish raven, for whom swine's flesh and barley broth were more than good enough," when the holda, whose quick eye had caught the manoeuvre as he entered, called out, "Holla there, maiden! is it your Saxon fashion to remove the best part of the cheer when a stranger surprises you at your meals? Now, that is the very dish whereof I mean to eat."</quote> So saying, he snatched it from her hand, and placing himself in the seat of honour at the table, he took a horn spoon from one of the serving men, and devoured the contents in a trice, with the exception of a small portion, which he left at the bottom of the vessel, and handed over his shoulder with a patronizing air to his youthful atttendant, who stood behind his stool, still holding the hounds in leash.</p>
<p>Guthred, for so the Danish chief called the boy, received this mark of favour with a sullen and reluctant air, and maintained a proud, cold demeanour, to the astonishment of the Saxon servants, who knew, from the iron collar, and other unequivocal badges of slavery about his person, that the boy was in a more degraded condition than themselves, being the purchased thrall or slave of Ricsig the Dane.</p>
<p>Riscig appeared by no means an unkind master, for he took some pains to supply both the cravings of his hounds, and the probable wants of his young slave, with the choisest provisions on the franklin's table, without paying the slightest attention to the feelings of the indignant host and mortified household; but it was thus that the insolent northmen conducted themselves when they entered the dwellings of the peaceful Saxons, who very seldom ventured to remonstrate with their unwelcome guests, lest they should draw upon themselves a still more formidable visitation in the shape of fire and sword, taking it for granted, that where one Dane made himself visible, ten more at least were lurking within call, in readiness to espouse any quarrel in which he might involve himself. It was this apprehension that withheld Selwood and his men from expelling the insolent intruder, who, after astonishing all parties with his voracity, laid hands on a curiously carved drinking horn, which Swindreda, in her anxiety to secure the plum porridge, had forgotten to remove, and calling for metheglin, emptied and replenished it so often with this heady beverage, that he soon got into high humour, and after bestowing great commendations on the beauty of the horn, he, instead of taking possession of it by sticking it into his girdle, beside his battle axe, as too many of his countrymen in such case would have done, actually offered to purchase it of Selwood.</p>
<p><quote>"It is the horn of my fathers," said the Saxon, "and if I sell it to thee, it shall be for naught less than gold."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Gold," echoed the Dane scornfully," dost think I am a Saxon monk, to carry coined pieces in my girdle? My wealth," added he, significantly grasping the handle of his battle axe, "is in the purses of my enemies."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"That is to say," rejoined Selwood, "that you mean to carry off my cunningly-wrought drinking horn, as a reward for my hospitality to thee and thy thrall."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Said I not that I would purchase it of thee?"</quote> demanded Ricsig.</p>
<p><quote>"Ay, but what art thou willing to give me in exchange?"</quote> said the franklin.</p>
<p><quote>"Thou shalt choose, whether thou wilt have my hound, Snath; his fleet-footed companion, Wilbrach; or my thrall, Guthred," replied the holda; "all three of these have displeased me this morning: the two first led me hither on a false track of deer, and the latter perversely refused to eat of the food which I flung to him even now from my own trencher; so choose between them, for the horn is now more precious in my sight than either."</quote></p>
<p>Selwood's judgment was assisted in making his election by a hint from the most prudent of housewives, the thrifty Winifred, who whispered in his ear, "Curs have we more than plenty, master mind, for they only encourage the serving folk in idle pastimes, and serve as a cloak to conceal their wastery when the oaten cakes wax mouldy, or the meat is too fat for their liking: but we are in need of a boy to tend the swine and sheep, and to do many other things, so choose the young thrall, who is a stout healthy lad, and if discreetly trained, will do us worthy service both in and out of doors.</p>
<p>No sooner had Selwood signified his choice to Ricsig, than the barter was completed by the Dane taking the boy by the collar, and transferring him to his new master in these words:</p>
<p><quote>"I, Ricsig, give to thee, Selwood, Guthred my slave, to be thy thrall for ever." Then tucking the drinking horn into his belt, he strode out of the Saxon homestead, whistling to his dogs to follow. Guthred flung himself on the ground and wept. "Nay, cheer up, my dainty bird," said Winifred compassionately, "thou wilt have no cause to lament thy change of masters, I promise, if thou wilt be a dutiful and painstaking slave."</quote></p>
<p>Guthred redoubled his tears, and at length sobbed audibly.</p>
<p><quote>"Thou didst not seem so loving to thy Danish master that thou shouldst bewail a separation from him thus passionately,"</quote> observed Swindreda.</p>
<p><quote>"Loving to him !" echoed the boy indignantly, his large dark eyes flashing through his streaming tears as he spoke, "loving unto a Dane,to my born foe?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Why then, thou shouldst rejoice in thy change of thraldom,"</quote> said Winifred.</p>
<p><quote>"It is for my thraldom that I weep," replied Guthred, "for I was free born, and am no more disposed to serve a Saxon churl than to be the slave of a Danish robber."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"High words do oft proceed from an empty stomach," observed his new master, sternly; "but I counsel thee, boy, to stint thy perverse prating, which can answer no other purpose than to bring the thong across thy shoulders."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Thy women folk pestered me with questions, or I had only wept in silence,"</quote> replied Guthred scornfully.</p>
<p><quote>"Women folk, indeed!" cried Swindreda, giving him a smart box on the years. "I'll teach thee to use more respectful language of thy betters, and let thee know, withal, that it is not the business of a thrall to weep, but to work."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"It is well for thee that thou art a women, though an ill-favoured one, or I had returned thy hard blow with usury,"</quote> retorted Guthred, clenching his hand.</p>
<p>Swindreda was preparing to inflict summary vengeance on the imprudent railer, but Winifred humanely interposed to prevent the visitation of her wrathful displeasure, by sending her to feed the poultry, while she herself proceeded to instruct the newly-purchased slave in some of the household duties which he would be required to perform.</p>
<p>On the following day, Selwood ordered his shepherd, his neatherd, swineherd, and wood cutter, to put him in the way of becoming a useful assistant in their several vocations, but Guthred was sullen and refractory with the men, and rebellious to the women; the authority of both was, of course, enforced by harsh measures, and the young thrall was compelled to yield reluctant obedience after repeated chastisements; thus entailing upon himself severe personal sufferings in addition to the hardships of servitude.</p>
<p>His foreign accent and complexion, so different from that of his Saxon masters, had obtained for Guthred the name of the Son of the stranger, a designation by no means likely to improve his condition among the Saxon serfs and ceorls, who had suffered too deeply from the aggressions of the Danes to be disposed to regard any foreigner with favourable eyes. Guthred was exposed to many taunts from the serving folk, on account of his persisting in wearing his dark hair, flowing on his shoulders, in its natural length, and rich luxuriance of spiral ringlets. Long hair was only worn by persons of noble or royal birth; and though Guthred had refused to declare his birth and lineage, he assumed this envied distinction, to the infinite displeasure of his associates in labour, who had more than once seized upon him, and, forcibly shorn these aristocratical honours from the proud head of the youthful slave; and when their mistress interposed her authority to prevent a repetition of the outrage, they vented their spleen in addressing him by the title of <quote>"high and mighty thane,"</quote> whenever they required him to perform the most servile offices.</p>
<p>Guthred once smiled in scorn at the insult, and told his tormentors, <quote>"that, like ignorant churls as they were, they addressed him by a title far below that which was his due."</quote></p>
<p>But this intimation drew upon him a torrent of such bitter mockery, that from that time forward he preserved a contemptuous silence when assailed by the taunts of the serfs.</p>
<p>The long weary winter, the hardest time of bondage that Guthred had yet sustained, passed away, and the sweet season of spring once more clothed the Northumbrian fields with verdure, and enamelled the pastures with flowers. It was some relief to the persecuted thrall of Selwood, when he was separated from the rude churls, and employed in the solitary office of keeping the sheep on the extensive downs, heath-clad hills, or pleasant meads; but lovely as the scenes were, the sick heart of the young exile fondly yearned after the wild and rugged scenery of the far distant land of his fathers, Those eternal forests of sombre pines and chains of barren mountains, he preferred to the oaken glades, and the verdant hills and dales of the fertile island of the west, of which he had become an unwilling denizen. The land was indeed fair; but to him who has neither sympathies nor companionship, the most smiling landscape becomes a dreary desert.</p>
<p>Had Guthred ever felt the divine influence of religion, he might have supported his early sorrows with resignation; for, though companionless, he would have known that he was not alone, that he was upheld by the everlasting arm of his Father and his God, and would have learned in every dispensation, however afflicting, to recognise his hand; but he had been born in a heathen land, and the light of Christianity had never dawned on his benighted mind. Selwood and his household, indeed, were, nominally speaking, Christians; but their creed and practice were so corrupted, and interwoven with pagan superstitions and idolatries, that they were scarcely in less darkness than the young heathen, whose aversion to their mode of worship excited their anger and contempt.</p>
<p>Guthred only disliked their mode of worship because it was theirs, for he had never deigned to examine into the nature of their belief; from his own he drew no consolation; it was made up of shadowy recollections of gigantic idols, before whose images he had been taught by his father to bow the knee in the depth of gloomy groves. His remembrance recalled their terrific forms, but of their attributes he retained no idea, though he was occasionally wont to revoke them as the avengers of his wrongs, when injured by his Danish or Saxon task-masters.</p>
<p>One day, when a war of words between him and Swindreda had ended in his stubborn refusal to draw water at her behest, and a severe corporeal punishment from the franklin had compelled him to submission, he proceeded to the sheepfold with a swelling heart, and throwing himself upon the ground, called aloud upon Thor and Woden to bring destruction upon Selwood and his whole household.</p>
<p>He paused, partly exhausted by the violence of his transport of fury, and partly, perhaps, from a sort of undefined expectation of receiving an answer to his vengeful invocation. It came; but neither in the uproar of the elements, nor the rush of the chariot wheels of the destroyer careering through the air; but in the soft low voice of compassionate expostulation. He raised his face from the earth, and perceived a stranger beside him, whose majestic form and mild countenance impressed him with the idea that he was a being of a different order from the rude and savage men with whom he had been accustomed to associate.</p>
<p><quote>"Unhappy boy!" said the stranger, "upon whom hast thou called?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"On the gods of my fathers," replied Guthred. "Those whom mine own people worshipped within the strong circles of their power, and on whose rough-hewn altars my father was wont to pour forth the blood of his slaughtered foes."</quote></p>
<p>The stranger shuddered. <quote>"Alas, poor child!" said he," and canst thou believe that such inhuman sacrifices could be acceptable to the beneficent Creator of this beautiful world, which he has formed for the happiness and delight of his creatures, whom he has commanded to love one another, and to worship him in the beauty of holiness, not with polluted hands and bloody rites?"</quote></p>
<p>Guthred looked perplexed, for the language of the stranger was incomprehensible to him. At length he said, <quote>"It was to Thor and Woden these sacrifices were offered by my father. To them the savour of the blood is sweet; for they are called the Destroyer and the Avenger. Oh that they would bring fire and sword upon the homestead of Selwood, the Saxon!"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Thy guilty prayer is such as might indeed be expected from the lips of a benighted worshipper of the powers of evil," replied the stranger: "but know, my son, that in offering homage to Thor and Woden you are acting in direct rebellion to the Lord and Giver of Life, and the Supreme Ruler of the Universe, and are provoking his wrath to visit you with those maledictions which you impiously call down upon your enemies."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I cannot be more wretched than I am," replied Guthred, "or suffer greater reverses, for I, who was born a prince, am now the slave of slaves."</quote> He bowed his face once more upon the earth, and lifting up his voice, wept aloud.</p>
<p>The stranger allowed his passionate grief to vent itself, without interruption, for some moments, and then drawing Guthred to him, he addressed him in words of sympathy and encouragement.</p>
<p>The soothing tones, and language of compassion and tenderness, were new to the ears of the youthful slave; but they made their way to his heart, and melted the obdurate pride which had always prompted him to oppose violence to violence, and to return wrong for wrong, and with the confiding frankness of childhood, he flung himself into the arms of his unknown comforter, and wetted his bosom with his tears.</p>
<p><quote>"You say you were born a prince," observed the stranger, after a pause. "Whence come you?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"From the land of the dark forest and the snowclad mountain," replied Guthred, with a flushing cheek and kindling eye, "from Lethra*, where my father, Hardacanute, was a king and a warrior: and I, his heir, was brought up on the knees of the valiant, served by the hands of the noble, and lulled to sleep by the songs of the bards, who told of the deeds of my great forefather, the mighty Odin, whose coal-black eye, and raven hair, they said resembled mine. But Halfdane and Hubba, the fierce sons of Regner Lodbrok, came, like a wintry torrent, spreading woe and desolation through my native Lethra, and having slain my sire, and burned his cities, they bore me, a helpless sorrowing child, from the place of my birth, and the kingdom I should have inherited, to their own detested land of Denmark, where Halfdane, the eldest of the fierce brethren, the same who now awes the trembling Northumbrian Saxons, with the terror of his name, this Halfdane, I say, exchanged me with his hunting companion, Ricsig, for a wolf-hound, and Ricsig, in his turn, trucked me away to Selwood, the Saxon, for a paltry drinking horn, as though I had been a thing of nought, a senseless utensil, or a beast of the field."</quote></p>
<p>* Lethra, a province of ancient Sweden.Palgrave.</p>
<p><quote>"And how have you been treated in the household of the Saxon franklin?"</quote> demanded the stranger.</p>
<p><quote>"With hard words and harder blows," returned Guthred, indignantly, "have I been driven forth to the performance of vile offices. A hewer of wood and a drawer of water have I been to sordid household queens, and a drudge in field and fold to the base churls who served my Saxon master, and with their injurious usage increased the bitterness of a prince's bondage. Pity have I had from no one save from thyself," added he, in a softened tone, on perceiving the kindly drops which the tale of his sorrows had drawn from the benign eyes of the stranger. "And who art thou that weepest for the woes of an alien and a slave? Surely thou belongest not to the race of the unfeeling Saxon, or the savage Dane!"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"My name is Eadred," replied the stranger, "and, though of Saxon lineage, I am not, I trust, unfeeling, but the servant of One who is the friend of the friendless ; who hath, in his Divine wisdom, for some good purpose, doubtless, brought thee hither, and hath sent me to thee with tidings of comfort."</quote></p>
<p>In reply to Guthred's eager inquiries, Eadred proceeded to reveal to him that God, of whose name and attributes he had hitherto remained in profound ignorance.</p>
<p>Guthred listened patiently, for the manners of the eloquent speaker had that mild persuasive charm which appeals resistlessly to every heart. He listened attentively, for the subject was one of powerful interest, conveyed as it was, in the impressive, but sublime simplicity of truth. He listened with delight, for the pure doctrines of Christianity were glad tidings to the desolate, heartbroken captive, to whom they offered better hopes of happiness in a future state of existence than the savage pleasure of quaffing mead and beer from the skulls of slaughtered foes, in the joyless valhalla, or heaven, of Scandinavian mythology ; and Guthred, the lineal descendant of the renowned Odin, who was honoured as one of the mightiest of the northern divinities, became a convert to the Christian faith.</p>
<p>Eadred frequently sought his young friend in the lonely pastures where he kept the franklin's sheep, for the purpose of imparting to his powerful, but uncultivated mind, the advantages of that learning which he was ably qualified to communicate; for Eadred was a Saxon monk of distinguished talents and eminent acquirements, who resided in a neighbouring convent, and employed himself in works of mercy and charity, and experienced a pure delight in diffusing the light of knowledge and religion, in succouring the distrest, and comforting the sorrowful. As his pupil, the hitherto fierce and intractable Guthred, became mild, reflective, and intelligent, the hours that he had been accustomed to waste in vain repining, listless inanity, or stormy bursts of passion, were now employed in study or heavenward meditation, which enabled him to correct the defects of his character, and to endure with resignation and fortitude the toil and persecution he occasionally had to bear. He no longer regretted the loss of power and dominions, for his mind was to him a kingdom, and the intercourse he enjoyed with the pious and accomplished Eadred, he would not have resigned for all the riches the world could bestow.</p>
<p>Books were then rare possessions, confined to the libraries of convents, and but seldom to be met with in the cabinets of monarchs, yet Guthred, through the favour of his learned friend, was seldom without a roll of illuminated MS. in his bosom wherewith to beguile his solitary hours, and sweeten the labours of the day. Nor were his studies confined to book-learning alone; he became an observer of the face of nature, and the characters of his fellow men.</p>
<p><quote>"Knowledge is power,"</quote> Lord Bacon, in later times, has said, and the enslaved Guthred, the servant of servants, as he, in the bitterness of his soul had aptly styled himself, acquired with his growing wisdom such influence over the minds of those around him, that he became as it were the oracle of the household and neighbourhood. His sayings were quoted, his advice solicited, and his judgment appealed to, in all cases where parties were at issue or difficulties occurred.</p>
<p>Like the captive Hebrew in the house of the Egyptian lord, every thing appeared to prosper with him. The flocks and herds of Selwood increased, and his crops were more abundant; plenty was without, and peace was within the dwelling, where the master mind of the young slave, as he approached to manhood, manifested its superiority over the ignorant serfs and ceorls, by the improvements he suggested, and the good order he contributed to establish and maintain. But these days of tranquillity were not to last. The growing wealth of Selwood excited the cupidity of the Danish hordes in the neighbourhood, who, taking advantage of a dispute among themselves, in which they pretended that the inhabitants of Whitingham had interfered, poured down upon the devoted Saxons, plundered their dwellings, drove away their flocks and herds, and put every man to the sword who dared to offer resistance to their lawless rapacity.</p>
<p>When Guthred, who had been sent by his master on a message of trust, to receive a sum of money from the monks of Lindisfairne, for a drove of fat bullocks, returned to Whitingham, he found the lands harried, the flocks and herds gone, and his mistress sitting on her ruined hearth-stone, weeping over the mangled corse of the murdered franklin, her husband; deserted by serfs and thralls, they having taken advantage of her calamity to provide for their own interests; and even abandoned by her niece and sole relative, Swindreda, that damsel having taken a fancy to one of the Danish plunderers, with whom she departed to the Danelagh.</p>
<p>It was then that Guthred found occasion for the exercise of those principles of Christian benevolence, which had been inculcated by the pious Eadred. That beloved friend was indeed lost to him, for the convent had been plundered and burned by the ferocious Danes, and no trace of the monks or their peaceful and useful occupations remained; but the precepts of Eadred remained indelibly impressed on tablets of Guthred's heart, whose first impulse was to bestow such consolation and assistance as it was in his power to offer to the broken-hearted widow.</p>
<p>Poor Winifred, who had not expected to receive that sympathy and succour from the foreign thrall which had been denied by those from whom she had most reason to expect it, lifted up her voice, and blessed him with the blessing of the widow and the destitute.</p>
<p>When Guthred had consigned the bleeding remains of his murdered master to a grave, which he dug for him beneath the umbrage of one of the noble elms that had formerly overshadowed the low roofed but pleasant dwelling, he conducted his sorrowing mistress to a miserable shieling, or cottage, that had escaped the general conflagration that had consumed house, barns, and cattle sheds; but, notwithstanding all his care and consideration, Winifred must have perished of want, had it not been for the sum which Guthred had received from the monks of Lindisfairne for his deceased master, and which he now, with scrupulous fidelity, delivered to the astonished widow. <quote>"Keep it, my son," said she, "and use it for our mutual benefit; surely it will be safer in thy hands than in mine, and will prosper under thy management."</quote></p>
<p>Guthred applied this little store with such prudence and success, and used such unremitting personal exertions, in improving the widow's mite, that, by degrees, her desolate dwelling began to wear an air of comfort, and at length she found herself the mistress of a productive little farm, with kine, sheep, swine, and poultry, sufficient for her use.</p>
<p>Guthred, who found a sweet satisfaction in administering to her comforts, was repaid a thousand fold by the tender affection with which he was regarded by the grateful widow, who was to him as a mother.</p>
<p>Northumbria continued the theatre of petty intestine wars, not only between its rival population of Saxons and Danes, but of fierce dissensions among the Danes themselves, who, since the death of Halfdane, their leader, and the overthrow and slaughter of his brother Hubba (the sons of Begner Lodbrok, and chief governors of the Danelagh), had not been able to agree among themselves respecting the choice of a successor to the sovereign authority, not one of the royal line of Odin remaining among their hordes.</p>
<p>But the wars and rumours of wars, which spread desolation, bloodshed, and terror, through country and town of this unfortunate district, disquieted not the humble cottage where the widowed Winifred and her thrall, Guthred, found shelter and contentment. There were moments, perhaps, when Guthred felt disposed to regret that his talents and acquirements had no nobler sphere for their exercise than the occupations of a shepherd or husbandman; but then the reflection that he was engaged in the virtuous performance of the duties of that state to which it had pleased his heavenly Father to call him, checked the rebellious suggestions of ambition and discontent, and he returned to his toils with the pious conviction, that if it were the will of God that the hand that ought to have wielded a sceptre should be doomed to guide a plough in an obscure corner of a foreign land, it was right that it should be so. But other things were in store for the royal orphan, who had been prepared and fitted in the school of adversity for a better inheritance than that which was his birthright.</p>
<p>One morning, on returning from the field to breakfast, he found Winifred attired in her best black kirtle, surcoat, and hood, and busily engaged in smoothing, with an iron, the plaits and coarse embroidery on the back and shoulder of his sabbath supertunic, which garment was made of coarse home-spun white linen, precisely similar in all respects to the long open frocks worn in the present day by waggoners. <quote>"How now, my good mother," said Guthred, with a smile, for by that endearing title he had long been accustomed to address her, "what makes you so full of business with my best parelling to-day? To-morrow is neither Sunday nor a saint's day, you know."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"No matter, my son," replied Winifred, "there is to be a goodly show and a great festival at Oswindune, for the Danes and Saxons are tired of their quarrels and evil doing, and have resolved to choose a king of Northumberland by mutual agreement, this blessed day, to put an end to bloodshed and deadly debate; and Ulph, the miller, of Whitingham, who hath just told me the glad tidings, hath promised to lend us one of his grist carts, and the old pied mare, that we may go thither like our neighbours to view the joyful sight."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"My dear mother," said Guthred, "those will be wisest who keep at home on such a day, especially women folk and Saxons, believe me; for such a meeting is far more likely to create deadly debate than to end them, and then the sword and the battleaxe will be the umpires that will decide any quarrel that may arise; for as to the Danes and Saxons agreeing in any thing, much less on a matter of such importance as the choice of a king, it is not to be expected ; therefore, their assembly will only be the cause of bloodshed, so, dear mother, be persuaded by me, and go not thither to-day."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Nay! nay ! my son, thou art, for once, mistaken in thy judgment," said Winifred, "for our people and the Danes have already agreed in the wise determination of leaving the nomination of their mutual governor to our good king Alfred and the pious bishop of Lindisfairne, who will both be present, they say; and if we go not to Oswindune to-day, we may never again enjoy the felicity of looking upon such a king and such a prelate. Besides," added she, on observing that Guthred was about to offer some fresh objection, "I am resolved on going, whether you approve of it or not; for I have lived under the shadow of this poor shieling in the depth of a wood, lo! this seven years, and seen neither feast nor festival since the day of my sad widowhood, and 'tis time now, I wot, that I should enjoy some pastime; so, if thou likest not to drive the pied mare, I will e'n ask Ulph the miller to give me a seat in his great meal waggon, with the rest of the gossips and neighbours, who are going to see this blessed sight."</quote></p>
<p>Well, mother,<quote>" replied Guthred, "if you are thus bent on going, I am your thrall, you know, and bound to do your bidding; and even were that not the case, I would attend you for love's sake, especially as there may be danger."</quote></p>
<p>Winifred, in high good humour at having carried her point, packed up a store of oaten cakes, cheese, and dried mutton, to which she added a bottle of her best metheglin, as a store for the journey, while Guthred combed his long dark ringlets, washed his face and hands, and donned his snowy super-tunic and fox-fur cap, in readiness to attend his mistress.</p>
<p>The roads were like all roads in those days, of a very rough description, full of deep ruts and holes, here and there mended with rough blocks of stone, or the trunks of trees laid side by side. The grist cart was an uncouth, and what was worse, a jolting conveyance, and the miller's old pied mare a sorry jade; nevertheless, the day was so fine, and they met with such abundance of good company on the road, that both mistress and slave were in the best possible spirits, and were willing to overlook all inconveniences, and only to dwell on the agreeable part of the journey.</p>
<p>When they drew near the scene of action, Winifred was greatly amused by examining the various cavalcades of Danish holdas in their burnished armour, over which flowed silken mantles, and their long red tresses braided with gems and threads of gold, for the Danes, notwithstanding their ferocious and barbarous manners, affected great nicety in dress, and were the fops of the ninth century; the gallantly armed and mounted Saxon thanes, with their courtly yet warlike bearing, and festal array, each attended by a train of martial followers; the bands of wealthy franklins, and sturdy ceorls, with their wives and families; even the poor serfs and craftsmen of low degree were flocking from all directions to the spot. Besides these were glee men and harps; travelling jugglers with apes and bears; morrice dancers; and itinerants of various descriptions, with their tempting wares, mingling in the motley groups.</p>
<p>The simple Winifred, who had never seen half so many grand people in the whole course of her life, was, in her ecstasies, ready to leap out of the grist cart with delight one moment, and the next inclined to rate the prudent Guthred soundly, for having endeavoured to prevent her from enjoying the pleasure of so brave a spectacle.</p>
<p><quote>"All is well that ends well,"</quote> was his only reply to her reproaches.</p>
<p><quote>"All must end well that hath so joyous a beginning," cried Winifred, "for lo! how lovingly are the Danish holdas riding with our noble thanes, and their grim spearsmen behave like brethren to the ceorls and milk maidens. Oh, it was never so seen in my time! or my poor dear Selwood had not been barbarously slain, only for withstanding the foul robbers from plundering his homestead! but the Lord hath turned their wolfish hearts since then, I trow!"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Or rather, the victorous arm of our noble Alfred hath taught them the necessity of adopting better manners," rejoined Guthred smiling. "The Saxon hath the best of it now, good mother, or the Danes had never consented to adopt a king of his choosing; but the truth of it is, Alfred's valour and Alfred's wisdom have so completely broken the power of the Danelagh, that their leaders are happy to accede to any terms he may choose to impose, as a condition of being allowed to remain in possession of the lands they have acquired in Northumbria."</quote></p>
<p>When they arrived at Oswindune, Winifred expressed an earnest desire to obtain a sight of the holy bishop of Lindisfairne; but, as he was surrounded by Saxon thanes and Danish chiefs, with whom he was discussing the important business on which this assembly had been convened, there would have been little chance of her wish being gratified, had it not been for the impertinence of the jester of a Danish holda, who, perceiving that his master was exceedingly amused at poor Winifred's equipage, maliciously rattled his bauble about the ears of the pied mare, which so terrified the animal, that, becoming perfectly unmanageable, she started off at headlong speed, and in spite of all Guthred's efforts to restrain her, carried the grist cart, with himself and Winifred, into the very centre of the privileged circle that surrounded the bishop of Lindisfairne.</p>
<p>The arrival of this unexpected addition to the national council appeared so thoroughly ludicrous to all parties, that Saxons and Danes alike indulged in the most immoderate bursts of laughter, while some of the younger of both nations were found sufficiently illmannered and undignified as to make sport for their companions, by scornfully calling their attention to the long tresses, indicative of high rank, which Guthred wore flowing over the coarse array of a peasant, and which ill assorted with the badge of thraldom on his neck. Others still more annoying, drew near, and goaded the startled mare on every side. Guthred on this, perceiving that his mistress's personal safety was greatly imperilled, by the kicking and plunging of the terrified animal, sprang from the cart, and seizing the head rein, attempted to lead the mare out of the press. The rude chiefs closed round about the cart, to prevent the escape of the objects of their amusement.</p>
<p>Guthred on this, mildly, but boldly, addressed himself to both Saxons and Danes, requesting them to desist from tormenting the mare; <quote>"for," said he, "the poor animal will receive some injury, and although she be a sorry beast, it behoves us to be careful of her, for, my masters, she is a borrowed one."</quote></p>
<p>This explanation was received with noisy shouts of mirth, the annoyances were redoubled on every side, while both Saxons and Danes bade Guthred stand back, and not presume to interrupt their pastime.</p>
<p>Guthred boldly maintained his ground, and brandishing his oaken quarter-staff, avowed his intention of defending his mistress and the miller's mare from all aggressions.</p>
<p>The imperious nobles of both nations were astonished and enraged at the hardihood displayed by a peasant's thrall, in daring singly to resist the will of powerful chiefs and magnates; and a gigantic holda, whose mature years and high rank ought to have restrained him from engaging in such proceedings, was preparing to deal the dauntless Guthred a blow with the heavy handle of his battleaxe, which must have prostrated him, had not Winifred, who perceived his intention, and recognised his person at the same moment, called out, <quote>"It doth ill become thee to pay in such base coin, methinks, for the plum porridge and metheglin with which thou wert feasted at the board of my husband, Selwood."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Just ten years agone, good wife, I think," returned Ricsig (for it was no other). I remember thee now by the token of that shrill voice of thine, and for the sake of the excellent plum porridge and metheglin whereof thou speak est, the like of which I have not tasted since, I will now stand thy friend, and help thee and thy son to a place whence thou mayest see the bishop, and hear him speak."</quote></p>
<p>Winifred was profuse in her acknowledgments to the holda; but, with the pride that formed a prominent part of her character, she thought proper to inform him that the young man was not her son, but her thrall; <quote>"The very lad," pursued she, "whom you gave to my poor dear husband, Selwood, for his carved ivory drinking horn."</quote></p>
<p>Notwithstanding all Guthred's magnanimity and acquired philosophy, he felt mortified at the feeling of littleness in his mistress, which prompted her to make this communication to the holda; and he thought from the eager manner in which his former master turned about and scrutinized him from head to foot, that it was more than probable he might think proper to reclaim him. But Ricsig, clapping his hands together, shouted in a loud voice, <quote>"He is found, Bishop! the lost son of Hardacanute, the last of the god-like race of Odin, the king whom you have named and we have chosen, is here! Behold, ye valiant Danes, the dark eyes and raven hair of the royal line of the 'king of men,' whose descendants alone are meet to sway a Danish sceptre. Lo! Ricsig, the son of Kingvar, is the first to bow the knee before him in homage."</quote></p>
<p>The bishop of Lindisfairne, at these words, descended from the rude episcopal throne, which had been raised for him on the green turf, and, revealing to the astonished eyes of Guthred the dearly loved and unforgotten features of his friend and instructor, Eadred, folded him to his bosom for a moment; then, amidst the mingling acclamations of Saxons and Danes, conducted him to the summit of the hill of Oswindune, where the royal inaugurations of the Northumbrian monarchs always took place, and pouring the consecrated oil on his head, exchanged the iron badge of thraldom for the golden bracelets and circlet of royalty, and presented him to the mixed multitude of Northumbrian Danes and Saxons as their king.</p>
<p>To the enfranchised slave, so lately the sport of adverse fortune, this sudden elevation appeared like a strange dream; but when he was admitted into the presence of the royal Alfred, to swear the oath of fealty to him as his liege lord, he learned from his lips that he had been long marked by him to fill the vassal throne of Northumbria on the recommendation of his friend and counsellor, the bishop of Lindisfairne, who had educated and (unknown to himself) fitted him for the discharge of royal duties, while he wore the iron badge of servitude. Nor did Guthred, when intrusted with the awful responsibility of despotic power, prove unworthy of the confidence reposed in him. The illustrious Alfred found in him a faithful friend, and an able coadjutor in establishing equitable laws, reforming abuses, and diffusing the pure light of Christianity through a semi-barbarous land, and introducing the refinements and virtues of civilization among the rugged race over, which he reigned, in peace and prosperity, during many years.</p>
<p>Guthred's first exercise of regal authority was to raise his friend and instructor, Eadred, to the bishopric of Durham, which he richly endowed ; nor was he forgetful of his old mistress, Winifred, whom he cherished with the greatest tenderness, and watched over her declining years with the dutiful affection of a son.</p></tale>
<historical_summary>Those who have not examined the map of that part of Great Britain which formed the Anglo Saxon empire, will be astonished to find, how large and important a portion of our island was once designated by the name of Northumberland. Children cast their eyes on the map, and see our northernmost county, or the land lying between the Tyne and the Tweed, at present so called, and must necessarily form a very inadequate idea of the power of the Saxon Northumbrian king; especially when they find from history that this sovereignty had two divisions, the north was called the Kingdom of Bernicia, and the south that of Deira. It is requisite to explain, that the ancient North Humber Land literally meant all the land lying north of the river Humber ; and the possessions of the monarchs of this district comprised the whole of the great county of York, Durham, and not only the spot now corruptly called Northumberland, but Roxburghshire, Lothianshire, and the north-eastern counties of Scotland as far as the Frith of Forth, and as much further as the strong hand of violence could grasp and retain. Edinburgh, or Edwinsborough, was then a city and a fortress belonging to the Saxons, founded by one of their chiefs.
<p>A further examination of the map of Europe will shew the youthful student how conveniently Northumbria, with her noble ports and rivers, and her long line of coast washed by the German Ocean, was to the piratical rovers that swarmed into England from Norway, Denmark, Sweden, and the north of Germany. These were collectively first called Saxons, then Danes, and afterwards Normans, who successively supplanted each other and were originally the inhabitants of the shores of the Baltic and North Sea. At the era of the tale of Guthred, or the Widow's Slave, the kingdom of Northumberland was the strong hold of the Danelagh, or Danish invaders, from whence they harassed the rest of the island. Another glance on the map of our country will shew our juvenile reader how strongly fortified by nature Northumbria was bounded on the north by the Frith or Forth; on the west by the chain of mountainous hills that divide the six northern counties; and on the south by the great estuary of the Humber, which is the receptacle of the Trent, with her thirty arms to the south ; and many fine rivers on the north, that traverse Yorkshire, the Alde, the Swale, the Wharfe, the two Dons, and their dependencies. We may aptly compare the figure of the Humber on the map to the thick trunk of an oak tree, with its numerous branches; and the mischievous influence of the Danes may be imagined, when we remember that they were able to navigate these rivers in their flatbottomed boats, and by these means pierce into the heart of South Britain.</p>
<p>Guthred is an historical character, and the Saxon annals thus relate his adventures. After the death of Halfdane, the <quote>"Host"</quote> of Danes, who had conquered Northumbria, remained without a leader. The Northmen were much at variance among themselves. Several years before, the sons of Regner Lodbrok had seized upon Guthred, the son of Hardacanute, the king of Lethra, in Sweden; they sold him as a slave or thrall, and in 803 he was the property of an old widow in Northumberland. Guthred's lineage was known, he was marked as one of the royal race, and he was raised to the supreme authority in a very singular manner. Eadred, Bishop of Lindisfairne, acting, as it was said, under the direction of St. Cuthbert, who had appeared to him in a dream, proceeded to the host of the Danes, and persuaded them, as well as the Saxons, to accept Guthred as their sovereign. He was conducted to Oswin's Dune, or the hill of Oswin, and invested with the golden bracelets, the ensigns of royal dignity, and solemnly inaugurated as king of the Northumbrians, though in vassalage to Alfred the Great as his superior. Guthred was deeply indebted to Bishop Eadred, and he paid his debt of gratitude by granting and confirming, not only the lands between the Tyne and Wear, but the royal dominion over all between the Tyne and Tees, now of the county of Durham. Alfred assented to this donation; for he saw the great advantage that would result to his country, from the wild forests of that district being reclaimed by the peaceful monks. From this grant the palatinate rights of the wealthy bishops of Durham arise, and which are still retained, in a great measure, in the present day. The bishop was a prince between the Tyne and Tees. He could pardon and condemn, and even exercise the power of life and death; and for this reason, a bishop of Durham may, if he please, sit on the bench in scarlet robes when the judges try a criminal within his diocese.</p>
<p>We must not omit to mention that Guthred ever remained faithful to Alfred.</p>
<p>The ready election of this prince by his former enemies, the Danes, as well as the Saxons, may be accounted for, by the reverence in which the royal line of Sweden was held throughout the north as the genuine descendants of Odin, who was the reformer, conqueror, and lawgiver, of the north, and for several ages worshipped as a god. He was said to be of Asiatic origin, and the dark hair and eyes that tradition decribes his descendants to have possessed, makes that idea probable.</p>
<p>In such respect was a king of Sweden held in ancient times, on account of his lineal descent from this mighty ruler of the north, that the rival monarchs of Denmark and Norway condescended to hold his bridle and stirrup when he mounted or dismounted, on solemn occasions, when these princes met.</p></historical_summary>
<tale><tale_title>ROYAL CHASE OF WAREHAM.</tale_title>
<p>On the death of Edgar the Second, sirnamed the peaceable, England was distracted by the contentions of two adverse factions respecting the choice of a successor to the crown.</p>
<p>At the head of the most powerful party, distinguished by the name of the Dunstanites, was the famous Archbishop Dunstan,* who supported the title of Edward the Atheling, or prince royal, the eldest son of the deceased monarch, by his first wife. The other faction called the Anti-Dunstanites, were the partisans of the queen dowager, the beautiful but wicked Elfrida, who was ambitious of placing her young son Ethelred on the throne, and governing in his name during a long minority. But while the whole nation was divided and involved in civil discord on this point, and the most deadly hatred agitated the minds of those who espoused the rival claims of the sons of Edgar, it is an interesting fact that the youthful princes, though only brothers by the half blood, were united in the tenderest bonds of love.</p>
<p>* Some account of this celebrated statesman and ecclesiastic will be found in the Historical Summary.</p>
<p>Edward, who had just completed his fourteenth year, had been named by his dying father as his successor. The right of primogeniture was his also, and in the Witenagemot or great national council, the eloquence and influence of the two archbishops, Dunstan and Oswald, obtained a formal recognition of those rights, and Prince Edward was, in conformity with the will of his deceased father, placed on the throne of the Anglo Saxons.</p>
<p>At the tender age of seven years the baleful passions of ambition had no place in the then guileless heart of the younger prince. Unconscious of the charms of royalty, of which he had as yet only experienced the restraints, the loss of a kingdom was not to him matter of either disappointment or regret. The only sorrow of which the decision of the Witenagemot was productive to him was his separation from that beloved elder brother, in whose affectionate bosom he had, from his earliest remembrance, been wont to repose his childish joys and griefs, and who had been his companion, his guide, and his own sweet familiar friend. Never were the soothing kindness and fond endearments he had been accustomed to receive from the princely Edward so much required by Ethelred as at this period, when all the evil passions of his haughty mother's nature had been roused and called into baleful activity during her late attempts to supplant her royal step-son: and having been foiled in her endeavours to usurp the royal authority in Ethelred's name, she vented her mortification and baffled rage on the unfortunate object of her maternal ambition and defeated machinations.</p>
<p>Weak in body and feeble in mind, Ethelred bad evidently been designed by nature for a private station, and these constitutional defects frequently subjected him to the bitterest reproaches and most injurious treatment from the imperious Elfrida, whose unrestrained violence of temper rendered her at all times an object of terror to him, although occasionally experiencing the most pernicious indulgence from her when caprice inclined her to fondness.</p>
<p>Child as he was, Ethelred was only too painfully aware of the evil traits of his mother's character, and since he had been deprived by death of his natural protector, and afterwards separated from his affectionate brother, he seemed to tremble at the sound of her step, and sought at all times to avoid her presence, while he beheld with jealous displeasure the caresses she bestowed on her little cankered dwarf Wulstan, whose droll tricks and impish mischief occasionally possessed the power of diverting the black gloom that oppressed her, after she had been compelled to resign the gaiety and splendour of the court for a solitary residence in Corfe Castle, one of the royal demesnes in Dorsetshire, which had been the favourite hunting palace of her late husband King Edgar, who had been accustomed to spend much of his time there; and thither Elfrida had been allowed by her generous step-son to retire, with her son Prince Ethelred and a train suitable to the dignity of his father's widow. Instead of being moved by the kindness and forbearance of the young king, Elfrida continued in secret her treasonable practices against him. She had already sacrificed her first husband Ethelbald to her ambition, and she only waited a suitable opportunity of attemping the life of Edward. The Archbishop Dunstan was, however, fully aware of her cruel and perfidious disposition, and he strictly guarded his royal pupil from all her machinations and conspiracies against his person, and warned him perpetually against the imprudence of either admitting her to visit the court, or trusting himself in the vicinity of her abode. So implicitly had the cautions of Dunstan been attended to by those about the young king, that for a period of three years he had been prevented from holding the slightest intercourse with Elfrida and her son.</p>
<p>But the affectionate heart of Edward yearned towards his younger brother, whom he earnestly desired to embrace once more. The cares of royalty, the sceptre of a divided realm, and the severe restrints and self-sacrifices imposed upon him by his austere but faithful guardian Dunstan, were grevious to the youthful monarch, who, in addition to these, was compelled to submit to the stern discipline of a monastic education; and the mode in which learning was communicated in those days was equally fatiguing to the preceptor and painful to the pupil. Elementary books were not then written to facilitate the progress of education. There were not above three copies of a meagre dictionary in existence in England, and lessons were learned from dictation, till, by frequent repetition the student. committed them to memory, or, according to the ancient phrase, <quote>"got them by heart."</quote></p>
<p>These impositions were distasteful to the young king, and were often sadly contrasted by him with the pleasures and joyous freedom of his early years, before his accession to the regal dignity had burdened him with the heavy fetters of state and deprived him of the amusements of his age, and above all of the company of his brother Ethelred, his tenderly-beloved living plaything.</p>
<p>The royal manor and castle of Corfe had been, as I said before, the favourite residence of the deceased king his father, during whose reign it had been a constant scene of gaiety and festivity. The happy days of Edward's childhood had been spent there, and when he compared the gloomy routine and fatiguing employments of his present mode of life with the sweet remembrances of that pleasant time, he felt disposed to regard the demesne of the queen dowager as a sort of Eden, contrasted with which the rest of his kingdom was but an extensive wilderness.</p>
<p>This desire of revisiting the scenes of his infancy, <quote>"his home,"</quote> as he emphatically styled Corfe Castle, became more pressing in proportion as it was resisted by his inexorable guardian and the rest of the wise counsellors by whose decision he, while a minor, was compelled to abide, and he secretly resolved to embrace the first opportunity that might occur for the gratification of his wish.</p>
<p>Meantime, unremitting application to the laborious studies and public duties which Dunstan enjoined, impatience of the restraints imposed upon him, and above all, his incessant pining for the beloved scenes and companion of his childhood, produced a visible change in his health. His fading cheek, heavy eye, and languid appearance, at length attracted the attention of Dunstan, who, in common with most ecclesiastics of that period, possessed a considerable knowledge of physic, and was desirous of administering to his royal pupil a medicine which he considered might be efficacious to him.</p>
<p><quote>"It is of no avail," said Edward, rejecting as he spoke the proffered cup, "it is not a nauseous compound of drugs that will restore me to health. It is the devertisements, the relaxations, and the companionships of my age that I require."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Know you not, Oh! King, that as the lord of a mighty nation, you are called upon to put away childish things, and to employ your precious time in fitting yourself for the performance of the important duties which pertain to your exalted station?"</quote> said the archbishop.</p>
<p><quote>"Ah! station full of sorrow!" exclaimed the young king, "how gladly would I exchange its gilded fetters for the healthful toils and envied freedom of a shepherd boy!"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"In the same sinful spirit of discontent and rebellion against the dispensations of the Most High, thou wouldst have coveted regal dignity, hadst thou been doomed to bear the hardships and privations of a herdsman's lot,"</quote> replied the archbishop.</p>
<p><quote>"I could endure them all patiently, yea joyfully, were I permitted to breathe the fresh free air of dale and down in liberty," rejoined the youthful monarch, "and to solace myself with the company of one dear familiar friend, were it but a day."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Thou art a perverse boy, and knowest not the value of a real friend when thou hast found one," said Dunstan reproachfully. "Thou deemest me harsh, and my counsels bitter, because, instead of dissembling with thy folly, I labour to convince thee that a king is the property of the nation that permits his authority, and that it behoves him to sacrifice his dearest wishes where they interfere with the duty he owes to his people."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Nay, but, my father," said Edward, "my present desire is so simple in its nature, that it concerneth no one beside myself, or I would not urge it."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"It is, I know, of no avail to reason with thy perversity to-day," said Duns tan impatiently. "What wouldst thou?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I would fain hunt the deer in my royal chase of Wareham,"</quote> replied the king in a hurried voice, being awed by the stern manner of his preceptor into dissembling half his wish.</p>
<p><quote>"Is that all?" demanded Dunstan, fixing his penetrating eye upon the varying cheek of the youthful king; "thou mightest well call thine a simple wish, and if thou hadst added foolish thou hadst not said amiss."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I knew thou wouldst call it so, my Lord Archbishop,"</quote> said the king, turning away.</p>
<p><quote>"Nay, Edward, nay, this is mere childishness," resumed the archbishop, taking the feverish hand of his royal charge, "if hunting the deer be thy desire, far be it from me to withstand thee in such a trifle, especially as thou thinkest the fresh air and jocund exercise of following the hound horn will restore thy health and spirits; but why shouldst thou speak of the distant woods of Wareham for thy divertisement, when thou hast thy royal and wide extended forest and chase of Waltham so close to thy loving city of London, that thou mayest enjoy goodly pastime there this very day, with thy noble thanes, and earldormen and trusty burgesses for thy company and guards?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"No," replied the king, "I love not to seek my game amidst such gaping crowds of idle followers, and I will not hunt at Waltham to-day."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Thou shalt find goodly sport in the fair forests of Windsor, if thou wilt seek it there," said Dunstan, "or in thy chase at Sheen, or at Greenwich and the Black-heath."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I do not incline to hunt at Windsor," replied the King, "nor yet at Sheen, nor Greenwich, nor the Black-heath, nor any where but at Wareham, where my royal father was wont to rouse the deer."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Wareham is too near to Corfe Castle, the abode of the bold bad woman,thy guileful stepdame Elfrida,' replied Dunstan. "It is a vicinity fraught with peril to thee, and thou shalt not go thither, Edward."</quote></p>
<p>Edward was sad and sullen during the remainder of the day.</p>
<p>The next morning there was an evident access of the low fever that hung about the young king; he was languid and dispirited, and would neither attend to his studies, nor enter into any of the little plans laid out for his amusement by his courtiers at Dunstan's instigation.</p>
<p>When Dunstan perceived this, and observed that his royal pupil sickened and rejected his food from day to day, he said to him again, <quote>"Edward, what wouldst thou?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I told thee before," replied the youth, "but it was in vain, that I did but desire to breathe the sweet air of the Dorsetshire hills and downs, and to hunt the deer in my pleasant woods of Wareham, and lo! thou didst refuse me this little thing."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Because I saw thou wert like a foolish bird, wilfully bent on falling into the snare of the cunning fowler," returned Dunstan, "and I know thou hast now only revealed a part of thy purpose, which is to visit Corfe Castle."</quote></p>
<p>A deep blush overspread the pale cheek of the young king, as he protested that he had no such intention.</p>
<p><quote>"I fear thou dost dissemble with thy true friend, King Edward," said the archbishop. "In troth, my son, it is only natural that thou shouldst desire to embrace thy brother Ethelred; but, give up this wild whim of thine, and I will send for the young prince to London when a convenient season shall befall."</quote></p>
<p>A feeling of false shame withheld the king from acknowledging that he had not dealt candidly in the matter, and he redoubled his protestations that his whole desire was simply to spend a few days in hunting the game in Wareham forest, which he prayed the archbishop not to deny him.</p>
<p><quote>"Thou shalt go," said Dunstan after a long pause, "but on condition that thou dost not visit Corfe Castle, nor hold any intercourse with the Queen Elfrida, nor any of her people."</quote></p>
<p>Edward accepted the terms, but in the secret hope that accident would bring him to a sight of his brother without a direct violation of his promise.</p>
<p><quote>"The word of a king ought to be an obligation more sacred than the oath of another man," said Dunstan when they parted; "as you observe yours, so be your speed, my son."</quote></p>
<p>Indisposition, languor, and melancholy, were alike forgotten by Edward, when, with a gallant train of nobles and gentles, attended by jolly hunters and falconers, with hawks and hounds, he left London to follow the sylvan sports in the fair wolds and vales of Dorsetshire.</p>
<p>They set forth with merry blasts of horns, baying of hounds, prancing of steeds, waving of plumes and broidered scarfs and mantles, jingling of falcon bells and blithsome caroling of jocund voices, so that all who met them paused to admire their goodly array and sprightly cheer; but Dunstan beheld the departure of his royal charge with a sort of prophetic fear which he could neither repress nor hide.</p>
<p><quote>"Thou goest, Edward," said he, when he bestowed his parting blessing upon him" thou goest like a foolish bird from beneath its mother's wing ere it be fully fledged for flight; God grant that thou escape the jaws of the serpent that are even now expanded to devour thee."</quote></p>
<p>Edward was touched, and indeed surprised, at the pathetic tenderness of his stern preceptor's solemn farewell; for Dunstan was an austere man, who, generally speaking, appeared dead to all human affections, and insensible to the softer emotions of the human heart. Yet now he folded the young king in his arms, and wept over him like a mother over the child of her bosom, who is about to be torn from her for ever.</p>
<p>Edward's purpose was shaken, and for a moment he felt disposed to forego his long-wished and eagerly anticipated journey, but the temptation was too strong to be thus easily resigned. It is a difficult matter for young people, especially princes, to know who are their real friends. The young king, who had always been accustomed in his childhood to receive deceitful flattery and caresses from Elfrida, could not prevail upon himself, notwithstanding her treasonable attempts to supplant him in the succession, to regard her as a personal enemy. He knew her to be ambitious, but he could not believe that she was wicked; on the contrary, he excused her conspiring to exclude him from the throne on the plea of her natural preference for her own son, and he secretly considered Dunstan's opinions respecting her as harsh and injurious, although he had never ventured in direct terms to tell him so. The archbishop, though tenderly attached to his pupil, and labouring incessantly to promote his interest, was of too stern and unbending a character to study to please him. He had a plain and uncompromising manner of reproving his faults and telling him unwelcome truths, which had the effect of wounding his self-love and offending his pride.</p>
<p>It is a correct observation, that people will sooner forgive a serious injury than overlook an affront, and Edward, although his step-mother had endeavoured to deprive him of a throne, was inclined to regard her more in the light of a friend than the man who had successfully. vindicated his rights, and watched day and night for his weal. But then, Elfrida had flattered his foibles, and during his father's life had procured him a thousand improper indulgences; while Dunstan controled his inclinations wherever he considered it for his interest so to do, and subjected him to the restraints of a useful and virtuous education.</p>
<p>It was with feelings of the deepest regret that this faithful guardian consented to the departure of his royal pupil, especially as he considered it incompatible with his sacred calling, venerable age, and high vocation, to accompany the court on. a hunting party. To the best of his power he provided against any imprudence on the part of the young king, by surrounding his person with a sufficient number of grave and incorruptible counsellors, whose wisdom and authority he hoped would restrain the vivacity and rash daring of that gay company.</p>
<p>The impression of his guardian's solemn warning and unwonted tears at parting, remained for some days on the mind of the young king, and strengthened his resolution of doing nothing in direct violation of his promise, though he continued to indulge a secret hope that some lucky chance might afford him the pleasure of an interview with Prince Ethelred and the Queen, for he certainly cherished a desire of seeing the guileful Elfrida as well as her son. Wareham Chase was only six miles distant from Corfe Castle, and, contrary to the advice of the sage monitors to whom the archbishop had delegated his trust, he continued to follow the game in that vicinity.</p>
<p>One day, when he had, as much by design as accident, outridden his train in pursuit of a white doe of peculiar beauty and fleetness, he perceived through a forest vista the towers of Corfe Castle rising in the distance, over wood and vale, like the gray crown of the richly-varied landscape.</p>
<p>At that sight a thousand sweet and pleasant remembrances of his early days, connected with that beloved spot, rushed to the mind of the young king, and filled his eyes with tears. The boisterous excitement of the chase was forgotten, and. dropping his silken bridle on the neck of his gallant gray, he gave himself up to pensive and regretful feelings on the subject of its being denied him to revisit the home of his childhood.</p>
<p><quote>"And thou, my fair-haired brother," said he, "who art now, perchance, tossing the ball in the castle court, or chasing the butterfly from flower to flower over the garden lawns and gay parterres, in the thoughtless glee of thine happy age, thou thinkest not, I ween, that the fond brother in whose bosom thou wert wont so oft to nestle when tired with playful gambols, is so near, if indeed thou dost still remember him."</quote></p>
<p>While the young king was still indulging in these thoughts, a strange sharp cry near him caused him to look round, when, to his surprise, a grotesque little creature, that appeared neither like a child nor an animal, but something between both, sprang out of a thicket near him, and coiling itself up in the form of a ball, rolled down the hill before him. Edward's curiosity was excited, and he spurred his horse forward to overtake it, but when the creature perceived his intention, he bounded up, and erecting himself to his full height, which did not appear to be above two feet, he whirled his long lean arms aloft, and clapping his hands above his head, uttered a cry so long and shrill that it pierced the king's ears with a painful sensation, and was answered back by a thousand echoes from grot and hill, in the deep solitude of Wareham forest. The tales of malign faries and woodland imps was then in common belief, and the young king thought it possible that this singular creature, whom he had thus unexpectedly encountered, might be one of these mysterious beings of whom he had heard so much. But then he had also a shadowy remembrance of having seen in his early childhood a sprightly animal that bore a grotesque resemblance, both in form and face, to a diminutive man, which played a thousand antic tricks, and was greatly caressed by the queen and her ladies; but it had either been stolen or made its escape from the palace of Corfe in the neighbouring woods; and though a period of nine or ten years had elapsed since this event, King Edward was simple enough to believe that this was the veritable creature whose loss had been so deeply lamented by all the pages and females of the royal household, and he determined to overtake it, if possible, whether it were monkey, fairy, or imp.</p>
<p>But the object of his pursuit, however diminutive in person, was more than a match in swiftness of foot for the fleet hunter on which the kin<quote>" was mounted, and, like the goblin page in Sir Walter Scott's Lay of the Last Minstrel, where Edward "rode on* mile he ran four,"</quote> yet with provoking subtlety he continued always to keep in sight, as if he enjoyed the race and wished to continue it. Sometimes, when he had climbed a hill, whose steep rugged ascent was scaled with difficulty by the royal steed, he paused on the brow, laughing with malicious glee, and swinging himself from bough to bough among the embowering trees, till the king was nearly upon him, then darting forward with the speed of an arrow, he resumed his flight, and in a few minutes distanced his pursuer. Sometimes, when Edward thought he had entirely lost all trace of the tantalizing elf, and was meditating how he should recover the track from which he had so widely deviated, he heard the same sharp shrill cry that had first announced his appearance close to his ear, and perceived a round rough head, covered with shaggy brown locks of tangled hair, through which peered a pair of small keen black eyes, peeping amidst the foliage or clustering ivy of some gnarled oak that wreathed its low fantastic arms across the path, from which, as soon as he perceived he was observed, he leaped with a sudden bound, and clapping his hands and shouting at the top of his voice, started away again down some opening glade of the forest, leaving horse and rider far behind. Both were now thoroughly hot and weary ; the young king, who had been on horseback ever since daybreak, and fasting withal, thought of giving up this unprofitable chase as a matter of necessity, on account of the jaded condition of his good steed, and his own fatigue and faintness. But the object of his pursuit appeared in still worse plight, limped as if lame, and sometimes rested on the green turf as if thoroughly exhausted weeping and uttering low moaning plaints, and King Edward thought he was now secure of his prize, especially as they had reached the farthest boundary of the forest, and were on the verge of an open park, towards which the urchin began to creep on all fours, occasionally rolling himself over and over at a great rate.</p>
<p><quote>"This," thought the young king, "is his last effort, and I presently shall overtake him on the plain when once he loses the vantage of the underwood and thickets;"</quote> and lest he should alarm him into plunging amidst its tangled mazes once more, he followed him at a cautious distance till he emerged from the forest shades, and proceeded at a gentle pace across the park, the enclosure of which they had entered.</p>
<p>Edward had been led on from glade to glade through the green mead, in his eager pursuit of the wily urchin, without pausing to examine the scenery through which he rode, or he might possibly have recognized many objects familiar to him in days long past; nor was it till he had leaped the enclosure of the park, and looked around, that he discovered he was in the immediate vicinity, almost at the gates of Corfe Castle, which rose before him in all its well remembered regal grandeur, as in the days when his father, King Edgar, kept court there. The intermediate time, the important events that had since befallen the youthful monarch, the solemn warning of his guardian against his venturing near this much loved abode of his childhood, and his own promise not to do so, were alike forgotten by King Edward when he found himself so unexpectedly on the spot to which he had, in fact, been artfully lured by Wulstan, the queen's dwarf, the misshapen little elf, who had led him such a weary chase through the forest, and now, uttering an impish yell, fled down the broad avenue of oaks that led to the castle with the speed of a lapwing, and seizing the bugle that hung at the portal, blew a blast that drew all the inhabitants to the windows and balconies, to learn the meaning of the summons.</p>
<p>The king, perceiving that it would now be impossible for him to withdraw unobserved, considered that it would have a very mean appearance, if, after having been seen on the demesne of Queen Elfrida, he retreated without paying his respects to her; and by no means regretting that the rules of courtesy would afford an excuse to himself for departing from a promise which had been so reluctantly wrung from him, he advanced towards the castle.</p>
<p>The queen, who was perfectly aware of his approach, hastened to the gates to receive him, and offering him the homage of her knee, entreated him <quote>"to enter and partake of the banquet which she had prepared in anticipation of this visit, on hearing that he was hunting the deer in the neighbouring forest of Wareham."</quote></p>
<p>Notwithstanding the fascinating sweetness of the queen's address, and the persuasive softness of her voice and language, there was an expression lurking in the sidelong glance of her large blue eye, and sometimes in the deceitful blandishment of her voice and manner, that, in spite of his partial opinion of her character, recalled the archbishop's impressive warning, and gave the king an idea that she meditated some sinister design.</p>
<p>This secret misgiving induced him to decline entering the castle, <quote>"on account," he said, "of the lateness of the hour, and the expediency of his returning immediately to Wareham, lest his court should take the alarm at his protracted absence."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Thou art hot and weary, my royal lord," replied the queen, respectfully kissing the hand of the youthful monarch, "and thou wilt not surely depart till thou hast, at least, tasted a cup of spiced hippocras, if thou will not feast with me to-day."</quote></p>
<p>Edward was not willing to offend the queen by declining this offer, especially as he was fatigued, and stood in need of refreshment, and was, moreover, too much inclined to linger near the much-loved abode of his childhood ; and while Elfrida took the silver goblet from her bower maiden, who stood holding it on a richly chased salver, he eagerly inquired for his young brother.</p>
<p><quote>"Thy servant, Ethelred, is sick within the castle, or he had come with me to the gate to offer homage to his lord," replied the queen. "He hath long pined for thy presence, like a plant that hath been deprived of sunshine."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Send quickly, my lady mother, and fetch him hither," exclaimed the king: "I also have panted to embrace him."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Drink hael* first, my gracious lord,"</quote> replied Elfrida, presenting the cup to the king.</p>
<p>* The Saxon phrase for drinking health, from which expression that once general custom was derived, which means, <quote>"Wish health," or "I wish your health."</quote></p>
<p>He received it with a smile, and bowing courteously to the queen, repeated the accustomed salutation of <quote>"Waes hael,"</quote> and raised it to his lips, but the same moment he felt the stab of an assassin's dagger from behind. He dropped the fatal goblet from his hand, and cast a look of keen but silent reproach on his perfidious step-mother; but ere he could recover his bridle reign, to turn his steed for flight, the deadly thrust was repeated, and his treacherous assailants closed about him to prevent his escape.</p>
<p>Indignation at the deep-laid iniquity of the snare into which he had suffered himself to fall thus easily, rendered the young king insensible for a moment to the smart of his wounds; but fully aware of the desperation of his situation, he struck the rowels into the side of his mettled gray, and the good steed as if equally conscious of his master's peril, with one gallant bound broke through the murderous circle, and dashed across the plain with the speed of an arrow just discharged from the bow, and presently distanced the pursuit of the traitors, who continued to trace the course the wounded king had taken by the red life-drops that tracked his path through the forest.</p>
<p>The last sound that fell on Edward's ear was the piercing cry of a child in mingled grief and terror, it was the voice of his brother Ethelred, who, on beholding the barbarous deed from a window of the castle, filled the air with his shrieks and lamentations. The assurances of his guilty mother, that it was for his sake, and to make him a king, that the crime had been perpetrated, instead of consoling him, increased his distress to such a passionate degree, that the queen, who considered that his tears a reproach to herself, becoming infuriated at what she styled his unseasonable sorrow, threw herself upon him, and beat him in so violent a manner* that it was for some time a matter of doubt to those about her whether she had not slain her own son in the ungovernable transport of her rage,that son, for whose advancement she had the moment previous caused so deadly a crime to be perpetrated in her very presence.</p>
<p>The unfortunate Edward meantime, though be had succeeded in outstripping the pursuit of his ruthless enemies, was sensible of the approach of a foe whom he could neither resist nor flee from. Life ebbed apace from the unstanched wounds, the landscape reeled in confusion before his swimming eyes, he struggled with the deadly faintness that was stealing over him, and laboured to rally his failing powers; but the hand of death was heavy at his heart; the reigns dropped from his relaxing grasp, and he fell from the saddle to the ground.</p>
<p>* <quote>"With a wax altar-taper;" say the Saxon chroniclers that being the first weapon that fell in the way of this furious and unreasonable woman."</quote></p>
<p>It is related that his foot unfortunately catching in the stirrup, the body of the king, whether dead or living is not exactly known, was much mangled, in consequence of being dragged at a rapid rate alone the ground by the terrified horse, which at length stopped of his own accord, at the gate of a blind woman's cottage. This lonely woman, notwithstanding the deprivation of sight under which she laboured, ascertained that some fatal accident had befallen the unfortunate youth, and though ignorant of his rank, she humanely carried the bleeding body into her humble dwelling, and laid it on her own bed, while she hastened to procure assistance. The wicked Elfrida, whose emissaries had tracked the horse to this place, sought to conceal her crime by causing the corpse of the murdered king to be thrown down a deep well; but there, in consequence of the evidence of the blind widow, it was presently discovered by his sorrowful friends, and her guilt was proclaimed to the whole world, by the indignant Archbishop Dunstan, at the coronation of her son Ethelred, and he then predicted that a crown so obtained could never prosper with the descendants of this bad woman.</p>
<p>The high rank of the queen protected her from the punishment due to her crime; but she was regarded with hatred and contempt by all mankind; and feeling herself an object of horror to her own son, for whose advancement she had perpetrated this barbarous deed, and above all, tormented by the fearful stings of her own accusing conscience, she retired to the gloomy shades of a convent, where she spent the residue of her days, vainly endeavouring, by constant penances and fasts, to expiate her crime.</p></tale>
<historical_summary>When Edward, the eldest son of Edgar the Peaceable, succeeded to his father's throne, under the guardianship, or regency, of Archbishop Dunstan, his dominions were exceeding prosperous ; besides swaying the sceptre of the united Saxon heptarchy, he was bretwalda, or emperor over the whole island of Great Britian, the kings of Scotland and Wales paying him vassal homage for their several domains; in short, he held the same rule that Edward Plantagenet the First afterwards endeavoured to obtain, and succeeded only in regard to Wales. The united wisdom of Edgar the Peaceable and his prime minister, Dunstan, established the English sceptre in peace and prosperity. During his reign the native Danes were kept in bounds, and the invading ones repelled. This desirable order of things was entirely subverted by the crime of Elfrida, the stepmother of King Edward; for, during the weak reign of her son and pupil, Ethelred, the Danes obtained the mastery of England, and inexpressible miseries ensued to the country, which Had a pause when Edward the Confessor succeeded to the throne, and were afterwards renewed, with tenfold horror, by the invasion of another set of Northmen, under William the Conqueror. The whole of this wretchedness may be traced to the personal wickedness of one woman.
<p>Elfrida was the only child of the Earl of Devonshire, and was considered the greatest beauty and the richest heiress in England. The king, Edgar, who was then a widower, having lost his wife, Elfleda the Fair, the mother of his eldest son, Edward, thought that the heiress of Devonshire was worthy to be his consort; but, as she had been brought up in great retirement, and Edgar required beauty and grace in a queen, as well as riches, he thought that report might have exaggerated these qualities in Elfrida, and sent Ethelwold, his favourite, to visit Elfrida, and give him a true account of her claims to personal beauty. Ethelwold went accordingly, and found the young lady so charming that he fell in love with her, and wooed her for himself instead of his master, to whom he gave a false testimony, declaring that Elfrida had no charms but in her rich inheritance. Edgar immediately relinquished the design of marrying her, and his favourite observed, that although Elfrida was not qualified to be the wife of a great king, she was a wealthy match, and he should, if the king would permit him, marry her himself forthwith. King Edgar consented, and Ethelwold soon after wedded the fair heiress, who, being unconscious of the greater honour intended her, thought she had made a good match. In a little time the fair wife of Ethelwold began to be malcontent at finding that her husband kept her mewed up at her own castle, instead of bringing her to the capital, to share in the festivities of the most splendid court in Europe. At last a report reached Edgar's ears that he had been deceived, and after vainly questioning his favourite, why he never brought his bride to court, the king announced his intention of paying a visit to Ethelwold and his wife. Terrified at this information, Ethelwold went to his lady and confessed his deception, imploring her to appear as ugly and awkward as she could, and rather strive to disgust the king than otherwise; for if she seemed as lovely as nature had made her, the king would never forgive him the false witness he had borne. Elfrida promised all things, and as her husband thought he had her heart, he was a little calmed. Nevertheless, both the vanity and ambition of Elfrida being mortified, she was enraged at losing a crown, and still more so at having been so misrepresented. She did her utmost to charm King Edgar, who was enfuriated at the falsehood of Ethelwold. The unfortunate husband was soon after found murdered in a wood, when on a hunting party. Whether he was assassinated by the order of the king, or his wife, was never clearly understood ; but soon after Edgar made Elfrida his queen, and she became the mother of his youngest boy, Ethelred, who was seven years old when his father died.</p>
<p>At the death of Edgar the councils of the kingdom were divided into Dunstanites and Anti-Dunstanites. The partisans of Dunstan were the advocates of church government, as dependent on the pope; these supported the claims of Edgar's eldest son, Edward, and the opposite party set up those of Ethelred, the son of Elfrida. Between Dunstan and the queen the most implacable hatred subsisted, which was not abated when that great prelate and minister carried his point, and established his pupil and ward on the throne, which it is to be noticed, although hereditary in one family, was not confined to the eldest son, being rather elective in the royal family. Elfrida retired to the royal domain of Corfe Castle, and privately meditated mischief, which, owing to the vigorous government of Archbishop Dunstan, and his power with the Witenagemot, she was not, for three years able to carry into effect.</p>
<p>It is here desirable to inform the youthful reader the meaning of the word Witenagemot, more than once mentioned in this tale. The Saxon word Witenagemot signifies a <quote>"Meeting of the Wise."</quote> It was the name of the grand legislative assembly of the Anglo-Saxon empire, bearing some resemblance to the parliaments of the present day. It was originally composed of five estates, or ranks of men. The king was the first estate, and the head of the assembly. Next to him sat the clergy, which were bishops, abbots, and priests and monks, elected for their superior abilities from different dioceses; the clergy being the only learned men in the kingdom, and as knowledge is more powerful than strength, they took precedence of the nobles and warriors, and sat next the king: the clergy ranked as the second estate. The great earls, or heads of counties, then called aldermen, sat with the tributary princes of Scotland and Wales, with whom they ranked equally, and, like them, wore gold collars and caps of maintenance: these were the nobles, and were reckoned the third estate. They filled the station of the present house of lords, only they are mixed with the clergy, as our house of peers has bishops, or spiritual lords, among its members. The fourth estate was composed of thanes, or warriors, but, as well as warriors, they were obliged to be landowners. An East Anglian (or Norfolk and Suffolk thane) was obliged to possess forty hydes of land to enable him to sit in the Witan: but a thane from Wessex, or the south of England, only needed to possess five hydes (a hyde of land is one hundred acres). This fourth estate is similar to our knights of the shire, or members returned for counties. The fifth estate were farmers and tradesmen, called in the Saxon language churls and burgesses, or burghers; they stood at the lower end of the hall, and when a law or doom was passed, seldom said more than yea, yea, or nay, nay; these were elected by their neighbours from every town and village, four good men and the reeve, or manager of the parish money, from each. It is plainly to be seen that the fourth and fifth estate of the Witenagemot, united together, were the origin of our house of commons; but a century after the Norman Conquest, they turned out the farmers and peasants, and only kept the burgesses, or representatives of towns and cities. It is likewise to be noted, that the Witenagemot was held in one great hall, or on a heath or common, while the house of lords and the house of commons, in our days, sit in council in different halls, excepting they meet together when the king convenes or dismisses them.</p>
<p>Tradition says, that the Witan existed before the Saxons or Romans conquered Britain, and was held by our British ancestors at Stonehenge, that surprising circle of masses of stone which is still to be seen in the midst of Salisbury Plain. In the times of our Saxon ancestors, when a law passed in the Witan it was called a doom, instead of our modern phrase of act of parliament, or a statute.</p>
<p>In our days the kingdom of Sweden, which was partly the mother country of the Anglo Saxons, still retains the grand national tribunal of the five estates, and the last (the peasants) are a grave, venerable body, men of few words, but of great respectability, and not without power in the commonwealth.</p>
<p>It was the great council of the Witenagemot that confirmed the title of young Edward, and placed him under the tutelage and guardianship of Archbishop Dunstan, who was a most austere man, deserving the reprobation of posterity as a fanatic and persecutor; but during the short reign of Edward, and the long one of Edgar his father, he was a great statesman, and most able prime minister over a happy people and a flourishing country. Elfrida and her partisans were kept in awe by his vigorous administration; but that which public rebellion dared not attempt, accident and private malice effected. Edward and Ethelred, though their several parties might strive to render them enemies, were united by strong ties of brotherly affection. Edward chose to hunt the deer at Wareham, in the neighbourhood of Corfe Castle, in Dorsetshire, where Elfrida and Ethelred then resided. It is said that with youthful curiosity he was purposely allured to the castle by the tricks of Wulstan, the queen's little cankered dwarf, and he advanced alone to the lofty hall of his mother-in-law. She received him at the doorway, and kissed him. Before the king alighted, a cup was offered, and as he was quaffing the draught, one of Elfrida's attendants (some say herself) stabbed him. The wounded prince had yet strength enough to spur his horse, but fainting on the road, his body was dragged in the stirrup by the affrighted animal, who stopped at the cottage of a blind widow. Life was then extinct in the young king, whose bloody corpse was frightfully mangled by the rough road over which he had been hurried. Elfrida thus gained her wicked ends, for Ethelred, the younger son of Edgar, was then sole heir. So little did the boy exult in his mother's successful crime, that, when told of his brother's dreadful death, he wept most bitterly; this conduct enraged his violent mother to that degree, that she seized a wax taper and so belaboured her child with it that she almost killed him. This vile woman became afterwards abjectedly penitent; she built a convent on the spot where Edward's body was found, and ended her life in childish penances; among others, history records that her terror of the supposed approach of the evil one was so great, that she sought to evade his clutch by covering her body all over with little crosses. She died in extreme horror.</p>
<p>There are two terms that require explanation in this tale, the expressions Drink heal and Weas heal. They were the forerunners of a custom not entirely obselete among us, and simply meant an invitation to drink one's health, and the answer before drinking of<quote>" Wish health." A little after this time, when the lawless Danes filled the land with violence and treachery, and actions similar to this murder of Elfrida's became of daily occurrence in the land, the custom of pledging a companion when drinking was usual; and the phrase of "I pledge you,"</quote> still in use in country places, meant originally, Your honour is pledged not to stab me while the cup is at my lips. </p>
<p>Ethelred, who seems to have had, naturally, kindly feelings, being brought up under the misrule of his violent, capricious mother, proved a weak and bad king, and his misgovernment laid the foundation of nearly three centuries of misery to his country, which might have been averted, if his brother Edward, a prince of great promise, and assisted by able ministers, had not been cut off by the murderous Elfrida.</p></historical_summary>
<tale><tale_title>WOLSEY BRIDGE; OR, THE BOY BACHELOR.</tale_title>
<p>On the south side of the ancient passage leading from the street to the churchyard of St. Nicholas, was formerly situated the commodious house of Thomas Wolsey, a substantial butcher and grazier, of the town of Ipswich, in the sixteenth century.</p>
<p>This Thomas Wolsey was one of those persons with whom the acquisition of wealth appears to be the sole purpose of existence. It was his boast <quote>"that he had thrice trebled the patrimony he had derived from his father," from whom he had inherited his flourishing business, besides some personal property. Acting in direct contradiction to that injunction of the royal psalmist, "If riches increase, set not your heart upon them,"</quote> his very soul appeared to dwell in his money bags, his well attended shambles, or the pleasant lowland pastures where the numerous flocks and herds grazed, the profits on which he calculated would so materially improve his store. He made no show, no figure among his fellow townsmen; never exchanging his long blue linen gown, leathern girdle, and coarse brown hose, for any other apparel, except on a Sunday, when he wore a plain substantial suit of sad coloured cloth, garnished with silver buttons, and the polished steel and huge sheath knife, which he usually wore at his side, were exchanged for a silver hiked dagger and an antique rosary and crucifix. Satisfied with the conviction that he was one of the wealthiest tradesmen in Ipswich, he saw no reason for exciting the envy of the poor or the ill will of the rich, by any outward demonstrations of the fact, but continued to live in the same snug plain manner to which he had been accustomed in his early days, making it the chief desire of his heart that his only son, Thomas, should tread in his steps, and succeed him in his prosperous and well established business, with the same economical habits and an equally laudable care for the main chance.</p>
<p>The maternal pride of his wife, Joan, who was the decendant of a family that could boast of gentle blood, prompted the secret hope that the ready wit and studious habits, together with the clerkly skill and learned lore which the boy had already acquired at the grammar school, might qualify him for something better than the greasy craft of a butcher, and perhaps one day elevate him to the situation of port reeve or town clerk. But for the boy himself, his youthful ambition pointed at higher marks than the golden speculations of trade, or the attainment of lucrative offices and civic honours in his native town. From the first moment he entered the grammar school, and took his place on the lowest seat there, he determined to occupy the highest, and to this, in an almost incredible brief period of time, he had rapidly ascended; and, though only just entering his twelfth year, he was now the head boy in the school, and in the opinion of his unlearned father, <quote>"knew more than was good for him."</quote></p>
<p>As soon, indeed, as his son Thomas had learned to write a <quote>"fair clerkly hand, to cast accounts, and construe a page in the Breviary,"</quote> he considered his education complete, and was desirous of saving the expense of keeping him longer at school; but here he was overruled by his more liberal minded wife, Joan, who, out of the savings of her own privy purse, paid the quarterly sum of eight-pence to the master of the school, for the further instruction of her hopeful boy, Thomas, whose abilities she regarded as little less than miraculous. Persons better qualified than the good wife, Joan Wolsey, to judge of the natural talents and precocious acquirements of her son, had also spoken in high terms of his progress in the learned languages, and predicted great things of him. These were personages of no less importance than the head master of the Ipswich grammar school, and the parish priest of St. Nicholas, the latter of whom was a frequent visitor at the hospitable messuage of master Thomas Wolsey the elder, on the ostensible business of chopping Latin with young Thomas, and correcting his Greek exercises for him ; but no doubt the spiced tankards of flowing ale, and the smoking beefsteaks, cut from the very choicest part of the ox, and temptingly cooked by the well-skilled hands of that accomplished housewife, Joan Wolsey, to reward him for his good report of her darling boy's proficiency, had some influence in drawing father Boniface thither so often.</p>
<p>The bishop of the diocess himself had condescended to bestow unqualified praise on the graceful and eloquent manner in which, when he visited the school, young Wolsey had delivered the complimentary Latin oration on that occasion. The good natured prelate had even condescended to pat his curly head on the conclusion of the address, and to say, <quote>"Spoken like a cardinal, my little man!"</quote></p>
<p>From that moment young Wolsey had made up his mind as to his future destiny. It was to no purpose that his father tried the alternate eloquence of entreating, reasoning, promises, and threats, to detach him from his engrossing studies, and induce him to turn his attention to the lucrative business of a butcher and grazier. The idea of such servilely earned pelf was revolting to the excited imaginanation of the youthful student, whose mind was full of classic imagery, and intent on the attainment of academic honours, the steps by which he projected to ascend to the more elevated objects of his ambition.</p>
<p>The church was, in those days, the only avenue through which talented persons of obscure birth might hope to arrive at greatness, and young Wolsey replied to all his father's exordiums urging him to attend to the cattle market, the slaughter house, or the shambles, by announcing his intention of becoming an ecclesiastic.</p>
<p>The flush of anger with which this unwelcome declaration had clouded the brow of the elder Wolsey was perfectly perceptible when he returned home after the fatigues of the day to take his evening meal, which his wife, Joan, was busily engaged preparing for him over the fire with her own hands. <quote>"I knew how it would turn out all along of your folly, mistress, in keeping the boy loitering away his time and learning all manner of evil habits at the grammar school, when he ought to have been bound apprentice to me, and learning our honest craft for the last two years,"</quote> muttered the malcontent butcher, throwing himself into his large arm chair, lined with sheepskins.</p>
<p><quote>"What a coil the woman keeps up with her frying-pan,"</quote> continued he, peevishly, on perceiving that the discreet Joan appeared disposed to drown the ebullitions of his wrath in the hissing and bubbling of the fat in her pan, as she artfully redoubled her assiduity in shaking it over the blazing hearth.</p>
<p><quote>"Why Joan," pursued he, "one cannot hear oneself speak for the noise you make."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"The noise is all of your own making, I trow, master,"</quote> replied Joan, continuing to stir her hissing sputtering pan briskly as she spoke.</p>
<p><quote>"I say, leave off that frizzling with the fat in that odious pan,"</quote> vociferated he.</p>
<p><quote>"So I will, master, if you wish to have burnt collops for your supper to night,"</quote> replied Joan, meekly.</p>
<p><quote>"I don't care whether I have any supper at all," replied the butcher, testily; "lam vexed, mistress."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Good lack! what should happen to vex you, master?" responded his wife. "I am sure the world always seems to wag the way you'd have it go; but losses and crosses in business will chance, even to the most prosperous, at times. Is one of your fat beasts dead?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"No!"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Some of your sheep been stolen?"</quote></p>
<p>« No!"</p>
<p><quote>"Mayhap then, some customer, whom you have suffered to run up a long score, is either dead or bankrupt?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Worse than that, mistress."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I prythee, good Thomas, let me hear the truth at once," exclaimed the startled Joan, upsetting the frying-pan into the fire in her alarm. "The misfortune must be great that hath befallen you, if it be reckoned by you worse than the loss of money."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Why, mistress, do not you reckon the perverse inclinations of one's own flesh and blood a more serious calamity than the loss of substance?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Ay, master; but that is a trial we have never had the sorrow of knowing; since our only son, Thomas, albeit I say it who ought not, is the most dutiful, diligent, and loving lad, that ever blessed a parent's heart,"</quote> said the fond mother, melting into tears of tenderness as she spoke.</p>
<p><quote>"Hold thy peace, dame," cried the indignant husband, darting a look of angry reproach on the offending youth, who had been comfortably reposing himself on an oaken settle by the fire side, reading Virgil's Eneid by the light of the blazing embers, during the whole of the discussion, without concerning himself about any thing, save to preserve the beloved volume from being sprayed by the fat which the frying pan, in falling, had scattered in all directions. "That lad, on whom you bestow such foolish commendations," pursued old Wolsey; "that lad, whatever might have been his former virtuous inclinations, hath now disappointed all my hopes, for he hath turned an errant scape-grace, and refuseth to become a butcher, though the shambles he would inherit from me are the largest, the most commodious, and best frequented with ready-penny customers, of any on the market hill. Moreover, it is a business in which his grandfather got money, and I, following in his good steps, with still better success, have becomeI scorn to boast, but the truth may be spoken without blameone of the wealthiest tradesmen in the borough."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Then the less need, my master, of enforcing such a clever lad as our Thomas to follow a craft which is so unsuitable for a scholar,"</quote> observed Joan.</p>
<p><quote>"There," groaned the butcher, "was the folly of making him one, which hath been the means of teaching him to slight the main chance, and to turn his head with pagan poesies or monkish lore. Would you believe it, mistress Joan,he hath had the audacity to profess his desire of becoming a student at the university of Oxenford?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"And why should he not, master Wolsey, since he promiseth to become a learned clerk?"</quote> asked the proud mother.</p>
<p><quote>"To what purpose should he go thither?"</quote> said the father.</p>
<p>"Marry, master, to increase his learning, and to put him in the way of becoming a great man,'* responded mistress Joan.</p>
<p><quote>"A great man, forsooth!" echoed her husband, contemptuously; "</quote>who ever heard of a butcher's son becoming a person of distinction?</p>
<p><quote>"I have heard, Sir," said young Wolsey, closing his book eagerly, "</quote>I have heard of a destitute swineherd becoming a pope.</p>
<p><quote>"Indeed!"</quote> ejaculated his father, with an air of incredulity.</p>
<p><quote>"Yes, Sir, it was Nicholas Brekespeare, afterwards Pope Adrian the fourth, the only Englishman who ever filled the papal chair, but perhaps not the last whom learning, combined with persevering enterprize, may conduct to that eminence."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Ho! ho! ho!" cried the butcher, bursting into a loud laugh; "I wist not of the high mark at which your ambition aimeth, son Thomas! Well, if enabling you to become a servitor in Magdalen College will advance your holiness one step towards the possession of St. Peter's keys, I will not withhold my assistance and my blessing, though much I doubt whether it will carry thee into the Vatican, or whatever you call it, of which you and father Boniface are always talking."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"And what if it do not carry him quite so far, master," interposed Joan, "didst thou never hear of the proverb, He who reacheth after a gown of cloth of gold shall scarcely fail of getting one of the sleeves?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Ay, mother," cried young Wolsey; "and when I am a cardinal, my father will thank you for the parable."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Ah! if I ever live to see that day, son Thomas!"</quote> observed the butcher.</p>
<p><quote>"Why should you doubt it, master?"</quote> asked mistress Joan.</p>
<p><quote>"Because, wife, it is easy to talk of dignities and honours, but to obtain them would be attended with difficulties, which I doubt our simple son, Thomas, will find insurmountable."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I shall, at least, lose nothing in making the attempt,"</quote> observed young Wolsey.</p>
<p><quote>"There is your mistake, boy; you will lose something very considerable,"</quote> replied his father.</p>
<p><quote>"Dear father, what can that be for which the learning I shall acquire will not make ample amends?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"The most flourishing butchery in Ipswich, simpleton! which, if once lost through your inconsiderate folly, you may study till doomsday, and acquire all the learning in popedom and heathenesse into the bargain, without being able to re-establish it in its present prosperity,"</quote> returned the mortified father, with a groan.</p>
<p>A smile, which the younger Wolsey strove in vain to repress, played over his features at these words.</p>
<p><quote>"Ay, scorn and slight the substantial good that is within your reach for the sake of the vain shadow which is beyond your power to obtain, Thomas Wolsey,"</quote> said his father, with great bitterness.</p>
<p><quote>"My dear father, you know little of the powers of the human mind, or of the mighty things which its energies, when once roused, and directed towards one object, may effect."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I tell you, Thomas, that the end which you propose is impossible."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Sir," replied young Wolsey, "I have blotted that word out of My dictionary."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I like your spirit, young man," said his father, "albeit, it savoureth a little of presumption."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"That remains to be proved," said his son, "and I am quite ready that my earnestness should be tried by any test you may be inclined to demand."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I shall hold you to your word," replied his father, "and condition, that if you take up your bachelor's degree within four years of your entering Magdalen College, then shall you proceed in the course of life on which you are so determinately bent; but if you fail in doing this, then shall you return to my house, and submit your future destiny to my disposal."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"If I take it not up within two years of my entering the college, barring accidents of sickness or death, then strip me of the learned stole of a clerk of Oxenford, and chain me to your girdle as a butcher's slave for life,"</quote> replied the youth with a heightened colour.</p>
<p><quote>"Thou hast pledged thyself to that which thou canst not perform, son Thomas," replied his father. "Who ever heard of a boy of fourteen taking up a a bachelor's degree of Oxenford?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Thou shalt hear of one, anon, mine honoured father,"</quote> said young Wolsey.</p>
<p><quote>"I will engage that thy mother shall have the finest baron of beef in my shambles to roast for dinner on the day on which I hear that news,"</quote> rejoined his father.</p>
<p><quote>"See that you keep my father to his promise, mother," said the youth, "for I shall travel night and day, in hopes of being the first to communicate the intelligence, or at any rate, to arrive in time to come in for a slice of the beef while it be hot."</quote></p>
<p>The important object being now accomplished of obtaining the consent of the elder Wolsey to his son's entering the university of Oxford, the lad commenced his journey on the following day for that ancient seat of learning. He was on foot, for the sturdy butcher, his father, though well able to send him thither on a stout pack-horse, attended by one of his own men, was determined to afford no facilities for an enterprize to which he had so little relish.</p>
<p>The loving care of mistress Joan Wolsey had supplied the youthful candidate for scarlet stockings and cardinal's hat with a few silver groats for his expenses on the road, and a needful stock of linen and other necessaries, which he carried in a leathern wallet over his shoulder at the end of a stout oaken staff; but that which young Wolsey considered more precious than either money or apparel, was a letter of recommendation from the head master of the Ipswich grammar school to the master of Magdalen College.</p>
<p>This credential obtained for its lonely and friendless bearer that attention which his juvenile appearance, diminutive stature, and his coarse and travel-soiled attire, would most probably have failed of attracting. Having passed his examination with great credit to himself, he was admitted as a servitor of Magdalen College. In this novel situation young Wolsey had some difficulties, and not a few hardships and privations to contend with; but these, when weighed against the mighty object which engrossed all his thoughts, were as dust in the balance, and the only effect they had was to increase his persevering diligence. At the end of the first term he had made a progress which astonished his masters and fellow students. Before the two years had expired within which the lad had pledged himself to take up a degree, an attempt which his father, with reason, judged unattainable by reason of his tender age, the good-wife Joan Wolsey, in great haste, entered the shambles, where her husband was preparing to put an uncommonly fine baron of beef into the basket of a nobleman's servant, and laying hands upon it, exclaimed, <quote>"Why, Thomas Wolsey, what are you about to do with that meat?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"To send it to the house of my lord, according to order, to be sure, mistress,"</quote> replied the butcher, with a look of surprise.</p>
<p><quote>"An it had been ordered by King Henry himself, he should not have it to-day,"</quote> said mistress Jean.</p>
<p><quote>"Is your wife delirit, master Wolsey?"</quote> asked the servant.</p>
<p><quote>"One would suppose so by her wild words,"</quote> said the astonished butcher,-who knew not what to think of the behaviour of his usually discreet spouse</p>
<p><quote>"If I be, master, it is with joy," replied Joan Wolsey; "but the truth is, I came hither to claim the finest baron of beef in the shambles, which you said I should roast for dinner on the day on which you heard the news of our son, Thomas Wolsey, taking up a bachelor's degree at Oxenford."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"And who brought you the intelligence, mistress?"</quote> demanded her husband.</p>
<p><quote>"A joyful messenger, my good man, for it was the boy himself, (blessings on him !) dressed in his bachelor's gown, and bearing the certificate of his admission as a fellow of Magdalen College."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Humphrey!" cried the delighted father, turning to his head man, "take that baron of beef home to my house, and help thy mistress to spit it, and put it down to the fire, that my boy bachelor may dine off the best joint in my shambles; and do you, master Ralph," added he, turning to his lordship's servant, "make my duty to my lord, and ask him if he will be pleased to put up with rump or ribs to-day, since the baron of beef, for which his housekeeper hath sent, was bespoken nearly two years before his order came, and my good dame hath come to claim my pledge in earnest."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Which my lord is too strict an observer of his own word to wish you to forfeit on his account, I am sure, master Wolsey," said Ralph; "and when I explain the pleasant cause for which you have made bold to disappoint his lordship of his favourite dish to-day, he, who is himself a scholar and a patron of learning withal, will hold you excused."</quote></p>
<p>This day being a holiday, the head master of the Ipswich grammar school, several of young Wolsey's chosen friends among the scholars, and the good-humoured curate of St. Nicholas, were invited to partake of the baron of beef which the young bachelor had so honourably earned, and which mistress Joan Wolsey cooked in her most approved style, to the great satisfaction of her husband and the guests.</p>
<p>This was one of the long vacations, but no season of idleness to young Wolsey, whose unremitting application to study impaired his appetite, and rendered him languid and feverish, which his anxious mother perceived, and feeling some alarm lest his incessant mental toil might injure his naturally feeble constitution, she communicated her uneasiness to her husband, and asked him if he could not contrive some little pleasant employment for him, which would have the effect of diverting him for a few days from his sedentary occupations.</p>
<p><quote>"Ay, ay, dame," replied old Wolsey, "I have a choice bit of pastime for the boy; he shall go with Humphrey and Peter and Miles to buy "beeves off the Southwold and Reydon commons and marshes."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"That would do well enough, master, if the lad were any judge of cattle, which I fear, with all his college learning, he is not,"</quote> responded mistress Joan.</p>
<p><quote>"You may well say that, mistress," rejoined the butcher, "for though he hath been born, bred, and nourished in the midst of such matters, and he is observant enough in other things, yet I would answer for it, he knoweth not the difference between a fat beast and a lean one, a Scot or a home-bred, yea, scarcely between a long horn or a short; and were I to send him on this business of mine without my shrewd foreman, Humphrey, to instruct his ignorance and detect the knavery of the sellers, he would bring me home pretty bargains of beasts against the Easter festivals. Why these fat monks of Reydon, who are far better skilled in grazing for the Ipswich and Yarmouth markets than in their church Latin, would be sure to palm their old worn-out mortuary cows upon him for fine young heifers, and make him pay the price of three-year-old steers for their broken-down yoke oxen that had ploughed the convent lands for the last ten years. But, as I said before, Humphrey shall go with him, who is used to their tricks of old, and will bid them half their asking price at a word, which our Thomas would be ashamed of doing to men of their cloth were he left to himelf, so he shall only have the pleasant part of the business, to wit, listening to the chaffering, and paying down the money when the price is agreed upon by those who are wiser in such matters than himself."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"And how do you propose for him to perform the journey, master, for the places whereof you speak are many miles distant?"</quote> said Joan.</p>
<p><quote>"Under forty miles, wife, which will be no great stretch for Miles and Peter (who are to drive the cattle) to walk; as for Thomas, he shall ride my grey mare, and Humphrey can take the black nag, and give Miles and Peter a lift behind him by turns, which will ease their legs, and make it a pleasant journey for them all. Ah! that part of Suffolk is a fine grazing country to travel through. I am sure I shall envy Thomas the prospect of so many herds and flocks as he will see on those upland meads and salt marshes; but he will think more of chopping Latin with the monks of Blitheborough, and looking over their old musty books and records, which could never give a hungry man his dinner, than of all the sensible sights he might see by the way."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Every one to his vocation, master," replied Joan Wolsey; "</quote>yours it is to feed the bodies, and my Thomas's will be to nourish the minds of men with a more enduring food than that which you have it in your power to provide.*'</p>
<p><quote>"Gramercy, mistress!" said the butcher, with a grin; "one would think he had been feasting you on some of his improving diet, for you begin to discourse like a doctor."</quote></p>
<p>The next day, by peep of dawn, the quartette set forth from St. Nicholas's passage on their expedition, on which no one reckoned more than young Wolsey, who, wearing his college cap and gown, the latter of which was tucked up round his waist, lest its long full skirts should impede his horsemanship, was mounted on his father's easy-pacing grey mare. For the convenience of riding he was accommodated with a pair of the old man's boots, which drew up far above his knees, and were wide enough to admit three pair of legs like the stripling's slender limbs. He rode cautiously at the head of the cavalcade, taking care to keep close to Humphrey, who jogged along very comfortably on the black nag, whose mettle, if ever it had possessed any, was tamed by the wear and tear of fifteen years of service in the butcher's cart.</p>
<p>Miles and Peter trudged steadily along with their quarter staffs in their hands, relying on their own excellent pedestrianism to reach the ultimate place of their destination almost as soon as the horsemen of the party, whose steeds they knew would be sorely jaded before they reached St. Peters, Wangford, where their master had directed them to crave lodging far the night of the monks of Clugni, who there occupied a cell dependent on the monastery Of Thetford, which also was the parent house of the cell at Reydon.</p>
<p>The two saucy knaves occasionally exchanged sly glances, and cracked dry jokes on the unsuitable array and cautious riding of the young Oxford student, their master's son, and the steady jog-trot of Humphrey, who rode quite at his ease on a soft sheepskin which supplied the place of a saddle, by being tightly buckled with a broad leathern strap under the belly of the black nag, whose quiet temper allowed her to be ridden safely without the aid of stirrups.</p>
<p>The sun rose brightly in a soft April sky by the time they reached Woodbridge. Young Wolsey had now become familiar with the paces of the grey mare, and the excitement of the exercise, the beauty of the morning, the invigorating freshness of the air, and lovely succession of new and agreeable objects, contributing to raise his spirits, he soon began to assume a little more of the cavalier, and occasionally used the whip and the spurs, in defiance of all Humphrey's prudential cautions. Nature had well qualified the youthful student, both in form and agility, to play the graceful horseman, and before they arrived at Wickham Market, the skill and boldness with which he managed his steed was a matter of surprise to the whole party. At this little town they stopped, and refreshed both men and beasts with a substantial breakfast, and then set forward on their journey with renewed spirits. Young Wolsey, who had a purpose of his own to answer, put his father's mare to her speed, and soon left the pedestrian Peter, and the hapless nag with its double burden, of Humphrey and Miles, far in the rear, regardless of their shouts of <quote>"Fair play, master Thomas! fair play!" and "Alack, alack, Sir, have a care of master's mare!"</quote> </p>
<p>But the stripling, who liked not the repeated hints which Humphrey had given him of the propriety and expediency, to say nothing of the kindness of giving poor Peter a lift behind him, now they were clear of the houses, was determined to ride forward, not wishing the bachelor's cap and gown to appear in such close fellowship with the butcher's blue and greasy buff of his father's men. Besides, he greatly desired, instead of keeping the jog-trot pace that suited their convenience, to gain an hour or two to spend with the monks of the Holyrood at Blitheborough, and to examine the antiquities, architecture, and localities of that ancient and interesting place, through which the route chalked out for him by his father lay; but the elder Wolsey had strictly charged Humphrey in his hearing, <quote>"not to permit his young master to delay their journey, by wasting his time and theirs in prating Latin gibberish with the black locusts of Blitheborough" (as he irreverently styled those worthy anchorites), "especially as he did not want to deal with them for sheep, the last he had bought off their walks having proved a very poor bargain."</quote></p>
<p>Now young Wolsey, when he heard this caution, secretly resolved to arrange matters so as to enjoy the conference with the monks without either infringing his father's directions, or being pestered with the company of his blue-frocked retainers. So, without allowing himself time to observe the pastoral Benhall, Kensale, or the picturesque village of Yoxford, which was then, as now, one of the prettiest in Suffolk, or even pausing to bestow more than the tribute of a passing glance of interest on Cockfield's Gothic Hall, at that period newly built, and rising proudly from its embowering woods, he prest his mare on, and though, as well as her, sorely wearied with the unwonted number of miles he had traversed, his youthful spirits carried him forward with unabated energy, till, on descending the last hill after crossing the extensive track of purple heath, known by the name of Blitheborough Sheep-walks, that most stately structure, the church of the Holy Trinity, rose before him, not in the dilapidated grandeur which even now strikes the eye of the eastward traveller with astonishment and delight, as, grey with the mantling lichens, and crumbling with the neglect and injuries of revolving centuries, it bursts upon his view, amidst surrounding desolation, but in all the magnificence of the monastic ages, untouched by time and unimpaired by accident, with the bright sunbeams playing and flashing on the many-coloured stains of its wide and lofty windows.</p>
<p>Young Wolsey checked his horse, and gazed upon this noble edifice with the enthusiasm natural to the future founder of colleges and gothic buildings; then slowly, and looking often backwards, he proceeded to the cell and chapel of the Holy Rood, which indeed was so contiguous to the spot that he was able still to enjoy a close view of the new church, as it was then called, while he partook of the good cheer which the hospitable fraternity produced for his refreshment, and to which the hungry stripling did ample justice. As the bells were chiming for vespers, monastic etiquette compelled him to accompany the monks to their pretty chapel, for which building the traveller would now look in vain, as its only relics are the crumbling group of broken gray arches, so thickly mantled with ivy and crowned with wild flowers, that form such an interesting feature in the landscape of the desolated village of Blitheburgh,</p>
<p>When the evening service was concluded, the friendly monks gratified their visitor with an interior view of the church of the Holy Trinity, and pointed out to him its rich carvings, screens, trellises, and magnificently sculptured and emblazoned roof, not forgetting to call his attention to the antique tombs which, as tradition reports, once covered the mortal remains of Annas, king of the East Angles, and Ferminius, his son, who were slain in a bloody battle with Penda, the pagan king of Mercia, which was fought in the adjacent marshes of Bulcamp, or Baldkemp. From the leads over the south aisle, they made him observe the fine sea view of Southwold, Walberswick, and the city of Dunwich, well known to him in ecclesiastic history as the ancient metropolitan city of the kingdom of the East Angles, where Saxon monarchs kept court in the olden time, and the bishop of the two counties held his see, till the resistless waves of the German Ocean committed such ravages as compelled the diocesan to remove his episcopal see to Thetford, and afterwards buried that time-honoured seat of learning and royalty (Dunwich), with its walls and brazen gates, its fifty-two churches and religious houses, together with its numerous streets and public buildings, beneath its raging waters.</p>
<p>With a sigh the young student turned from the contemplation of the melancholy wreck of ancient splendour, which the fallen city of the East Anglians presented even in the sixteenth century, when several churches and numerous vestiges of its former greatness still survived the storms of ages and the assaults of the hungry waves; but what would he have thought had he seen it as it now is, reduced to a few ruinous fishermen's huts, and of all its churches and religious houses, retaining only the roofless shell of one, in which divine service is no longer performed! Doubtless he would have applied the words of the lamentation pronounced by the prophet over the desolation of Tyre: <quote>"Is this your joyous city, whose antiquity is of ancient date? Who hath taken this counsel against Tyre, the crowning city, whose merchants are princes, whose traffickers are the honourable of the earth?"</quote> </p>
<p>Young Wolsey had been too deeply engaged in the contemplation of these interesting localities to embrace the opportunity of displaying his own learning to the friendly monks, who had treated him with the respect which his natural talents and early acquirements were well calculated to inspire, and pressingly invited him to sojourn with them during the rest of the evening, and pass the night in their dormitory; but the importunities of Humphrey (who, with Peter and Miles, had arrived while he was at vespers, and having refreshed themselves and the black nag, were now clamorous to proceed) prevailing over his desire of accepting an invitation so agreeable to his own inclinations, he took a loving farewell of the hospitable fraternity, promising to find some way of gratifying his wish of passing a few hours with them on his return. Then mounting the gray mare, he rode forward at a gentle pace with his weary and somewhat malcontent companions, who scrupled not to reproach him for the want of good fellowship he had displayed in deserting their company. Nor did Humphrey fail to exert the privilege of an old and trusted servant, by rating his young master soundly for having over heated the gray mare on a long journey, besides incurring much peril of accidents both to himself and that valuable animal, on account of his being an inexperienced rider, and quite unacquainted with the road. The young student, who was of course rather impatient of these rebukes, which he considered very derogatory to the dignity of a bachelor of Oxford to receive from butchers and cattle drovers, endeavoured to escape from them by a repetition of his offence, namely, outriding the party; but that was no longer in his power, for he had fairly knocked up the gray mare, so that she was unable to compete with the shabby nag on which Humphrey rode, and the only alternative left him, was to listen meekly, or to turn a deaf ear, to the reproaches that assailed him right and left, and amuse himself with his own reflections, or in contemplating the charms of the varied landscape before him, when, on ascending the gentle hill leading from Blitheburgh, he found himself among the rich woods and cowslipped meads of Henham, whose castellated hall, then the residence of the Brandons, rose in all its gothic grandeur over grove and vale, as the crowning object of the prospect, but was soon after hidden behind the intervening screen of deep embowering shades, which were then almost impervious to the light of day, and converted the advancing gloom of evening into early night. No sooner was the party involved in this security, than the offended trio, Humphrey, Miles, and Peter, united their chorus of grumbling at their detention at Blitheburgh, declaring that they were benighted, and should in all probability be robbed of the sum entrusted to them for the purchase of the cattle.</p>
<p>The welcome sound of the curfew bell of St. Peter's, Wangford, however, soon informed them that their apprehensions were groundless, and put them into better humour, by advertising them that they were not more than a mile distant from the place of their destination, and presently, after emerging from beneath the sombre shadows of Henham's oaken glades, they found themselves once more in day light, and in the immediate vicinity of the<quote>""- pretty village of Wangford, which, with its picturesque monastery and chapel of St. Peter"</quote>s, crowning a gentle eminence, lay full before them.</p>
<p>The pastoral rivulet of the Wang, from which the name of this hamlet was derived, was soon forded by the weary travellers, who, proceeding to the little convent, obtained without difficulty food and shelter for the night. The next morning, as soon as matins were over, which service they of course considered themselves bound to attend, they set forward on their short journey to the neighbouring monastery of Reydon, which, as I said before, was a detached branch of the cell of St. Peter's, both dependencies on the monastery of Thetford.</p>
<p>Leaving its green bowery labyrinth of sylvan lanes, its antique hall and park, its aboriginal forest. and the gray spire of its venerable church, and all that was pleasing and attractive in the landscape of the Reydun, or the red hill (which its Saxon name signifies), to the left, Humphrey guided the party through a narrow, wet, and incommodious road, to a mean conventual building, situated at the most desolate extremity of the parish, among the salt marshes.</p>
<p>If Wolsey had expected to find learning, piety, or hospitality among this fraternity, he was certainly much disappointed; for a set of more illiterate and narrow-minded men than these Reydon monks were never congregated together. Far from expressing the least interest in the acquirements of their young guest, they received the intelligence of his proficiency in the learned languages with dismay, and appeared far better pleased with the conversation of Humphrey, Peter, and Miles, which indeed was more in unison with their tastes than that of the scholastic Wolsey, whom they entertained with long dissertations, not on the fathers or the classics, but on the most profitable breeds of cattle, and the most approved methods of fatting swine, in all which matters they were very fluent, and appeared to consider it passing strange that a butcher's son possessed so little knowledge on such interesting topics. They also discussed the best method of curing white bacon, as the fat of pickled pork is called in that part of Suffolk. On this delectable article Wolsey and his party had the felicity of supping that evening, which he afterwards declared was the dullest he ever spent in the whole course of his life.</p>
<p>The next morning, though the bells chimed for matins, the monks made no movement to enter the chapel, as THEIR matin service was confined to that ceremony; and when Wolsey expressed his surprise at such unorthodox neglect of the prescribed offices of holy church, they replied <quote>"that it was neither a sabbath nor a festival, and their swine must be attended to."</quote></p>
<p>When this interesting duty had been zealously performed by the fraternity, they proceded with their guests to the marshes where their cattle fed, where a long and animated discussion took place between Humphrey and the superior of the convent respecting the price, the merits, and defects of the beasts which Humphrey deemed most worthy of his attention, in which so much time was wasted that the dinner bell rung before they had settled the price of so much as one bullock.</p>
<p>At this meal they were again regaled with white bacon, which appeared a standing dish in this convent, for it was produced at supper, breakfast, and dinner; at the latter, indeed, there was the addition of a huge dish of hard dumplings, with which they devoured a quantity of pork dripping by way of sauce.</p>
<p>The morning had been fine but showery, in the afternoon a heavy rain set in, which rendered it impossible either to visit the cattle-marshes again, or to proceed homewards, which young Wolsey recommended his father's men to do, on the conviction of the impossibility cf ever concluding a bargain with these frocked and cowled dealers in cattle and feeders of swine.</p>
<p>The rain, however, continued without intermission, and the malcontent student was compelled to remain where he was till the <quote>"plague of water,"</quote> as he called this unwelcome downpouring, should abate.</p>
<p>How to pass the weary interval with men whose minds and manners were so dissimilar to his own, he knew not. Books they had never a one except their breviaries, and their acquaintance with these was a doubtful matter to the young student, since no persuasions of his could induce them to perform vespers when the bells chimed for that service, although it was a wet afternoon on which nothing else could be done.</p>
<p>Whether to attribute this to their utter disrelish to any thing of a spiritual nature, or to their fear of betraying their ignorance in latin and other deficiencies to one whom they feared would detect their blunders, and perhaps report them to their superior at Thetford, Wolsey knew not, but he was so heartily weary of his sojourn among them, that nothing but the most pathetie remonstrances and earnest protestations on the part of Humphrey against such a measure, prevented him from retracing his steps to Blitheburgh, in spite of the rain, and remaining with the monks of Holy-Rood Chapel till his father's people had transacted their business with the conventual graziers of Reydon.</p>
<p>The following morning proving fine, they again proceeded to the marshes in the hope of striking a bargain^ which was at length concluded; but not till after a delay that appeared to the impatient Wolsey almost interminable, which time he employed, not in listening to the altercations of the buyer and sellers of the bullocks, but in strolling through the marshes, and making observations, till he obtained a view of Blitheburgh on the line of country that intervened, across which he persuaded himself a much shorter cut to that village might be made than by following the usual road through Wangford. Just as he had come to the resolution of attempting that route, the convent bell rang for dinner, and summoned him to a sixth meal of white bacon, of which the monks ate with as keen an appetite as if it had been the first time they ever partook of that savoury fare, of which Wolsey was by this time almost as weary as of the company of the founders of the entertainment.</p>
<p>The bullocks, twelve in number, were now driven into the convent yard, and Humphrey called upon his young master to pay down the price for which he and the monks had agreed, at the average sum of one pound ten shillings a head, which he pronounced an unconscionable sum with a sly wink of intelligence at the Oxford student, by which he gave the youth, who was about to take his words literally, to understand that he was well satisfied with the bargain. In fact, the Reydon monks, shrewed and exacting as they were, had met with more than their match in the calculating, experienced Humphrey, who, without making a boast of his wisdom in this way, knew how to judge of the weight of a living ox almost to an odd pound. Till the business was concluded, the money paid, and the receipt given, he had forborne to taste of the convent meed or ale, though both had been pressed upon him with an earnestness passing the bounds either of politeness or hospitality by the cunning monks, who hoped to overcome Humprey's cool clear judgment and caution, by means of the merry brown bowl; but now all fear of being overreached in his bargain in consequence of such an indulgence was at an end, Humphrey, malgre all his young master's expostulations, demanded the lately rejected beverage, of which he, with Miles and Peter drank pretty freely, though not so much as they would have done had the cloistered cattle-dealers been willing to produce more, which they were always sparing in doing after a bargain had been definitely struck.</p>
<p>The draughts which the trio had swallowed had had, however, the effect of putting them all into such good humour, that when Wolsey on mounting proposed to them his plan of changing the roundabout route though Wrangford, for a straight cut acroos the marshes to Blitheburgh, they offered no objection, for even the prudent Humphrey was desirous of adopting any expedient by which they might make up for the time they had lost in drinking the convent ale after the business was transacted. </p>
<p>The monks assured them the project was feasible, since the branch of the Blithe which separated Hentham and Reydon was fordable, and they would save a considerable distance by crossing the river, but their hospitality did not extend to the civility of sending one of their swineherds or goose-boys to point out the precise spot at which the attempt might be made without danger to passengers. The stream was much swollen in consequence of the late heavy rains; Humphrey and the drovers paused on the rushy bank, each prudently declining to be the first to try the ford. Wolsey, who was piqued at their doubts of his assurance <quote>"that it was safe! perfectly safe!"</quote> though he would rather have had one of the others show a demonstrable proof that there was no danger, urged his reluctant mare forward.</p>
<p><quote>"Hold, master Thomas, hold! for the love of St. Margaret of Rissmere,"</quote> cried Humphrey, who was suddenly sobered by the sight of his young master's peril, and the recollection that the stream was deep and muddy.</p>
<p>Now this St. Margaret of Rissmere was a saint for whom Wolsey had neither love nor reverence, for she was the patroness of the unlearned monks of Reydon; so, without heeding the adjuration so pathetically addressed to him in her name, he boldly plunged into the dark and swollen waters of the dangerous ford. He was, as we have seen, an inexperienced rider on dry land, but a more skilful horseman than the stripling student would have found it a difficult matter to retain his seat and guide the terrified animal, who presently lost her footing, and began to kick in the muddy slippery ooze of which the bed of the Blithe and its dependent streams are composed, and which, having recently been violently disturbed by the heavy rains, was in a state of complete ferment and liquefaction.</p>
<p>Wolsey, though encumbered with his bachelors gown, which he had not this time taken the precautionary measure of tucking up and fastening to his girdle, courageously maintained his seat till the mare, exhausted with her violent efforts, sunk, and left him floating on the stream. He was an expert swimmer in the clear calm Orwell, or the pastoral Gipping, his native streams, but scarcely a fish that had been used to the fresh sparkling element of such rivers as these, could have steered its course in the dank vortex of brackish mud in which poor Wolsey was immersed.</p>
<p>Peter and Miles stood aghast at the accident, uttering doleful cries for help, without venturing to make a single effort to save the almost exhausted youth. Humphrey, the faithful Humphrey, at the first alarm had dismounted from the nag, and was preparing to plunge into the stream to save his master's son, or perish in the attempt, when one of Sir Richard Brandon's wood-rangers, who had seen the accident and hastened to the spot, reached the end of the long pole he had been using in leaping the marsh ditches to the youth, by which assistance, the stream being narrow at that place, he was enabled, though not without some difficulty, to gain the opposite bank, from which, as soon as he had cleared his eyes and mouth of the salt, bitter, and unsavoury ooze he had been compelled to swallow, he called out in an accent of distress to Humphrey, <quote>"Oh! Humphrey, Humphrey! what shall we say to my father about the gray mare?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"St. Margaret of Rissmere take the mare!" sobbed Humphrey, who appeared to consider the patroness of Reydon as somehow chargeable with their mishap; "don't talk of her, my dear boy, when she had nearly been the death of you. Howsomdever, master Thomas, you must never undertake to lead those who are wiser than yourself short cuts any more. I hope you have had enough of this precious ford, that was to take you such a near way to Blitheburgh."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Why so it will, you simple fellow," said Wolsey," laughing, and wiping the mud from his face, "do not you see the beautiful church over those marshes almost at my elbow? I shall bestir myself to get there as fast as I can, now I am over the water, that I may get dry clothes, a good supper, and some pleasant chat with the worthy monks of the Holy Rood, which will console me for the drenching I have got."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Alack, alack! master Thomas ! what is to become of us and the bullocks?"</quote> howled Miles and Peter from the opposite bank.</p>
<p><quote>"You may come over the river to me, an you like,"</quote> responded Wolsey, from the other side.</p>
<p><quote>"We durst not do that for our lives,"</quote> cried the trembling drovers.</p>
<p><quote>"Then turn yourselves and the bullocks about, and find the road to Wangford as well as ye can: Humphrey knows the country, and he will guide ye to Blitheburgh by that roundabout way, ye poltroons, unless ye choose to stay where ye are till I am a Cardinal, when it is my intention to build a bridge over this sweet stream, to prevent other travellers from incurring the peril which I have done, in endeavouring to ford such a bottomless abyss of mud."</quote></p>
<p>We will not follow the young bachelor to Blitheburgh, where doubtless he met with agreeable entertainment, nor will the limits of our tale admit of our tracing the progressive steps by which he in the sequel attained to the eminence to which his ambition, even in childhood, prompted him to aspire. By keeping bis attention constantly fixed on this object, he found it at last within his reach ; but was he then contented? Let me answer this query with anotherWhen was the desire of human greatness ever satisfied? I refer the juvenile reader to the historical summary for further particulars of the career of this extraordinary man, who, when he had attained to the coveted rank of Cardinal, though he was burdened with the cares of the prime minister of England, which office he held during twenty years of Henry the Eighth's reign, was not forgetful of his promise of building a bridge over the stream which had so nearly proved fatal to himself. The name of the bridge, and the local tradition thereunto belonging, will long, I trust, exist to preserve the memory of an action of pure benevolence to future ages.</p></tale>
<historical_summary>Thomas Wolsey was the only son of Thomas and Joan Wolsey, and was born at Ipswich, in August, 1471. His father was a butcher and grazier. The house in which Wolsey was born is still shown, and is situated in the south side of the passage leading to St. Nicholas' churchyard; and in the ancient shambles, or butchery, which lately stood upon the Cornhill, at Ipswich, was a stall, or stand, with the initials of Wolsey's father carved thereon, and some other insignia which tradition points out as belonging to him. Wolsey's father, though a man of low trade, was in opulent circumstances, and connected with some of the most respectable families at Ipswich, either by descent or marriage. His will is preserved, wherein it appears that he left his lands to his wife Joan, and the rest of his wealth divided between his wife and son, reserving however a handsome bequest to the church of St. Nicholas and the poor of the parish.
<p>There are floating traditions in Suffolk, which intimate that the butcher Wolsey was desirous that his son should follow his own trade, and in pursuance of this plan, he made him assist is driving the beasts he bought at various markets for sale and slaughter at Ipswich. In one of these expeditions he nearly lost his life, at a dangerous ford at Reydon. over a branch of the river Blythe, when driving a number of bullocks which had been purchased from Reydon salt marshes and South wold common. It is further said, that he promised on the spot, <quote>"that if ever he became cardinal, he would build a bridge at that dangerous spot."</quote> Wolsey kept his word, and when he arrived at the high dignity his youthful ambition even then aimed at, he built a bridge at Reydon, which is to this day called Wolsey Bridge.</p>
<p>It is a singular thing, that although forced to join at times the inconsistent occupations of a drover and student, that Wolsey was admitted as a bachelor of arts at Magdalen College at the age of fourteen, from which extraordinary circumstance he was called the Boy Bachelor. It must be observed, that students were entered at the universities much earlier in former times than is usual at this era; but to take a degree at the age of fourteen, justly excited universal astonishment throughout the kingdom, in all men who were devoted to, or interested in, learning; and Wolsey was marked as a character likely to rise in the church, which was then the only path to high distinction. We must not forget to note here, that young Wolsey had been as promising at Ipswich school as he was as a student at Magdalen College; so says Lloyd, one of his biographers. The first step to his subsequent greatness in the state was his appointment to the situation of domestic chaplain to Henry the Seventh, a monarch who himself had received a conventual education, and was a discerning patron of learned men, knowing well how to appreciate them. There were, as matters stood in the middle ages, two roads in the church to great distinction: one was, for a leraned priest to practise great austerity and sanctity, so that he was considered a saint and revered by all men; and the other, tr devote himself regularly to business as a statesman, and govern church and state as prime minister, which was done in England by whoever held the office of lord chancellor. The latter path was chosen by Wolsey, who had a particular inclination to a court life, and declared, that <quote>"if he could set one foot in the court, he would soon introduce his whole body."</quote></p>
<p>The first affair of state in which he was concerned, was a mission from Henry the Seventh to Maximilian, Emperor of Germany, who was then at Bruges. After receiving his instructions at the royal palace of Shene (now called Richmond), where the king then kept court, he set out on his errand. We must consider the state of the roads, and the delays of travelling at that time, which were so great that a journey from Ipswich to London took at least a week, and even in the memory of man, a day and night was spent on the road when travelling by a stage coach. Therefore, when Wolsey presented himself before Henry the Seventh at the end of three days, that monarch naturally supposed that his envoy had not yet set out, but had returned for fresh instructions, and he began to reproach him for his dilatoriness, when, to his astonishment, Wolsey declared that he had actually been at Bruges, and performed his mission successfully. <quote>"Ay," answered the king, "but upon farther deliberation, finding that something had been omitted in your instructions, I despatched a messenger after you with fuller powers." To which Wolsey replied, "that he had indeed met the messenger on his return, and on communicating with him, found that he had anticipated the view that Henry had taken of the business, and performed his negociation with the emperor precisely according to Henry's second thoughts of the affair, so that there was no need of a second journey."</quote> Henry was highly pleased with his envoy's sagacity and promptitude, and with its favourable issue; he gave him public thanks, and declared him in council fit to be entrusted with the management of affairs of the utmost importance. He rewarded him with the deanery of Lincoln, and the prebends of Walton, Brindhold, and Stow; and to complete his good fortune, his graceful and eloquent relation of the particulars of his embassy before the council, attracted the notice of the Prince of Wales, afterwards Henry the Eighth, who grew from that time extremely fond of his company.</p>
<p>Such was his introduction as a statesman. From the first year of the reign of Henry the Eighth, 1509, till 1529, the butcher's son ruled England with absolute power, and at the same time with great ability. These twenty years was the happiest epoch of Henry's reign; for, after Wolsey's fall, the sovereign commenced a career of crime, and his people of misery. Wolsey filled the high offices of Grand Almoner, Archbishop of York, Lord Chancellor, Pope's Legate, and Cardinal. He carried personal splendour and state higher than any subject ever did before or since, and would most likely have died in possession of all these honours, had he not aimed at the highest then in the world, even at the Popedom; but his intrigues to reach this pinnacle of a churchman's ambition, lured him to such imprudent steps as caused the downfall of his mighty power, and a few weeks after he died of grief at Leicester Abbey.</p>
<p>The munificent public works executed by Wolsey, both as prime minister and from his own private revenue, are greater perhaps than any subject ever performed. He reendowed and reformed his own university of Oxford, with such magnificence, that he is almost considered as its founder, according to its present state. His love for his native county of Suffolk was great, and the college he built and endowed in his mother town of Ipswich, is a proof that he had the magnanimity not to be ashamed of his origin; but the rapacious tyrant, whose caprice caused his downfall, seized upon the revenues and destroyed the infant college, of which only one of the gateways remain. But perhaps the most extraordinary work in which this great man engaged, was, that he partly wrote and wholly revised, Lillye's grammar, a work of such use that it was in general use within the last century. Such was the love of this mighty statesman for learning, that he paused in his career of unbounded power and pomp to smooth the way to children for the attainment of knowledge: who, after such an example, need be ashamed of devoting their talents to writing children's books!</p>
<p>This sketch of Wolsey has not shown the dark side of his character, which was deformed with many faults, and some crimes. Shakspeare has summed up the account of both good and ill, with such skill that volumes cannot impress upon the youthful mind a more accurate comprehension of Wolsey's character, than that given in the dialogue between Catherine of Arragon, Henry the Eighth's divorced queen, and Griffith, her chamberlain.</p>
<p>CATHERINE.</p>
<p>Didst thou not tell me, Griffith, as thou led'st me,
That the great child of honour, Cardinal Wolsey,
Was dead?
Prithee, good Griffith, tell me how he died.</p>
<p>GRIFFITH.</p>
<p>Well, the voice goes, madam;
For after the stout Earl Northumberland
Arrested him at York, and brought him forward
(As a man sore tainted), to his answer,
He fell sick suddenly, and grew so ill,
He could not sit his mule.
At last, with easy roads, he came to Leicester,
Lodg'd in the abbey; where the reverend abbot,
With all his convent, honourably received him;
To whom he gave these words," O, father abbot,
An old man, broken with the storms of state,
Is come to lay his weary hones among ye;
Give him a little earth for charity!"
So went to bed; where eagerly his sickness
Pursu'd him still; and, three nights after this,
About the hour of eight (which he himself
Foretold should be his last), full of repentance,
Continual meditations, tears, and sorrows,
He gave his honours to the world again,
His blessed part to heaven, and slept in peace.</p>
<p>CATHERINE.</p>
<p>So may he rest; his faults lie gently on him!
Yet, thus far, Griffith, give me leave to speak him
And yet with charity ;He was a man
Of an unbounded stomach, ever ranking
Himself with princes; one, that by suggestion
Tithed all the kingdom; simony was fair play;
His own opinions were his law: I'the presence
He would stay untruths; and be ever double,
Both in his words and meaning: He was never,
But where he meant to ruin, pitiful:
His promises were then as be was, mighty;
But his performance as he now is, nothing.
Of his own body he was ill, and gave
The clergy ill example.</p>
<p>GRIFFITH.</p>
<p>Noble madam, 
Men's evil manners live in brass; their virtues
We write in water. May it please your highness
To hear me speak his good now?</p>
<p>CATHERINE.</p>
<p>Yes. good Griffith
I were malicious else.</p>
<p>GRIFFITH.</p>
<p>This cardinal,
Though from an humble stock, undoubtedly
Was fashioned to much honour. Fom his cradle
He was a scholar, and a ripe and good one;
Exceeding wise, fair spoken, and persuading:
Lofty, and sour, to them who lov'd him not;
But, to those men that sought him, sweet as summer.
And though he were unsatisfied in getting
(Which were a sin), yet in bestowing, madam,
He was most princely: Ever witness for him
Those twins of learning, which he raised in you,
Ipswich and Oxford! one of which fell with him,
Unwilling to outlive the good he did it;
The other, though unfinished, yet so famous,
So excellent in art, and still so rising,
That Christendom shall ever speak his virtue.
His overthrow heap'd happiness upon him;
For then, and not till then, he felt himself,
And found the blessedness of being little:
And, to add greater honours to his age
Than man could give him, he died, fearing God.</p>
<p>CATHERINE.</p>
<p>After my death I wish no other herald,
No other speaker of my living actions,
To keep my honour from corruption,
But such an honest chronicler as Griffith.
Whom I most hated living, thou hast made me,
With thy religious truth and modesty,
Now in his ashes honour. Peace be with him.</p></historical_summary>
<tale><tale_title>THE JUDGMENT OF SIR THOMAS MORE.</tale_title>
<p>In the pleasant fields of Battersea, near the river side, on a spot which is now covered with houses, dwelt, three hundred and ten years ago, the blind widow, Annice Collie, and her orphan grandchild, Dorothy. These two were alone in the world, and yet they might scarcely be said to feel their loneliness; for they were all the world to each other.</p>
<p>Annice Collie had seen better days; for she was the daughter of a substantial yeoman, and her husband, Reuben Collie, had been a gardener in the service of good Queen Catherine, the first wife of King Henry the Eighth; and Annice had been a happy wife, a joyful mother, and a liberal housekeeper, having wherewithal to bestow on the wayfarer and stranger at their need. It was, however, the will of God that these blessings should be taken from her. The queen fell into adversity, and, being removed from her favourite palace at Greenwich, to give place to her newly exalted rival, Anne Boleyn, her faithful servants were all discharged; and, among them, Reuben Collie and his son, Arthur, were deprived of their situations in the royal gardens.</p>
<p>This misfortune, though heavy, appeared light, in comparison with the bitter reverses that had befallen their royal mistress: for the means of obtaining an honest livelihood were still in the power of the industrious little family; and beyond that their ambition extended not.</p>
<p>Reuben Collie, who had spent his youth in the Low Countries, had acquired a very considerable knowledge of the art of horticulture, an art at that time so little practised in England, that the salads and vegetables with which the tables of the great were supplied, were all brought, at a great expense, from Holland, and were, of course, never eaten in perfection. Reuben Collie, however, whose observations on the soil and climate had convinced him that these costly exotics might be raised in England, procured seeds, of various kinds, from a friend of his in the service of the Duke of Cleves, and was so fortunate as to rear a few plants of cabbages, savoys, brocoli, lettuces, artichokes, and cucumbers, to the unspeakable surprise of all the gardeners in London and its environs; and honest Reuben narrowly escaped being arraigned as a wizard, in consequence of their envy at the success of his experiment. He had hired, on a long lease, a cottage, with a small field adjoining, at a reasonable rent, of Master Bartholomew Barker, the rich tanner of Battersea; and this he and his son, Arthur, had, with great care and toil, converted into a garden and nursery ground, for rearing fruit trees, vegetables, costly flowers, and herbs of grace: and this spot, he flattered himself, would, one day, prove a mine of wealth to himself, and his son after him. That golden season never arrived; for Arthur, who had, during a leisure time, obtained work in a nobleman's garden at Chelsea, for the sake of bringing home a few additional groats, to assist in the maintenance of his wife, Margaret, and his little daughter, Dorothy, who lived with the old people, was unfortunately killed by the fall of an old wall, over which he was training a fig-tree.</p>
<p>The news of this terrible catastrophe was a deathblow to Reuben Collie. The afflicted mother and wife of Arthur struggled with their own grief to offer consolation to him; but it was in vain, for he never smiled again. He no longer took any interest in the garden, which had been before so great a source of pleasure to him: he suffered the weeds to grow up in his borders, and the brambles to take root in his bed. His flowers bloomed unheeded by him, and his fruit trees remained unpruned : even his darling exotics, the very pride of his heart, and the delight of his eyes, whose progress he had, heretofore, watched with an affection that almost savoured of idolatry, were neglected; and, resisting all the efforts which his wife and daughter-in-law could make to rouse him from this sinful state of despair, he fell into a languishing disorder, and died a few months after the calamity that had reddered him childless.</p>
<p>And now the two widows, Annice and Margaret Collie, had no one to work for them, or render them any comfort in their bereavement, save the little Dorothy; nevertheless, they did not abandon themselves to the fruitless indulgence of grief, as poor Reuben had done; but, the day after they had, with tearful eyes, assisted at his humble obsequies, they returned to their accustomed occupations, or, rather, they commenced a course of unwonted labour in the neglected garden, setting little Dorothy to weed the walks and borders, while they prepared the beds to receive crops, or transplanted the early seedlings from the frames. And Dorothy, though so young, was dutifully and industriously disposed, and a great comfort to them both: it was her especial business to gather the strawberries and currants, and to cull the flowers for posies, and carry them out to sell daily; nor was she afraid to venture, even to the great City of London, on such errands, though her only companion and guard was a beautiful Spainish dog, called Constant, which had been given to her, when quite a little puppy, by her royal mistress, good Queen Catherine, who was wont to bestow much notice on the child; and she, in her turn, fondly cherished the dog for the sake of her former benefactress. But Constant was, for his own sake, very deserving of her regard, not only for his extraordinary sagacity and beauty, but for the faithful and courageous attachment which he manifested for her person, no one daring to attack or molest her while he was at her side. Constant was, moreover, very useful in carrying her basket of posies for her, while she was loaded on either arm with those which contained the fruit; and so they performed their daily peregrinations, with kindly words on the one part, and looks and gestures of mutely eloquent affection on the other. Very fond and faithful friends were this guileless pair; and they were soon so well known, and excited so much interest, in the environs of London, that they were treated and caressed at almost every gentleman's house on the road: and the little girl found no difficulty in disposing of her fruit and flowers, and was as happy as a cheerful performance of her duties could render her. But these pleasant days did not last; the small-pox broke out in the neighbourhood :Dorothy's mother was attacked with this fatal malady, and, after a few days' severe illness, died; and the very night after the melancholy and hurried funeral of her beloved daughter-in-law took place, Annice Collie was laid upon the bed of sickness with the same cruel disease, and Dorothy was roused from the indulgence of the intense sorrow into which she was plunged by the unexpected death of her last surviving parent, to exert all her energies for the succour of her aged and helpless grandmother. <quote>"I know not how it was that I was enabled to watch, day and night, beside her bed, without sleep and almost without sustenance," would the weeping orphan say, whenever she referred to that sad period; "but of this I am assured, that the Lord, who feedeth the young ravens when they cry unto him, had compassion upon us both, or I never could have been supported, at my tender years, through trials like those. 'In the multitude of sorrows that I had in my heart, His comforts refreshed my soul;' and it was through His mercy that my dear grandmother recovered: but she never beheld the light of day again, the cruel disease had destroyed her sight." Yes, in addition to all her other afflictions, An nice Collie was now blind, a widow, childless, and destitute; yet was repining far from her; and, raising her sightless orbs to heaven, when she was informed by the sorrowful Dorothy of the extent of the calamity that had befallen her, in the loss of her daughter-in-law, she meekly said, with pious Eli, "It is the Lord, and shall I complain or fret myself because he hath, in his wisdom, resumed that, which, in his bounty, he gave? Blessed be his holy name for all which he hath given, and for all that he hath taken away; though these eyes shall behold his glorious works no more, yet shall my lips continue to praise him who can bring light out of darkness."</quote></p>
<p>But the illness of herself and her deceased daughter-in-law had consumed the little reserve that poor Annice had made for the payment of their rent; and their landlord, a hard and covetous man, who had, ever since the death of Reuben Collie, cast a greedy eye on the garden, which he and his son had made and planted with such labour and cost, called upon the poor widow on the quarter-day, and told her, with many harsh words, that, unless she resigned the lease of the garden to him, he would distrain her goods for the rent she owed him, and turn her and her grand-daughter into the street.</p>
<p><quote>"It is hard to resign the lease of the garden, which has not yet remunerated us for the sum my poor husband laid out upon it, just as it is becoming productive; but I am in your debt, Master Barker, so you must deal with me according to your conscience,"</quote> said the blind widow; on which he took the garden into his own hands, and made a merit of leaving the two forlorn one in possession of the cottage.</p>
<p>And now Dorothy betook herself to spinning, for the maintenance of herself and her helpless relative; but it was not much that she could earn, in that way, after having been accustomed to active employment in the open air: and then, her grandmother fell sick again of a rheumatic fever, and Dorothy was compelled to sell first one piece of furniture and then another to purchase necessaries for her, till at length nothing was left but the bed on which poor Annice lay; and, when Dorothy looked round the desolated apartment that had formerly been so neat and comfortable, she was almost tempted to rejoice that her grandmother could not behold its present dreary aspect.</p>
<p>Winter again approached with more than ordinary severity: quarter-day came, and found the luckless pair unprovided with money to pay the rent; and their cruel landlord turned the blind widow and her orphan grandchild into the street: and, but for the benevolence of a poor laundress, who, out of pity, admitted them into her wretched hovel by the way-side, they would have had no shelter from the inclemency of the night that followed. Annice, helpless as as infant, sunk down upon the straw, whereon her compassionate neighbour had assisted in placing her, and, having feebly expressed her thanks, turned her face to the wall; for she could not bear that her son's orphan should see the tears which she vainly strove to repress; but she could not hide them from the anxious scrutiny of the weeping girl. Dorothy did not speak, but looked very earnestly on the pale cheek and sunken features of her venerable grandmother, while she appeared to hold communion with her own heart on some subject of very painful interest. At length she rose up with the air of one who has effected a mighty conquest, and exclaimed, <quote>"Yes, dearest grandmother, it shall be done : the sacrifice shall be made!"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"What shall be done, my child?" inquired Annice, in surprise: "I have asked nothing of you."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Not indeed with your lips, dear parent of my departed father," said Dorothy; "but your pallid cheek and tearful eyes have demanded a sacrifice of me, which, however dearly it cost me, shall be madeI will sell Constant."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Sell Constant!" echoed her grandmother "can you part with the gift of your royal mis tress?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Not willingly, believe me," said Dorothy, throwing her arms about the neck of her mute favourite, and bursting into a flood of tears; "but how can I see you want bread? It is not long since that I was offered an angel of gold for him by a servant of the Duchess of Suffolk; and this I selfishly refused at that time, saying, I would rather starve than part with my dog. Alas, poor fellow! though I have shared my scanty pittance with him, since your illness he has suffered much for want of food: famine hath touched us all; and I have reason to reproach myself for having retained a creature I can no longer maintain."</quote></p>
<p>The next morning she rose at an early hour, and, accompanied by her faithful Constant, took the road to Westminster, to inquire if the Duchess of Suffolk were still disposed to purchase him at the price she had named; but she returned, bathed in tears, and in great distress, having encountered two ruffians, in a lonely part of the road at Knightsbridge, one of whom claimed Constant as his property, violently seized upon him, and, in spite of her tears and remonstrances, carried him off, threatening her with very harsh usage if she attempted to follow.</p>
<p>Poor Dorothy! this appeared the severest trial that had yet befallen her: at any rate it was one of those drops of bitterness which make a brimful cup of misery overflow; and, regardless of the soothings or expostulations of her grandmother, she wept and sobbed all that night, refusing to be comforted. She rose the following morning with the melancholy conviction that no resource now remained but the wretched one of supplicating the alms of the charitably disposed in the streets and highways. Nothing but the imperative urgency of the case could have reconciled the meek and timid Dorothy to a - mode of life so every way repugnant to her feelings. <quote>"We wept when we saw my dear mother laid in the cold and silent grave; but now I rejoice that she was spared the grief of seeing this day," said the sorrowful orphan, when she commenced her unwonted vocation, and experienced the bitter taunts of the pampered menials of the great, the rude repulses of the unfeeling, or the grave rebukes of the stern, but well-meaning, moralists who, though they awarded their charity, accompanied their alms with reflections on the disreputable and lazy trade she had adopted. Some there were, indeed, who, touched with the sweetness and modesty of her manners and appearance, spake to the forlorn one kindly, relieved her present wants, and bade her .call again; but the number of these was comparatively small: and the bread which she earned so hardly for herself and her aged relative was, literally speaking, steeped in her tears. While pursuing her miserable occupation, she sadly [missed the company and caresses of the faithful Constant. "He would have been kind and affectionate," she said, "if all the world had frowned upon her. Her change of circumstances made no alteration in his regard; if she were in sickness or sorrow, and others chid or scorned her, he appeared to redouble his endearments ; and, while he was by her side, she did not feel so very lonelyso sweet it is to be assured of the love of one friend, however humble."</quote> Sometimes, too, she thought she should feel less sorrowful if she were assured that he had fallen into good hands.</p>
<p>Meantime days and weeks passed away, her clothes grew old and her shoes were worn out, and Dorothy, who was accustomed to appear so neat and nice in her attire, was reduced to the garb of the most abject misery; but, though barefoot and sorely pinched with cold and famine, she thought less of her own sufferings than of the privations to which her blind grandmother was exposed.</p>
<p>One evening, when the snow lay deep upon the ground, and Dorothy had been begging all day without receiving a single penny in alms, neither had she tasted a morsel of food since a very early hour in the morning, her strength failed her; and, overcome by cold, hunger, weariness, and sorrow, she sat down on a heap of frozen snow by the way-side, and wept bitterly. The river Thames was then frozen over; she had walked across it on the ice, and was now in the parish of Chelsea. She regretted that she had ventured so far from her home, for she was oppressed with fatigue; and, though she saw the trees and houses on the opposite shores of Battersea so near, she felt as if she could not reach them that night. A drowsy feeling, the fatal effects of cold and hunger combined, was stealing over her: she tried to rouse herself, <quote>"for," she faintly whispered to herself, "my poor grandmother will be so uneasy, if I do not return: but then," she thought, "how pleasantly I could go to sleep here, and forget all my troubles! I am not cold now, only so very, very drowsy;"</quote> and, though aware that, if she did yield to these lethargic feelings, her sleep would be the sleep of death, she* required some stimulus, more powerful than even that conviction, to dispel the soporific influence of the deadly cold which had seized her tender frame, like a withering blight, and benumbed her faculties. But at the very moment when the shores of Battersea, with their snow-clad trees and houses, were fading before her closing eyes, and she was sinking passively and almost pleasingly, into that slumber from which she would never have awaked, she was roused by a dog bounding suddenly upon her with a joyful cry, and licking her benumbed face and hands with the most passionate demonstrations of affection.</p>
<p><quote>"Ah, my dear, dear Constant! is it you?" she exclaimed in an impulsive burst of delight at this unexpected rencontre. The icy bonds of the death-sleep that had enchained her were broken: she returned the eager caresses of the faithful animal with the rapture of one who is suddenly restored to a long-lost friend: and, starting from the ground with renewed strength and spirits, she exclaimed, "I shall be able to reach home now I have found you, my pretty Constant, my own dear dog!"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Your dog, hussey ?" interposed a serving-man, rudely separating the reunited friends, "I'd have you know that this dog belongs to my Lady More, whose footman I have the honour to be."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Indeed, indeed, it is my dog that was stolen from me, on the Knightsbridge-road, by a hardhearted man," sobbed Dorothy; she was going to add, "just such a one as yourself,"</quote> but she stopped short.</p>
<p><quote>"And pray, my sweet mistress, may I ask how a beggar-wench, like yourself, came in possession of a dog of such a rare and costly breed ?"</quote> demanded the man with a sneer.</p>
<p><quote>"He was given to me, when quite a puppy, by my sovereign lady, good Queen Catherine, who was ever gracious unto me,"</quote> said she.</p>
<p><quote>"Ho! ho! ho! was she so ?" responded the man, bursting into an insulting laugh: "a likely tale, forsooth! you look like a Queen's minion, my mistress, do you not? Well, well, it is not a small lie that will choke you! Good night, my fair courtier, 'tis too cold to stand parleying with you on the matter."</quote> So saying, he laid violent hands on Constant; and, in spite of his resistance and Dorothy's tears and passionate remonstrances, he tucked him under his arm, and trudged off.</p>
<p>Cold, hunger, weariness, and dejection, were alike forgotten by the bereaved mistress of Constant at the prospect of a second separation from this faithful friend, whose affecting remembrance of her, after so long an absence, had endeared him to her more than ever; and, without a moment's hesitation, she followed the servant as quickly as her naked and lacerated feet could carry her over the frozen snow, till he arrived at the gates of Sir Thomas More's mansion, which she essayed to enter with him.</p>
<p><quote>"Why, you saucy young jade!" exclaimed he, thrusting her back: "this is a pass of impudence beyond any thing I ever heard of! Don't you know that I am my Lady More's own footman, and Sir Thomas More, my Lady's husband, is Lord High Chancellor of England."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I pray you then to bring me to the speech of her ladyship," said Dorothy, "for the higher she be, the more will it behove her to do me justice."</quote></p>
<p>On this the serving-man, who was aware that his lady was a proud worldly woman, and by no means likely to resign her favourite dog to a beggar-girl, laughed immoderately. Some of his fellow servants who were standing by, joined in his mirth, while other were so cruel as to address many jeering remarks to Dorothy on her address and appearance, all which she heard patiently, and meekly replied, <quote>"the fashion of her clothes was not of her choice, but her necessity, to which she prayed that none of those who reviled her might ever be exposed:"</quote> and when none would undertake to bring her to the speech of Lady More, she seated herself on a stone at the gates of the court yard, to wait for the appearance of some of the family, though she was exposed to the inclemency of the snow-storms, which beat on the uncovered head of the friendless orphan.</p>
<p>At length she heard the sound of wheels, and the servants came hastily to throw open the gates, crying, <quote>"Room, room, for my Lord Chancellor's coach;" and all the daughters of Sir Thomas More, with their husbands and children, came forth to welcome him, as was their custom; for that great and good man was very tenderly beloved by his family, to every member of which he was most fondly attached: yet, when he saw the half-naked child sitting so sorrowfully at his gate, he looked reproachfully upon them all, and said, "How now, have ye all learned the parable of Lazarus and Dives to little purpose, that ye suffer this forlorn one to remain without the gates in such an evening that no Christian would turn a dog from the fire?" "Noble Sir," said Dorothy, making a lowly reverence to Sir Thomas, "none of this good family wist of my distress, nor have I applied to them for an alms: the cause of my making bold to come hither was upon another matter, on which I beseech your worshipful Lordship to do me justice."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Well, my little maiden, it is cold deciding on causes here," said Sir Thomas: "so thou shalt step into my kitchen with the servants; and, after thou art fed and warmed, I will hear thee on thy matter."</quote></p>
<p>Now, though the words <quote>"fed and warmed," sounded pleasantly enough in the ears of the cold, half-famished child, yet her attachment to her dog prevailed over every other consideration, and she said "Alack! noble sir, though I stand greatly in need of your hospitable charity, yet would it be more satisfaction to me if you would be pleased to hear me forthwith on the matter of my dog, which is detained from me by one of my Lady More's serving-men, under the false pretence that it belongeth to her ladyship."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Go to, thou saucy vagrant! hast thou the boldness to claim my favourite dog before my face?"</quote> exclaimed a very sour-spoken and hard-favoured old gentlewoman, whom Dorothy had not before observed.</p>
<p><quote>"Craving your honourable ladyship's pardon, nay,"replied Dorothy, curtseying, "I do not claim your ladyship's dog, for that would be a sin; but I demand my own to be restored to me, in which I wrong no one, seeing he is mine own lawful property, which a false caitiff took violently from me three months agone."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"That agreeth well with the time when your dog Sultan was presented to you, Mistress Alice,"</quote> observed Sir Thomas, significantly.</p>
<p><quote>"Tilley-valley! tilley-valley!" ejaculated Lady More in a pet; "that is ever the way in which you cross me, Sir Thomas, making out withal as though I were a receiver of stolen goods."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Nay, patience, my lady; I went not so far as to decide the cause before I had heard both sides of the question, which it is my purpose to do without farther delay," returned Sir Thomas, smiling: "so follow me into court, both plaintiff and defendant, and I will give judgment between the parties before I sup;" and, with a merry air, he led the way into the servants' hall, where, placing himself in the housekeeper's chair, and putting on his cap, he said, "Beggar versus my Lady, open the pleadings, and speak boldly."</quote></p>
<p>But poor Dorothy, instead of speaking, hung down her head, and burst into tears.</p>
<p><quote>"How! speechless!" said Sir Thomas: "then must the court appoint counsel for the plaintiff. Daughter Margaret, do you closet the plaintiff, hear her case, and plead for her."</quote></p>
<p>Then Mistress Margaret Roper, Sir Thomas's eldest daughter, with a benevolent smile, took the abashed, trembling girl aside; and, having, with soothing words, drawn the particulars of her melancholy story from her, she advanced to the front of Sir Thomas's chair, leading the weeping orphan by the hand, and attempted to humour the scene by opening her client's case in a witty imitation of legal terms, after the manner of a grave law-sergeant; but, as she proceeded to detail the circumstances under which the dog was lost recognised, and again taken from the friendless orphan, she, by imperceptible degrees, changed her style to the simply pathetic terms in which the child had related the tale to herthe language the unadorned language of truth and feeling, which never fails to come home to every bosom. All present, save my Lady More, who preserved a very aigre and impenetrable demeanour, were dissolved in tears: as for the poor plaintiff, she covered her face with a part of her tattered garments, and sobbed aloud; and the counsel herself was compelled to pause for a moment to overcome her own emotion, ere she could conclude her eloquent appeal on her client's behalf.</p>
<p><quote>"Thou hast pleaded well, my good Meg," said Sir Thomas, smiling through his tears on his best beloved daughter; "but now must we hear the defendant's reply, for the plaintiff ever appeareth in the right till after the defendant hath spoken: so now, my Lady, what hast thou to say to this matter?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"My Lady hath to repeat what she hath too often said before, that Sir Thomas More's jests are ever out of place,"</quote> replied my Lady in a huff.</p>
<p><quote>"Nay, marry, good Mistress Alice, an thou have naught better to the purpose to respond, I must fain to give judgment for the plaintiff in this case."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Tilley-valley, Sir Thomas! thou art enough to provoke a saint with thy eternal quips and gibes," replied her ladyship: "I tell you the dog is my property, and was presented to me by an honourable gentleman one Master Rich, whom you, Sir Thomas, know well; and he said he bought him of a dealer in such gear."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Which dealer probably stole him from my client,"</quote> said Mistress Margaret Roper.</p>
<p><quote>"Nay, but, daughter Margaret, how knowest thou that Sultan was ever this wench's property?"</quote> retorted Lady More, sharply.</p>
<p><quote>"Well answered, defendant," said Sir Thomas: "we must call a witness whose evidence must decide the matter. Son Roper, bring the dog Sultan, alias Constant, into court."</quote></p>
<p>The eyes of Dorothy brightened at the sight of her old companion; and Sir Thomas More, taking him into his hands, said, <quote>"Here am I placed in as great a strait as ever was King Solomon, in respect to the memorable case in which he was called upon to decide whose was the living child, which both mothers claimed, and to whom pertained the dead child, which neither would acknowledge. This maiden saith, the dog which I hold is hers, and was violently taken from her three months agone: my lady replies, "Nay, but he is mine, and was presented to me by an honourable man," (one of the King's Counsellors forsooth). Now, in this matter, the dog is wiser than my Lord Chancellor, for he knoweth unto whom he of right pertaineth; and, therefore, upon his witness must the decision of this controversy depend. So now, my Lady, you stand at the upper end of the hall, as befits your quality, and you, my little maiden, go to the lower; and each of you call the dog by the name which you have been wont to do : and to whichsover of you twain he goeth, that person I adjudge to be his rightful owner."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Oh, my Lord, I ask no other test!"</quote> exclaimed Dorothy joyfully.</p>
<p><quote>"Sultan! Sultan! come to thy mistress, my pretty Sultan!" said my Lady, in her most blandishing tone, accompanying her words with such actions of enticement as she judged most likely to win him over to her: but he paid not the slightest heed to the summons. Dorothy simply pronounced the word "Constant!"</quote> and the dog, bounding from between the hands of Sir Thomas More, who had lightly held him till both claimants had spoken, leaped upon her, and overwhelmed her with his passionate caresses.</p>
<p><quote>"It is a clear case," said Sir Thomas: "the dog hath acknowledged his mistress, and his witness is incontrovertible. Constant, thou art worthy of thy name."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Hark ye, wench!" said my Lady More, whose desire of retaining the object of dispute had in creased with the prospect of losing him, "I will give thee a good price for thy dog, if thou art disposed to sell him."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Sell my dear, beautiful, faithful Constant! Oh, never, never!"</quote> exclaimed Dorothy, throwing her arms about her newly recovered favourite, and kissing him with the fondest affection.</p>
<p><quote>"I will give thee a golden angel, and a new suit of clothes to boot, for him, which, I should think, a beggar-girl were mad to refuse,"</quote> pursued Lady More.</p>
<p><quote>"Nay, nay, my Lady, never tempt me with your gold," said Dorothy; "or my duty to my poor blind grandmother will compel me to close with your offer, though it should break my heart withal."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Nay, child, an' thou hast a blind old grandmother, whom thou lovest so well, I will add a warm blanket, and a linsey-woolsey gown for her wear, unto the price I have already named," said the persevering Lady More:"speak, shall I have him?"</quote> pursued she, pressing the bargain home.</p>
<p>Dorothy averted her head, to conceal the large tears that rolled down her pale cheeks, as she sobbed out, <quote>"Yees, my Lady."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Dear child," said Sir Thomas, "thou hast made a noble sacrifice to thy duty: 'tis pity mat thou hast taken up so bad a trade as begging, for thou art worthy of better things."</quote></p>
<p>'* It is for my poor blind grandmother,<quote>" said the weeping Dorothy : "I have no other means of getting bread for her."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I will find thee a better employment," said Sir Thomas, kindly: "thou shalt be my daughter Hoper's waiting-maid, if thou canst resolve to quit the wandering life of a beggar, and settle to an honest service."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"How joyfully would I embrace your offer, noble Sir, if I could do so without being separated from my aged grandmother, who has no one in the world but me,"</quote> replied Dorothy, looking up between smiles and tears.</p>
<p><quote>"Nay, God forbid that I should put asunder those whom nature hath so fondly united in the holy bands of love and duty," said Sir Thomas More, wiping away a tear: "my house is large enough to hold ye both; and while I have a roof to call mine own, it shall contain a corner for the blind and aged widow and the destitute orphan: that so, when the fashion of this world passeth away, they may witness for me before Him, with whom there is no respect of persons, and who judgeth every man according to his works."</quote></p></tale>
<historical_summary>Sir Thomas More was the only son of Sir John More, a judge of the king's bench, and was born in Milk Street, London, 1480. At a very early period of his life he gave such indications of the talents for which he was conspicuous, that Cardinal Morton*, Archbishop of Canterbury, in whose household he was placed, prophetically remarked, <quote>"This child, here waiting at table, whosoever shall live to see it, will prove a marvellous man!"</quote> The young reader must note from this anecdote the peculiar manners of those days. Sir Thomas More was then a judge's son, and yet he was servitor at the cardinal's table. In ancient times, the tyro, either in arms or learning, let his birth or rank in life be what it might, during his noviciate, ever waited on his elders, and supposed betters in learning or wisdom; and even at the present day in schools and establishments of monastic institution, as Eton, Winchester, or Westminster, some faint traces may still be discovered of this antique system, which has now degenerated into the capricious and irregular system of fagging. 
<p>* This excellent prelate has already been introduced to the juvenile reader, in a preceding tale, under the name of Dr. Morton, Bishop of Ely.</p>
<p>Sir Thomas More greatly distinguished himself at Oxford, after which he entered the inns of court, which were then, whatever they may be now, the finishing schools of moral worth and high attainment for the young nobles and gentry of England, whether their intention was to devote themselves to a legal profession, or to arms, or the senate. Young More's destination was to the former, for we find him called to the bar, when a student at Lincoln's Inn, and he followed his profession with the greatest success. In 1502, he became a member of parliament, and distinguished himself in such a manner, in opposing a grant for the marriage of Henry the Seventh's daughter to the King of Scotland, James the Fourth, that the king was told, a beardless boy had prevented its being passed ; in revenge for which, Henry the Seventh had the meanness to send young More's father, the judge, to the Tower, for some pretended offence, from whence he was not set at liberty till he was heavily fined. When Henry the Eighth ascended the throne, the fame of young More's abilities and eloquence having reached his ears, his majesty persuaded him to enter his service, and immediately gave him the situation of master of requests, soon after knighted him, and made him a member of his privy council. His wit and universal talents so effectually gained the favour of his sovereign, that he treated him with extraordinary condescension and familiarity, of which many stories are told. In 1518, Sir Thomas became treasurer of the exchequer, and five years afterwards was chosen speaker of the house of commons ; having filled several other high offices with invariable credit and success, Henry selected him, in 1529, to be the successor of Cardinal Wolsey, as Lord Chancellor, being the first layman that had ever filled that exalted office.</p>
<p>After executing that high charge with singular zeal and impartiality, he resigned it in May, 1532, because he would not countenance the destruction of a church to which he was a most faithful and devoted servant. His retirement was not attended with the security, either to his person or his conscience, which might have Wen anticipated; for, having been uniformly opposed to Henrys divorce from Catherine of Arragon, he rendered himself obnoxious both to his master and the new queen and by refusing to attend Anne Boleyn's coronation, his doom was sealed. A crisis was at hand from which no honest man of the Catholic religion could escape. In 1534, the Act of Supremacy appeared, and Sir Thomas More, sincerely attached to the faith of his ancestors, refused to swerve from it. He was imprisoned, arraigned of high treason, and on the most scandalous testimony, pronounced guilty. The usual penalty of being hanged, drawn, and quartered, was commuted into simple decapitation, a boon which Sir Thomas More acknowledged by one of those lively sallies for which he was as celebrated as for his graver talents:</p>
<p><quote>"God forbid," said he, "the king should use any more such mercy to any of my friends, and God bless my posterity from such pardons."</quote></p>
<p>He was beheaded at Tower Hill, on Tuesday, the 6th of July, 1535, being then in his fifty-fifth year, and suffered, not only with fortitude, but with cheerfulness.</p>
<p>Sir Thomas More, amidst all the cares of state, spared time to devote to the superintendence of the education of his children, and he was amply rewarded, since his three daughters were the pride of their sex and their country for their high attainments and many virtues; even his step-daughter, likewise much beloved by him, manifested great excellence of character, and shewed a tender regard for him in his misfortunes. His great-grandson, Cresacre More, wrote the life of his noble progenitor, which is one of the most beautiful biographies ever penned. <quote>"It happened," says Cresacre More, "on a time, that a beggar woman's dog, which she had lost, was presented for a jewel to my Lady More, and she kept it some seven-night very carefully; but at last the beggar had notice where her dog was, and presently she came to complain to Sir Thomas, that his lady withheld her dog from her; presently my lady was sent for, and the dog brought with her: which Sir Thomas taking in his hands, caused his wife, because she was the worthier person, to stand at the upper end of the hall, and the beggar at the lower end, and saying that he sat there to do justice, he bade each of them to call the dog, which when they did, the dog went presently to the beggar, forsaking the lady. When he saw this, he bade my lady be contented, for the dog was none of hers ; yet she, repining at the sentence of my lord chancellor, agreed with the beggar, and gave her a piece of gold which would well have bought three dogs, and so all parties were agreed, every one smiling to see his manner of inquiring out the truth."</quote></p>
<p>Let all disunited families study with care this beautiful sketch of a household of love, as given by an eye witness, Sir Thomas's friend, thegreat Erasmus; <quote>"More hath built near London, upon the Thames' side, to wit, at Chelsea, a commodious house, neither mean nor subject to envy, and yet magnificent enough; there he converseth affably with his family, his wife, his son, and daughter-in-law, his three daughters and their husbands, with eleven grandchildren. There is not any man so loving to his children as he, and he loveth his old wife, as well as if she were a young maid; and such is the excellency of his temper, that whatsover happeneth that could not be helped, he loveth it as though nothing could have happened more happily. You would say, there were in that place Plato's academy; but I do the house injury in comparing it to Plato's academy, wherein there was only disputations of members, or geometrical figures, and sometimes of moral virtues. I should rather call his house a school of the Christian religion; their special care is piety and virtue ; there is no quarelling, or intemperate words heard ; none seen idle; which household discipline that worthy gentleman doth not govern by proud and lofty words, but with all kind and courteous benevolence. Every body performeth, yet is there always alacrity, neither is sober mirth anything wanting. He suffereth none of his servants either to be idle or to give themselves to games, but some of them he allotted to look to the garden, assigning to every one his separate plot; some again he set to sing, some to play on the organs; he suffereth none of them touch cards or dice. He used, before bed time, to call them together, and say certain prayers with them."</quote> This life of domestic felicity was suddenly destroyed by the decree of a tyrant; and the mandate which consigned the most accomplished individual in the English dominion to the scaffold, carried desolation to all who depended on him, gave his lands to a stranger, and his</p>
<p><quote>"Once fair spreading family dissolved."</quote></p>
<p>Amidst this most estimable and distinguished family, none shone with greater lustre than Margaret, the eldest daughter and most beloved pupil of Sir Thomas More. She resembled him in person more nearly than the rest of his children, and in the depth and acuteness of her understanding. She was the dispenser of her father's secret charities, and to her alone he entrusted the knowledge of the severe religious austerities to which he subjected himself. A most affecting scene took place between the father and daughter on his return from the Tower after his condemnation, which it would be a want of judgment to describe in any other words than those of her husband's, Mr. Roper, a most accomplished gentleman, worthy of being the son-in-law of Sir Thomas More:</p>
<p><quote>"When Sir Thomas came from Westminster to the Tower ward again, his daughter, my wife, desirous to see her father, whom she thought she should never see in this world after, and also to have his final blessing, gave attendance about the Tower wharf, where she knew he would pass by before he could enter the Tower. There tarrying his coming, as soon as she saw him, after his blessing upon her knees reverently received, she hasting towards him, without consideration or care of herself, pressing in amongst the midst of the throng and company of the guard, that with halberds and bills went round about him, hastily ran to him, who, well liking her most natural and dear daughterly affection towards him, gave her his fatherly blessing, and many goodly words of comfort besides. From whom when she turned to depart she, not satisfied with the former sight of her dear father, and like one that had forgotten herself, being all transported with the entire love of her dear father, having neither heed to himself nor the press of people and multitude that were there about him, suddenly turned back again, ran to him as before, took him about the neck, and divers times kissed him most lovingly, and at last, with a full and heavy heart, was fain to depart from him; the beholding whereof was to many of them that were present thereat so lamentable, that it made them, for very sorrow thereof, to weep and mourn."</quote></p>
<p>The morning before he suffered, Sir Thomas wrote to his dear daughter the following letter, with a piece of charcoal, in the blank leaf of one of his works. Besides its intrinsic excellence, the allusions it contains to the persons composing his once happy family circle, make it deeply interesting:</p>
<p><quote>"Our Lord bless you, good dauhgter, and your good husband, and your little boy, and all yours, and all my children, and all my good children, and all oar friends. Recommend me, when ye may, to my good daughter Cecily *1, whom I beseech the Lord to comfort; and I send her my blessing, and to all her children, and pray her to pray for me. I send her a handkerchief, and God comfort my good son, her husband. My good daughter Dauncey *2 hath the picture in parchment, that you delivered me from my lady Coniers; her name is on the back. Shew her that I heartily pray her, that you may send it in my name to her again, for a token from me, to pray for me. I like special well Dorothy Collie *3: I pray you be good to her. I would wot whether this be she that you wrote me of; if not, yet I pray you be good to the other as you may, in her affliction, and to my daughter Joan Alleyn too *4. Give her, I pray you, some kind answer, for she sued hither to me this day to pray you to be good to her. I cumber you, good Margaret, much; but I should be sorry if it should be any longer than to-morrow, for it is St. Thomas's eve, and the utas of St. Peter, and therefore tomorrow long I to go to God. It were a day meet and convenient for me. I never liked your manners towards me better than when you kissed me last, for I love when daughterly love and dear charily hath no leisure to stay for worldly courtesy *5. Farewell, my dear child, and pray for me, and I shall for you and all your friends, that we may merrily meet in Heaven. I thank you for your great cost. I send now to my good daughter Clement *6, her algorisme stone, and I send her and my godson, and all her children, God's blessing and mine. I pray you, at time convenient, commend me to my good son John More. I liked well his natural fashion *7. Our Lord bless him and his wife, my loving daughter, to whom I pray him to be good, as he hath great cause; and if that the land of mine come into his hand, he brake not my will concerning his sister Dauncey; and our Lord bless Thomas and Austin (his sons), and all that they have."</quote></p>
<p>*1 Mrs. Heron, his third daughter.</p>
<p>*2 A beloved servant in the family, who married another faithful retainer of Sir Thomas's, his secretary, John Harris. It is a redeeming trait in human nature that so many persons should have been affectionate and true in the trying hour of adversity.</p>
<p>*3 His second daughter, Elizabeth.</p>
<p>*4 A servant of Mrs. Roper's, his god-daughter</p>
<p>*5 In this beautiful sentence he alludes to their last interview on Tower Wharf.</p>
<p>*6 The wife of Dr Clement, his ward and relative, and be loved as a daughter.</p>
<p>*7 He likewise met his father on Tower Wharf.</p>
<p>It was one of the last requests of Sir Thomas More to Henry the Eighth, that his daughter Margaret might attend his funeral. In defiance of the danger which attended the act, she bought the head of her honoured parent, when it was about to be thrown into the Thames; and when brought before the privy council, and harshly questioned concerning this act, and why she did it, she replied boldly, <quote>"That it might not become food for fishes."</quote> She died at the early age of thirty-six; and by her own desire she was buried with her father's head on her bosom.</p>
<p>A fine family picture of all these interesting personages, by Holbein, is still in existence, likewise engravings from it. In this picture is introduced the portrait of the beggar-girl's dog, on which the accompanying tale is founded.</p>
<p>Alice Lady More, although not a pleasant mannered or sweet tempered woman, must have possessed some good qualities, as she was an excellent stepmother to Sir Thomas's motherless children, as we learn from some verses of his, translated from the Latin, in which he wrote them, by Archdeacon Wrangham. They were meant for an epitaph on his first and second wives.</p>
<p>Within this tomb Jane, wife of More, reclines;
This, More for Alice and himself designs.
The first, dear object of my youthful vow.
Gave me three daughters and a son to know:
The next,ah, virtue in a step-dame rare,
Nursed my sweet infants with a mother's care.
With both my years so happily have pass'd,
Which most my love I know notfirst or last.</p>
<p>The worthies of Sir Thomas More's family are not yet enumerated. Mrs. Roper's daughter, Mrs. Bazett, was one of the most accomplished and pious ladies of her time, and translated from the Latin her grandfather's <quote>"Exposition of our Saviour's Passion,"</quote> in a style so like his own, that for some time many believed it to be his composition. England still possesses descendants from this most illustrious branch of a noble family.</p></historical_summary>
<tale><tale_title>LADY LUCY'S PETITION TO THE QUEEN.</tale_title>
<p><quote>"And is my dear papa shut up in this dismal place to which you are taking me, nurse?"</quote> asked the little Lady Lucy Preston, raising her eyes fearfully to the Tower of London, as the coach in which she was seated with Amy Gradwell, her nurse, drove under the gateway.</p>
<p>She trembled and hid her face in Amy's cloak, when they alighted and she saw the soldiers on guard, with their crossed partizans, before the portals of that part of the fortress where the prisoners of state were confined, and where her own father, Lord Preston, of whom she was come to take a last farewell, then lay, under sentence of death.</p>
<p><quote>"Yes, my dear child," returned Amy, mournfully, "my lord, your father, is indeed within these sad walls. You are now going to visit him. Shall you be afraid of entering the place, my dear?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"No," replied Lady Lucy, resolutely, "I am not afraid of going to anyplace where my dear papa is." Yet she clung closer to the arm of her attendant, as they were admitted within the gloomy precincts of the building; her little heart fluttered fearfully as she glanced round her, and she whispered to the nurse, "Was it not here that the young princes, Edward the Fifth and his brother Richard Duke of York, were murdered by their cruel uncle Richard Duke of Gloucester P"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Yes, my love, it was; but do not be alarmed on that account, for no one will harm you,"</quote> said old Amy, in an encouraging tone.</p>
<p><quote>"And was not good King Henry the Sixth murdered here also, by that same wicked Richard?"</quote> continued the little girl, whose imagination was full of the records of the deeds of blood that had been perpetrated in this fatally celebrated place, many of which had been related to her by Bridget Oldworth, the housekeeper, since her father had been imprisoned in the Tower on a charge of high treason.</p>
<p>"But do you think they will murder papa, nurse?'* pursued the child, as they began to ascend the stairs leading to the apartment in which the unfortunate nobleman was confined.</p>
<p><quote>"Hush! hush! dear child; you must not talk of these things here," said Amy, "or they will shut us both up in a room with bars and bolts, instead of admitting us to see my lord your father."</quote> Lady Lucy pressed closer to her nurse's side, and was silent till they were ushered into the room where h°r father was confined, when, forgetting every thing else in her joy at seeing him again, she sprang into his arms, and almost stifled him with her kisses.</p>
<p>Lord Preston was greatly affected at the sight of his little daughter, and overcome by her passionate demonstrations of fondness and his own anguish at the thought of his approaching separation from her, and the idea of leaving her an orphan at her tender age (for she had only just completed her ninth year and had lost her mother), he clasped her to his bosom, and bedewed her innocent face with his tears.</p>
<p><quote>"Why do you cry, dear papa?" asked the little girl, who was herself weeping at the sight of his distress. "And why will you not leave this gloomy place, and come home to your own hall again?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Attend to me, Lucy, and I will tell you the cause of my grief," said her father, seating the little girl on his knee. "I shall never come home again, for I have been condemned to die for high treason (which means, an offence against the king), and I shall not leave this place till they bring me forth on Tower Hill, where they will cut off my head with a sharp axe, and set it up afterwards over Temple Bar or London Bridge."</quote></p>
<p>At this terrible intelligence, Lady Lucy screamed aloud, and hid her face in her father's bosom, which she wetted with her tears.</p>
<p><quote>"Be composed, my dear child," said Lord Preston, "for I have much to say to you, and we may never meet again on this side the grave, since I am so soon to die."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"No, no, dear papa," cried Lady Lucy, "they shall not kill you, for I will cling so fast about your neck, that they shall not be able to cut off your head; and I will tell them all how good and kind you are, and then they will not want to kill you."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"My dearest love, this is all simple talking," said Lord Preston; "I have offended against the law as it is at present established, by trying to have King James, my old master, restored to the throne, and, therefore, I must die. Do you not remember Lucy, I took you once to Whitehall, to see King James, and how kindly he spoke to you?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Oh, yes, papa! and I recollect he laid his hand upon my head, and said, I was like what his daughter, the Princess of Orange, was at my age,"</quote> replied Lady Lucy, with great animation.</p>
<p><quote>"Well, my child, very shortly after you saw King James at Whitehall, the Prince of Orange came over to England, and drove King James out of his palace and kingdom, and the people, who were displeased with King James on account of his professing the Roman Catholic religion, which they suspected he designed to re-establish in this country, deposed him, and made the Prince and Princess of Orange king and queen in his stead."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"But was it not very wicked of the Princess of Orange to join with her husband to take her father's kingdom away from him? I am very sorry King James thought me like her,"</quote> said Lady Lucy, earnestly.</p>
<p><quote>"Hush, hush, my love; you must not talk so of the Princess of Orange; for, perhaps, she considered she was doing right in depriving her father of his dominions, because it is against the law for a king of England to be a Catholic. Yet, I confess, I did not believe she would have consented to sign the death-warrants of so many of her father's old servants, on account of their faithful attachment to him,"</quote> said Lord Preston with a sigh.</p>
<p><quote>"I have heard that the Princess of Orange is of a merciful disposition," said old Amy Gradwell, who had been a weeping spectator of the scene between the father and child ; "and perhaps she might be induced to spare your life, my lord, if your pardon were very earnestly entreated of her by some of your friends."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Alas! my good Amy, I have no one who will undertake the perilous office of soliciting the royal grace for an attainted traitor, lest they should be suspected of forwarding the cause of King James,"</quote> said Lord Preston mournfully.</p>
<p><quote>"Dear papa! let me go to the queen, and entreat for your pardon,"cried Lady Lucy, with a crimsoned cheek and sparkling eye. "I will so beg and pray her to spare your life that she will not have the heart to deny me."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Simple child!" exclaimed her father; "what should you be able to say to the queen that would be of any avail?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"God would teach me what to say," returned Lady Lucy piously; "and he has also power to touch her heart with pity for a child's distress, and to open her ear to my earnest petition."</quote></p>
<p>Her father clasped her to his bosom, but said, <quote>"Thou wouldst be afraid of speaking to the queen, even if thou shouldst be admitted to her presence, my Lucy."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Why should I be afraid of speaking to the queen, papa? for even if she should be angry with me, and answer harshly at first, I should be thinking too much of your peril to mind it. Or if she were to send me to the Tower, and cutoff my head, she could only kill my body, you know; but would have no power at all to hurt my soul, which is under the protection of One who is greater than any king or queen upon earth."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"You are right, my child, to fear God, and to have no other fear," said her father. "It is He who hath perhaps put it into your young heart to plead with the queen for my life, which if it be His pleasure that she should grant, I shall feel it indeed a happiness for my child to be made the instrument of my deliverance from the perils of death which now encompass me ; but if it should be otherwise, His will be done. He hath promised to be a father to the fatherless, and he will not forsake my good and dutiful child when I am low in the dust."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"But how will my Lady Lucy gain admittance to the queen's presence, my Lord?"</quote> asked old Amy.</p>
<p><quote>"I will write a letter to her godmother, the Lady Clarendon, requesting her to accomplish the matter,"</quote> said Lord Preston. He then wrote a few hasty lines to that lady, which together with his own petition for the royal mercy, he gave to his little daughter, telling her she was to go the next day to Hampton Court, properly attended, and to obtain a sight of Lady Clarendon, who was there in waiting upon the queen, and to deliver that letter to her with her own hand. He then kissed his child, tenderly blessed her, and bade her farewell.</p>
<p>Though the little girl wept much at parting with her father, she left the Tower with a far more composed mind than that with which she entered it, for see had formed her resolution, and her young heart was full of hope. She had silently committed her cause to God, and she trusted that He would dispose the event prosperously for her.</p>
<p>The next morning, before the lark had sung her matins, Lady Lucy was up and dressed in a suit of deep mourning, which Amy had provided, considering it the most suitable garb for a child whose only surviving parent was under sentence of death.</p>
<p>The servants, who had been informed of their young lady's intention to solicit the queen for her father's pardon, were all assembled in the entrance hall to see her depart, and as she passed through them, leaning on her nurse's arm, and attended by her father's confidential secretary and the old butler, they shed tears, and bade God bless her and prosper her in her pious design.</p>
<p>Lady Lucy arrived at Hampton Court, and was introduced into the Countess of Clarendon's apartment before her ladyship was out of bed ; and having told her artless tale with great earnestness, delivered her father's letter.</p>
<p>Lady Clarendon, who was wife to the queen's uncle, received her young god-daughter very affectionately, but plainly told her, she must not reckon on her influence with the queen, because the Earl of Clarendon was in disgrace on account of being suspected of carrying on a correspondence with King James, his brother-in-law; therefore she dared not solicit the queen on behalf of her friend Lord Preston, against whom her majesty was so deeply exasperated that she had declared she would not show him any mercy.</p>
<p><quote>"Oh!" said the little girl, "if I could only see the queen myself, I would not wish any one to speak for me, for I should plead so earnestly to her for my dear papa's life that she could not refuse me, I am sure."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"Poor child! what could you say to the queen?"</quote> asked the countess compassionately.</p>
<p><quote>"Only let me see her, and you shall hear,"</quote> said Lady Lucy.</p>
<p><quote>"Well, my love, it were a pity but what thou shouldst have an opportunity," said Lady Clarendon; "but much I fear thy little heart will fail thee, when thou seest the queen face to face, and thou wilt not be able to utter a syllable."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"God will inspire me with courage, and direct the words of my lips,"</quote> said the little girl, with tears in her eyes.</p>
<p>The countess was impressed with the piety and filial tenderness of her young god-daughter, and she hastened to rise and dress, that she might, without further delay, conduct the child into the palace gallery, where the queen usually passed an hour in walking, after her return from chapel, which she attended every morning.</p>
<p>Her majesty had not left the chapel when Lady Clarendon and Lucy entered the gallery, and her ladyship endeavoured to divert the anxious impatience of her little friend, by pointing out to her the portraits with which it was adorned.</p>
<p><quote>"I know that gentleman well,"</quote> said the child, pointing to a noble whole-length portrait of James the Second.</p>
<p><quote>"That is the portrait of the deposed King James, Queen Mary's father," observed the Countess, sighing, "and a very striking likeness it is of that unfortunate monarch;but hark! here comes the queen, with her chamberlain and ladies, from chapel,now, Lucy, is the time! I will step into the recess yonder; but you must remain alone standing where you are, and when her majesty approaches near enough, kneel down on one knee before her, and present your father's petition. She, who walks a little in advance of the other ladies, is the queen. Be of good courage, and address yourself to her."</quote></p>
<p>Lady Clarendon then made a hasty retreat. Lady Lucy's heart fluttered violently when she found herself alone, but her resolution did not fail her; and while her lips moved silently in fervent prayer to the Almighty for his assistance in this trying moment, she stood with folded hands, pale, but composed and motionless as a statue, awaiting the queen's approach; and when her majesty drew near the spot, she advanced a step forward, knelt, and presented the petition.</p>
<p>The extreme beauty of the child, her deep mourning, the touching sadness of her look and manner, and, above all, the fast flowing tears which bedewed her innocent face, excited the queen's attention and interest; she paused, spoke kindly to her, and took the offered paper; but when she saw the name of Lord Preston, her colour rose, she frowned, cast the petition from her, and would have passed on, but Lucy, who had watched her countenance with a degree of anxious interest that amounted to agony, losing all awe for royalty in her fears for her father's life, put forth her hand, and grasping the queen's robe, cried in an imploring tone, <quote>"Spare my father,my deardear father,royal lady!"</quote></p>
<p>Lucy had meant to say many persuasive things, but she forgot them all in her sore distress, and could only repeat the words, <quote>"Mercy, mercy for my father, gracious queen!"</quote> till her vehement emotion choked her voice, and throwing her arms round the queen's knees, she leaned her head against her majesty's person for support, while her rich profusion of flaxen ringlets, which partly concealed her fair face, floated over the queen's dress; she sobbed aloud in the uncontrolable anguish of her heart.</p>
<p>The intense sorrow of a child is always peculiarly touching; but the circumstances under which Lucy appeared were more than commonly affecting.</p>
<p>It was a daughter, not beyond the season of infancy, overcoming the timidity of that tender age, to become a suppliant of an offended sovereign for the life of a father.</p>
<p>Queen Mary pitied the distress of the young petitioner; but as she considered the death of Lord Preston a measure of political expediency, she told Lucy mildly, but firmly, that <quote>"she could not grant her request."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"And will you kill my dear papa, who is so good and kind to every one?"</quote> said Lucy, raising her blue eyes, which were swimming in tears, to the face of the queen.</p>
<p><quote>"He may be so, my child," returned her majesty, "but he has broken the laws of his country, and therefore he must die."</quote></p>
<p><quote>"But you can pardon him if you choose to do so, madam," replied Lucy; "and I have read that God is well pleased with those who forgive, for he has said, ' Blessed are the merciful, for they shall obtain mercy.'"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"It does not become a little girl like you to attempt to instruct me," replied the queen, gravely; "I am acquainted with my duty, and as it is my place to administer justice impartially, it is not possible for me to pardon your father, however painful it may be for me to deny the request of so dutiful a child."</quote></p>
<p>Lucy did not reply, she only raised her streaming eyes, with an appealing look to the queen, and then turned them expressively on the portrait of King James, opposite to which her majesty was standing.</p>
<p>There was something in that look which bore no ordinary meaning, and the queen, whose curiosity was excited by the peculiar manner of the child, could not refrain from asking her, <quote>"wherefore she gazed so earnestly on that picture?"</quote></p>
<p><quote>"I was thinking," replied Lady Lucy, "how strange it was that you should wish to kill my father, only because he loved yours so faithfully."</quote></p>
<p>This wise, but artless reproof, from the lips of infant innocence, went to the heart of the queen. She raised her eyes to the once dear and honoured countenance of a parent, who, whatever were his political errors as a king, had ever been the tenderest of fathers to her; and when the remembrance that he was an exile in a foreign land, relying on the bounty of strangers for his daily bread, while she and her husband were invested with the regal inheritance of which he had been deprived, pressed upon her mind, the thought of the contrast of her conduct as a daughter, when compared with the filial piety of the child before her (whom a sentence of hers was about to render an orphan), smote her heart, and she burst into tears.</p>
<p><quote>"Rise, dear child," said she. "Thou hast prevailedthy father shall not die. I grant his pardon at thy entreaty,thy filial love has saved him."</quote></p></tale>
<historical_summary>The conspiracy against the government of William the Third, and to effect the restoration of his exiled father-in-law, James the Second, for which Lord Preston and his friend, Mr. Ashton, were condemned to death, took place in 1692.
<p>Sir John Dalyrymple relates the anecdote of the courageous child of Lord Preston, in his Memoirs. Ashton was put to death, but the presence of mind of the young lady saved Lord Preston's life.</p>
<p>Her name was Catherine, and not Lucy. Her brother Edward dying young, she, with her two sisters, became her father's co-heiresses; at seventeen she married a gallant young nobleman, the son of Lord Widdrington, with whom she led a most happy life. Her memory is still greatly respected for her virtues and talents, in Lancashire, her native count v.</p></historical_summary></body>
</illustrious_children>